<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on the defence of the answer to a paper, intituled The case of the dissenting Protestants of Ireland, in reference to a bill of indulgence from the exceptions made against it together with an answer to a peaceable &amp; friendly address to the non-conformists written upon their desiring an act of toleration without the sacramental test.</title>
            <author>Mac Bride, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369472</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369472</idno>
            <idno type="VID">188013</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188013)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2852:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on the defence of the answer to a paper, intituled The case of the dissenting Protestants of Ireland, in reference to a bill of indulgence from the exceptions made against it together with an answer to a peaceable &amp; friendly address to the non-conformists written upon their desiring an act of toleration without the sacramental test.</title>
                  <author>Mac Bride, John.</author>
                  <author>Pullen, Tobias, 1648-1713. Defence of the ansvver to a paper intituled The case of the dissenting Protestants.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Belfast :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Mac Bride. Cf. Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:188013:1"/>
               <hi>Animadverſions</hi> ON The Defence of the Anſwer To a PAPER, INTITULED, <hi>The CASE of the Diſſenting Proteſtants of</hi> Ireland, <hi>In Reference to a</hi> BILL of Indulgence, <hi>from the Exceptions made against it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With An ANSWER to A Peaceable &amp; Friendly Addreſs TO THE <hi>Non-Conformiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written upon their deſiring an <hi>Act of Toleration</hi> without the <hi>SACRAMENTAL TEST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phil. 4. 5. <hi>Let your Moderation be known unto all men, the Lord is at hand.</hi> Printed in the the Year, 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:188013:2"/>
            <head>To the Proteſtant Reader.</head>
            <p>THe Publication of theſe Animadverſions, tho deſign'd ſome time ago, had ceas'd, if a late Pamphlet, called, <hi>A Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs, &amp;c.</hi> had not importun'd it. For ſeeing ſome men judge it their Intereſt to miſ-repreſent to the world them they'r pleas'd to call N. Conforming Brethren, as a factious and ſchiſmatical people, whereby we are miſ-apprehended and pre-condemn'd. We cannot in juſtice to Truth and Innocence, ſuffer ſuch ſo to prey upon the Credulity of ſome, and our Reputation, as thereby to hazard their Souls, and our Safety: Yea, compaſſion to our Adverſaries, in endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the prevention of their being wiſe in their own conceit, (a caſe more deſpcrate than that of Fools) obligeth us to vindicate our ſelves, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form miſ-guided people, with words of Truth and Soberneſs.</p>
            <p>The people we plead for, are not the Idle and Conſuming Caterpillars of the Nation, but Induſtrious Labourers, Ingenious Artiſts, and Honeſt Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: whoſe religious Principles will abide in their ſtrength, while one j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t or tittle of the Law of God indures: becaſe they adore the fulneſs of the H. Scriptures as the perfect and only rule of Faith and Manners. They believe the neceſſity of a ſtanding Goſpel-Miniſtry in the Church; to whoſe directive Authority they ſubmit themſelves; not by an implicit Faith, but by a judgment of Diſcretion. All God's holy Ordinances and inſtituted Worſhip they embrace, but their Fear towards God is not taught by the Commandments of men. Their doctrine bears conformity with that of the Reformed Churches abroad, and harmoniouſly agrees with that of <hi>Ireland</hi> declar'd in her Convocation, <hi>An. 1615,</hi> excepting in what relates to Prelacy and Ceremonies. They are willing to give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, and unto God what is God's. They profeſs their <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda, Petenda,</hi> and <hi>Agenda,</hi> ought all to be regulated by the word of God. Theſe Principles we believe are able to abide a Fiery Tryal.</p>
            <p>And as their Principles are true, ſo their Petitions are modeſt: Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Grandeur, Juriſdiction, or Revenues, is not demanded for their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or by them. A liberty to ſerve God according to theſe foreſaid Principles, with a relief from ſome Penal Laws formerly fram'd againſt them, and that no new ones be forg'd to their preiudice, is all they require. And if ſuch modeſt Requeſts may be with Chriſtian Conſcience deny'd a people of ſuch Principles, we leave to the determination of our Judge, that ſtandeth at the Door, if Men ſhould give ſentence againſt us.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:188013:2"/>
            <head>Animadverſions On the Defence of the Anſwer to a Paper, ENTITULED, The Caſe of the Diſſenting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in Ireland, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHen <hi>Diogenes</hi> trampled upon <hi>Aristippus</hi>'s Cuſhion, and inſulted over himſelf in theſe words; See how I trample on <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stippus</hi>'s Pride: he had this return; thou doſt it but with no leſs Pride: So when the Defendant of the Anſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſalutes the Vindicator of the Diſſenters Caſe, with a charge of ſourneſs, and vanity of temper. In the very entrance of his diſeourſe, he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſo much of the diſtemper in himſelf, that if Civility coult not, yet Conſcience of the ſame evil in himſelf, ſhould have oblig'd him to treat his Adverſary more decently: But whether the ſourneſs of his temper, or his vanity to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize an Iliad of Railing Accuſations in a Nut-ſhell, hath induc'd him, with one breath, to upbraid the Vindicator with <hi>ſourneſs, and vanity of temper, dexterity in perverting, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſincerity, diſing enuity, injuſtice, &amp;c.</hi> I determine not, but if his Reaſoning ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, be equivalent to his Railing, no Diſſenter will be able to ſtand before him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:188013:3"/>
Leſt he ſhou'd be ſuſpected of tranſgreſſing the <hi>9th</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, he attempts to make good this charge, by, as he calls it, <hi>A remarkable Inſtance of the Diſſenters injuſtice to him, viz. The phraſe, general Indulgence us'd by him (which,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>doth plainly ſignify no more than a legal toleration of Diſſenting Proteſtants);</hi> the Vindicator wreſts to import a comprehenſion of all ſorts of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this be Injuſtice, he hath cauſe to fear, that all who have ſenſe to diſcern words, will be injurious to him, ſeeing <hi>General Indulgence</hi> natively ſignifies, Indulgence to all ſorts of Perſons and Opinions: And 'tis improper to ſay, that General Indulgence imports only toleration of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters, which is but Special, unleſs Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentors ſhould comprehend all ſorts, which himſelf doth not aſſert.</p>
            <p>As the Vindicator hath not wreſted his Expreſſions, ſo neither hath he miſrepreſented his Senſe, ſeeing all the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he uſeth againſt the Indulgence pleaded for, militat only againſt an unlimited and general Indulgence of all ſorts.</p>
            <p>The next thing diſguſts the Defendant, is a rule laid down by the Vindicator, <hi>that theſe are of the ſame Religion with the Eſtabliſh't Church, who ſubſcribe her Doctriual Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles:</hi> this rule he'll not allow to be true; and that becauſe, <hi>there being three general parts of Religion, viz. Doctrin, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Government, unleſs we agree in all theſe, we are not of the ſame Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. If the Rule be not good, why do the Books of Articles in <hi>England, an.</hi> 1552, and 1562, and thoſe in <hi>Ireland</hi> in 1616, unanimouſly declare, <hi>that they were agreed upon in Convocation, for avoiding of diverſities of Opinions, and for Eſtabliſhing Conſent touching true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do not the Subſcribers to the <hi>6th</hi> Article, concerning the ſufficiency of holy Scripture for Salvation, ſubſcribe to the Worſhip and Government of the Church, as well as to its
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:188013:3"/>
Doctrin? if they do not, as the D. inſinuates, it muſt be becauſe <hi>that Worſhip and Doctrin is not read in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor may be proved thereby:</hi> which is no honor to the Liturgy, Ceremonies, or Prelacy.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Stillinfleet</hi> in his <hi>Irenicum</hi> hath endeavoured to prove that Men may be of the ſame Religion, and yet not under the ſame particular form of Church Government: And I am perſuaded 'twill be hard for the D. to produce any Church that is, or hath been in the world, with which the Eſtabliſht Church of <hi>England</hi> doth exactly agree in Form of Worſhip and Government. And thus by his Rule exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us from the ſame Religion with the Eſtabliſht Church, he doth alſo cut her off from Communion in the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with any Church in the World. The <hi>Anabaptists</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the D. excepts as unfit to be comprehended in the Indulgence, are of age, let them ſpeak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, we are none of their Advocates: Yet the V's. rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for including them, and his Charity alſo, was their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing included in the Act of Indulgence for <hi>England, An.</hi> 1689. And in a Bill prepared by the Council of <hi>Ireland</hi> in my Lord <hi>Sydneys</hi> Government, and approved by the <hi>K. Q.</hi> and council of <hi>England,</hi> and Re-tranſmitted to be Enacted by the Parliament here in 1692. But if the Reaſon of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction with them be only, their denying one of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal Articles, durſt he be ſo Impartial, he hath no leſs cauſe to look upon many of his Brethren, Fathers and Sons of the Church, as intolerable as the Anabaptiſts; for they are too truly ſuſpected to have no ſincere veneration for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Articles. And Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi> hath taught us concerning the 39 Articles, <hi>that the Church doth not define any of theſe Queſtions, as neceſſary to be believed either</hi> neceſſitate praecepti, <hi>or</hi> medii, <hi>nor doth look upon them as Eſſentials of Saving Faith, or Legacies of Chriſt, or his Apoſtles; but as pious Opinions, fitted for the preſervation of Vnity,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Stillingſt. Ratif. p. 54, 55.</note> 
               <hi>neither doth ſhe oblige any man to believe them, but not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:188013:4"/>
to contradict them.</hi> Whence we may ſee what great eſteem the great Prelates of the Church have for the 39 Articles: Seeing then (by ſuch) the Incarnation, Death and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt be not <hi>Eſſentials of Saving Faith, but only pious Opinions;</hi> why ſhould Anabaptiſts be look'd on as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable for denying Infant Baptiſm, when the Doctrin of Biptiſm is only a pious Opinion. We notice this, not in defence of Anabaptiſts, but to lay open the D's groſs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, who knowing how little regard many Sons of the Church have for theſe Articles, yet tacitly juſtifies them, when he condemns others for the ſame, or leſs faults. But for this, let him read Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Liberty of Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>p. m.</hi> 227.</p>
            <p>The V. aſſerted, that the Bill pleaded for by the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, would multiply no other Sects, than thoſe mention'd in it, and tolerated by it; which the D. tells, <hi>hath little ſhew of Reaſon to recommend it; and that becauſe ſuch a Toleration may occaſion the Riſe and Increaſe of many others not pleaded for.</hi> To confirm which, he inſtanceth <hi>Holland, where in few years the Anabaptiſts ſpawned 50 Sects all under the ſame name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Reaſon giv'n to diſprove the V's Aſſertion, hath as little ſubſtance of Reaſon to recommend it, as the V. had ſhew; for what if Toleration to ſome Proteſtant Diſſenters ſhou'd occaſion the Riſe of other Sects, muſt it be therefore unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to tolerate them: By this way of arguing, we might prove the Reformation from Popery, yea, Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf Intolerable; becauſe they occaſion'd the Riſe of many Sects, and moſt bloody Perſecutions, tho they were not the proper cauſes of theſe Evils: even ſo, the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting two or three can never be the cauſe of multiplying more, if no other be tolerated ſave thoſe two or three: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Inſtance of <hi>Holland</hi> is diſingenuouſly offered; for he knows the Toleration there granted, is nothing like what's here deſired, ſeeing there are comprehended all ſorts, Jews, Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore all multiply where they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:188013:4"/>
are equally tolerated, but here only three are preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>But again, his Inference with its Reaſon, are neither fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not prudently produced; his Inference is, <hi>That perſons in Authority ſhould deny an unlimited and irreſtricted Indulgence to Presbyterians and Independents:</hi> his Reaſon is, <hi>leſt the general and legal Allowance granted, ſhould be productive of many Sects, which, tho different from each other, ſhould diſire to be called by their names, to take away their reproach, and that they might enjoy the benefit of the publick Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This Inference unjuſtly inſinuate, that on unlimited Toleration is deſired, when, as in matters of Religion, we are ſatisfy'd to be limited by the Law of God: In matters Civil, by the Law of the Land. The imprudence of his Reaſon is, that it militats as much againſt a legal Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a legal Toleration, and more; for Experience reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, that many deſire the Ruler's favour, and to be called by the name of the Eſtabliſhed Church, and ſhrowd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under her cover, both to take away their reproach, and alſo to ſhare of the Honour, Riſe, and plentiful provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion allow'd the Sons of the Church.</p>
            <p>The <hi>D.</hi> being diſſatisfy'd with the V's weakneſs, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to apprehend the miſchievous conſequences of this legal Toleration, notwithſtanding all he had ſaid, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of him, <hi>that he had propounded ſeveral Queſtions to little purpoſe;</hi> among which, he inſtanceth one, <hi>viz. Whether the Popiſh Intereſt will be ever the ſtronger, becauſe there are more Proteſtants to oppoſe it, and becauſe their mutual forbearance will more unite their endeavors againſt the common Enemy.</hi> ſo this the <hi>D.</hi> anſwereth; <hi>1ſt. That tho the Popiſh intereſt will be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly weak, and by the increaſe of Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ants of the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, yet it will be conſiderably ſtrengthned by the multiplicity of Sects, which Legal Indulgence generally promotes. 2d. That Diſſenters on the grant of Legal indulgence will grow far more inſolent and tumultucus than they were before, as hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in a Neighbour Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:188013:5"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> To his firſt 'tis plain that the increaſe of Proteſtants, tho' not of the ſame Communion, doth, not conſiderably ſtrengthen, but weaken the Popiſh Intereſt, for hath not the Increaſe of Proteſtants in <hi>Germany, France, Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince 1691, particularly in the <hi>North,</hi> tho' of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Communion, conſiderably weaked the Popiſh Intereſt? Much more would the greater increaſe of the number of Proteſtants here in <hi>Ireland,</hi> weaken them in their Civil, and conſequently in the defence and maintenance of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Intereſts, were they encouraged by a legal Indulgence: And 'tis too well known to be with modeſty denied, that the Popiſh Intereſt here hath been, and yet is weakened by other hands than thoſe of the Eſtabliſhed Church only, for he and all may know how formidable <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> appeared to <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> and his Party in Winter 1688, and how undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly it reſiſted and foiled King <hi>James</hi>'s Army, and Reinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Duke <hi>Sconberg's.</hi> And he, and every Man of ſence knows the far greater Number there are Diſſenters; for the truth whereof we vouch Bp. <hi>King</hi> for 30000 in his Dioceſs, and leaves him in his next to publiſh their Numbers in his own and Neighbouring Dioceſſes.</p>
            <p>But bleſs't be God we are not divided in defending the Britiſh and Proteſtant Intereſt againſt a Popiſh Iriſh Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; And I hope as the many Parties of different Religions and Intereſt now confederate againſt <hi>France,</hi> do conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly weaken that King, while they unite all in one to make him juſt and peaceable; ſo will we the Proteſtants of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt our common Enemy; for the Union of many Parties Syncretizing againſt a common Foe, is not that which ſtrengthens the Adverſary, but when theſe ſeveral Parties divide in heart and hand by mutual conflict, that impedes their joining for the common good, which is the native Fruit of one prevailing Party's perſecuting the reſt: And this the Papiſts labour to effectuat, whoſe drudgery he and his Brethren do with all their might, while they daily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:188013:5"/>
labour to keep us off and at under, with this ſilly ſhift of bending the Knee in the Euchariſt, which came in with Popery, they call indifferent, and well know we will not do contrary to our Conſcience; while they do not try us with the Doctrinal Articles for a Teſt; let all Wiſe Men judge of this Policy and Religion.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Obſervation of <hi>Diſſenters growing much more tumultuous ſince the Legal Indulgence hath been granted them,</hi> I apprehend hath been made by the D. in his Dream, ariſing from frightful Ideas he hath of the Diſſenters; for ſure ſince the commencement of a Legal Indulgence in 1689. no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Diſſenters Tumults can be produc'd: Tho' we can inſtance Bloody Tumults, Rebellions and Conſpiracies againſt the King and Government, carried on by thoſe who call themſelves the Sons of the Church, both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> in which no Presbyterian hath been concern'd.</p>
            <p>The V. having deſired to know from the D. wherein a Toleration to Diſſenting Proteſtants will advance the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> he promiſeth to give a full and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſatisfaction in this matter: And <hi>1ſt. He deſires him ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to conſider whether there be not violent preſumption, that a publick Legal Indulgence to Proteſtants, doth not highly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Popiſh Intereſt; ſince all Romiſh Emiſſaries ſo eagerly deſire, and induſtriouſly promote Tolerations, tho limited to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters; and when all other meaſures fail'd, have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily expended conſiderable Summs of Money to purchaſe them; And it is generally known that the Declaration</hi> A. 1671/2. <hi>was of the Papiſts procuring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If this Declaration was not granted in favor of the Diſſenters in <hi>Ireland</hi> (as he knows it was not) his Anſwer can't ſatisfy the V's demand, who would only know, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Toleration to Diſſenters in <hi>Ireland</hi> wou'd advance the Popiſh Intereſt here: but the Declaration he ſpeaks of, ſeems to be that emitted in <hi>England, A.</hi> 1691/2, and then he moſt diſingenuouſly repreſents the matter, for it was procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:188013:6"/>
by an Exigence of State Affairs; <hi>England</hi> then being engaged in a War againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> it was thought unſafe to perſecute ſo numerous and wealthy a part of the Nation as Proteſtant Diſſenters then were, and in the interim to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on a War againſt their Friends abroad; therefore to keep matters at home as quiet as poſſible, a Declaration for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence was Publiſhed, but ſo far from limiting the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to Proteſtant Diſſenters, that Popiſh Recuſants had apparently the greateſt ſhare in that Liberty, which ſo much diſguſted the Nation, that the King was neceſſitated to make Apology for it; as appears by his Speech to the Parliament, <hi>Feb. 5. An. 1672.</hi> In which he ſaith, <hi>I put forth my Declaration for Indulgence to Diſſenters, and have hitherto found the good effect of it. There is one part that is ſubject to miſ-construction, which is that concerning the Papiſts, as if more liberty were granted to them, than to other Recuſants; when it is plain there is leſs: I do not intend to prejudice the Church, but will ſupport its Religion in its full Power; having ſaid, I ſhall take it very ill to receive Contradiction in what I have done, and I will deal plainly with you, I am Reſolved to ſtick to my Declaration.</hi> The Lord Chancellor alſo ſpake the ſame thing, <hi>viz. His Majeſty hath ſo fully Vindicated his Declaration from that Calumny, concerning the Papiſts, that no reaſonable ſcruple can be made againſt it, by any good Man, he hath ſufficiently juſtify'd it, by the time it was Publiſhed in the Effects he hath had from it, and might have done it more from the agreeableneſs of it to his own natural Diſpoſition, which no good Engliſh-man could wiſh other ways than it is: he loves not blood nor rigorous ſeverities, but where mild and gentle me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods may be uſed by a Prince, he is certain to chuſe them:</hi> and concludes that head thus; <hi>But His Majeſty is not convinced that violent Ways are the Intereſt of Religion, or the Church.</hi> By this we may ſee if the D. doth not Rival the V. in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (as he ſaith of him) things in a falſe light, for what can be leſs candid than this Repreſentation of that matter:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:188013:6"/>
Seeing, 1. There was no legal Toleration, but a Liberty granted by a Declaration, which is queſtionable, whether Law, or not. 2. Nor was it limitted to Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters only, but included alſo Papiſts. Nor, <hi>3dly.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by mony. By this we may ſee the mercileſs diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of ſome Church-Men, who firſt extort from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate Rigorous Laws, and then reproach Diſſenters for diſloyalty in not obeying them, which they have ſqueezed from the Magiſtrate, contrary to his Inclination and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <p>The D's ſecond Argument to prove that the free exerciſe of Proteſtant Religion, according to different Modes, will advance the Popiſh Intereſt here, is drawn from his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; for, ſaith he, <hi>when Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> or (as he calls them) <hi>pretended Protestants have been Legally Indulged, it hath been experimentally found, that Popiſh Emiſſaries were more numerous, their Application greater, and Harveſt more plenteous than at other times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If the D. had as ſincerely intended, as he vainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ample ſatisfaction in this point, he would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanc'd the time when, and place where, a legal Indulgence granted to Proteſtant Diſſenters produc'd that effect: for tho he values his own teſtimony as demonſtration, others do not; for it appears not that this fell out in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s, K. <hi>James</hi>'s, or K. <hi>Charle's 1ſt.</hi> time; it then muſt be either in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s time, as by the date of Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s Letter in 1659 (which he cites) would appear: but then the Papiſts do not glory in their Harveſt here, unleſs it was, that many of them were cut down at the ſame rate, being ſet on a Prieſt's Head in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as on a Wolf, which occaſion'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries to be never leſs numerous than then; or after the Reſtauration of K <hi>C. 2d.</hi> during whoſe Reign, Diſſenters had no Legal Indulgence here, tho we confeſs the application of Papiſts was ſtrong, the Harveſt plentiful, and Emiſſaries nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous; or for King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>2d</hi>'s time, in which, no ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:188013:7"/>
Toleration, limited to Diſſenters, was thought on: The charge then muſt lye on K. <hi>W.</hi> and Q. <hi>M.</hi> ſince 1689. but then his experience will be found falſe: for neither (we bleſs God for it) are Popiſh Emiſſaries ſo numerous as in former times have been, nor their harveſt ſo plentiful; nay, we have found it experimentally, that when Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters has been violently Perſecuted, Popiſh Emiſſaries has been moſt warmly Entertain'd; for when Diſſenters in the <hi>North</hi> of this Kingdom were forced in the beginning of K. <hi>C.</hi> I's. Reign to undertake a troubleſome Voyage to <hi>America,</hi> there to ſhelter themſelves from Perſecution (tho' providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially driven back) then a Toleration for <hi>Papiſts</hi> here was granted.</p>
            <p>Concerning Bp. <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s Letter to Primate <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to prove his experience <hi>Anno</hi> 1659. in which 'tis ſaid, <hi>that ſeveral of the Popiſh Clergy of</hi> France <hi>were taught manual Trades to qualify them as Emiſſaries to foment diviſions in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> A few Inſtances given of theſe mechanick Prieſt-Miſſionaries that came into <hi>England,</hi> would prove the truth of that Letter better, which will be ſuſpected till then, by all that conſider how hard it would be to perſwade lazy Prieſts to undergo the long fatigue of learning Handycrafts, which would do them little ſervice without the language of the Land: And they who know the ſtrict ſcrutiny made by Presbyterians and Independants e're they admit any as members of their Congregations, or Miniſters, will be more affraid that ſuch ſhould thruſt themſelves in the Eſtabliſh'd Churches than ours.</p>
            <p>His <hi>3d.</hi> Argument to prove that Toleration to Diſſenting Proteſtants will increaſe Popery, is, <hi>becauſe 'tis the cauſe of our Diviſions; whereof the Papiſts take great advantage.</hi> For proof whereof, he cites Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That Papiſts, and all other Adverſaries, make their advantage by our Diviſions, is ſeen and bewailed by all good men with Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> but that our mutual forbearance of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:188013:7"/>
one another in matters not neceſſary to Salvation, was ever the cauſe of diviſions, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath nor taught, but the contrary: Yet if he deſire an account of the true cauſes of our diviſions, he may learn them from one of the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> the memorable Mr. <hi>John Hales</hi> of <hi>Eaton,</hi> in his Tract of Schiſm, <hi>page</hi> 201. <q>Who teacheth us, that all Schiſms have crept into the Church by one of theſe three ways; <hi>(1st.)</hi> Upon matter of Fact; <hi>(2d.)</hi> Upon matter of Opinion; <hi>(3d.)</hi> On point of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Ambition: I call that matter of Fact, when ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is required to be done by us which we know, or ſtrongly ſuſpect to be unlawful: So the firſt notable Schiſm of which we read in the Church, contained in it matter of Fact; for it being upon Error taken for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that an <hi>Eaſter</hi> muſt be kept; and upon worſe than Error, if I may ſo ſpeak, (for it was no leſs than a point of Judaiſm forc'd upon the Church) upon worſe than Error I ſay, thought further neceſſary, that the ground for the time of keeping that Feaſt, muſt be the Rule left by <hi>Moſes</hi> unto the Jews: There aroſe a ſtout Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we were to celebrate with the Jews on the <hi>14th</hi> of the Moon, or on the Sunday following. This matter, tho moſt unneceſſary, moſt vain, yet caus'd as great a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion as ever was in the Church: the firſt ſeparating, and refuſing Communion with the laſt for many years together. In this phantaſtical hurry, I cannot ſee but that all the world were Schiſmaticks; neither can any thing excuſe them from that Imputation, excepting only this, that we charitably ſuppoſe, that all Parties out of Conſcience did what they did; a thing which befell them through the Ignorance of their Guides, (for I will not ſay their Malice) and that through the juſt judgment of God, becauſe through Sloath and blind Obedience men examin'd not the things which they were taught, but like Beaſts of burthen, patiently couched down, and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:188013:8"/>
underwent whatſoever their Superiors laid upon them. Further, <hi>page</hi> 210. For in theſe Schiſms which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Fact, nothing can be a juſt cauſe of refuſal of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but only to require the execution of ſome unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſuſpected Act: for not only in Reaſon, but Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion too, that Maxim admits of no Releaſe; <hi>Cautiſſimi cujuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praeceptum, quod dubtias, ne feceris.</hi> And ſpeaking of the ſecond Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> where Image-worſhip was eſtabliſhed, where was the firſt remarkable Schiſm upon juſt occaſion of Fact; he tells us, <hi>The ſchiſmatical Party was the Synod it ſelf, and ſuch as conſpir'd with it;</hi> for concerning the uſe of Images in <hi>Sacris.</hi> 1. It is acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all, that it is not a thing neceſſary. 2. It is by moſt ſuſpected. 3. It is by many held utterly unlawful. Can then the injoyning the practice of ſuch a thing be ought elſe but abuſe; or can the refuſal of Communion here, be thought any other thing than duty here, or upon the like occaſion to ſeparate, may peradventure bring perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal trouble and danger; (againſt which, it concerns eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honeſt man to have <hi>pectus bene preparatum)</hi> ſo that in theſe caſes you cannot be to ſeek what you think, or what you have to do.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>2d</hi> ſort of Schiſm ariſing upon occaſion of variety of Opinion, is thus: <q>It hath been, ſaith he, the common diſeaſe of Chriſtians from the beginning, not to content themſelves with that meaſure of Faith, which God in Scripture hath expreſly afforded us; but out of a vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know more than is revealed, they have attempted to diſcuſs things of which they can have no light, neither from Reaſon nor Revelation; neither have they reſted here, but upon pretence of Church Authority, which is none; or Tradition, which is for the moſt part but fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they have peremptorily concluded, and confidently impos'd on others a neceſſity of entertaining concluſions of that nature, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After he tells, were Liturgies, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:188013:8"/>
publick Forms of Service, ſo framed, as that they admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of no particular and private Fancies, but contained only ſuch things, as in which all Chriſtians do agree: Schiſms in opinions were utterly Vaniſhed; for conſider all the Liturgies that are, or have been, and remove from them whatſoever is Scandalous to any Party, and leave nothing but what all agree in, and the event ſhall be, that the publick Service and Honour of God ſhall no ways ſuffer, whereas to load our Publick Forms with the private fancies upon which we differ, is the moſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign way to perpetuate Schiſm unto the Worlds End. Prayer, Confeſſion, Thankſgiving, Reading of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Expoſition of Scripture, Adminiſtration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the plaineſt and ſimpleſt manner, were matters enough to furniſh out a ſufficient Liturgy, tho' nothing either of private Opinion, or of Church Pomp, of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of preſcribed Geſtures, of Imagery, of Muſick, of matter concerning the Dead, of many ſuperfluities which creep into the Churches, under the Dream of Order and Decency did interpoſe it ſelf: For to charge Churches and Liturgies with things unneceſſary, was the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all Superſtition: and when ſcruple of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence began to be made or pretended, then Schiſm begun to break in: If the ſpiritual Guides and Fathers of the Church would be a little ſparing of incumbring the Churches with ſuperfluities, and not over-rigid, either in receiving abſolute Cuſtoms, or impoſing New, there were far leſs danger of Schiſm, or Superſtition, and the inconveniency were likely to iſſue, would be but this, they ſhould in ſo doing yield a little to the imbecillities of Inferiors; a thing which St. <hi>Paul</hi> could never have refuſed to do; in the mean while, where ever falſe and ſuſpected Opinions are made a piece of the Churches Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, he that ſeparates is not Sciſmatick; for it's alike unlawful to make profeſſion of known and ſuſpected
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:188013:9"/>
falſehoods, as to put in practice unlawful and ſuſpected Actions.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The third Cauſe of Schiſm is Epiſcopal Ambition, <hi>p.</hi> 218, ſaith he, <q>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us, that neceſſity cauſeth but ſmall Faults, but Avarice and Ambition are Mothers of great Crimes: Epiſcopal Ambition hath made this true, for no occaſion hath produc'd more continuing and more ſanguinary Schiſms, than this hath done; the Sees of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and above all of <hi>Rome</hi> do abundantly ſhew this much, and our Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Stories Witneſs no leſs of which the greateſt part conſiſts in factionating, and tumultuating of Great and Potent Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This Epiſcopal Ambition ſhewed it ſelf eſpecially in two Heads, one concerning plurality of Biſhops in one See, another the Superiority of Biſhops in divers Sees: As to the firſt he tells us, That the general Practice of the Church ſince the Original of Epiſcopacy as now it is, was never to admit at once, more than one Biſhop in one See, and to prevent Spiritual Polygamy, neither would they admit of two Cathedrals, but from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it was not ſo; for even at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Hippo</hi> there were two Biſhops at one time; neither doth it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Vice, or Miſdemeanour, that it ſhould be ſo ſtill, their Puniſhment ſleeps not, who go about unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily and wantonly to infringe it: But the other head of Epiſcopal Ambition, concerning Supremacy of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in divers Sees, one claiming Superiority over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it hath been from time to time, a great Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſer againſt the Churches Peace, ſo it is now the final Ruin of it, the Eaſt and Weſt through the fury of the two prime Biſhops, being irremediably ſeparated, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all hope of Reconcilement; and beſide, all this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is founded on a Vice contrary to all Chriſtian Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, without which no Man ſhall ſee his Saviour, for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:188013:9"/>
they do but abuſe themſelves and others, that would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, that Biſhops, by Chriſt's Inſtitution, have any Superiority over other men, further than that of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; or that any Biſhop is Superior to another, further than poſitive Order agreed upon amongſt Chriſtians hath preſcrib'd: for we have believed him that hath told us, that in Jeſus Chriſt there is neither high n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r low, and that in giving honour, every man ſhould be ready to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer another before himſelf: which ſayings cut off all claim moſt certainly to Superiority, by title of Chriſtianity; except men can think that theſe things were only ſpoken to poor and private men. Nature and Religion agree in this, that neither of them have a hand in this heraldry of <hi>ſecundum, ſub &amp; ſupra;</hi> all this comes from compoſition, and agreement of men among themſelves: wherefore this abuſe of Chriſtianity, to make it lacquy to ambition, is a vice for which we have no ordinary name, and an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary one we will not give it; leſt you ſhould take ſo tranſcendent a vice for a trivial: Thus the Memorable</q> Mr. <hi>Jo. Hales.</hi> And would to God all would conſider his words moſt ſeriouſly, by which we may ſee what are the true cauſes of Schiſm, and who are the Schiſmaticks. Whence alſo it will appear that a publick Indulgence to weaker Brethren, in matters not neceſſary, and ſuſpected to be unlawful, is no cauſe of Diviſions; but on the contrary, an ambitious claim of Superiority, impoſing private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and commanding ſuſpected Practices, are the true cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them, and ever will be.</p>
            <p>The D's <hi>4th</hi> Argument againſt Publick Indulgence is, <hi>That they have not only fatally conduced to the perverting a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of Proteſtants, but alſo effectually hindred the converſion of many Papiſts, who tho ſenſible of many groſs Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Principles and ungodly Practices in the Worſhip enjoyn'd them by</hi> Rome; <hi>yet have been ſo highly ſcandalized by the Diviſions amongſt us, that they have rather choſen to continue in them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:188013:10"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Had not the D. truſted more to the Rhetorick than Logick of this Argument, he had conceal'd it; being a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſm, as they call it, of <hi>non cauſa, pro cauſa,</hi> and is no ſtronger than this; the legal eſtabliſhment of one of the divided parties, perverts many, and hindreth the converſion of Papiſts, becauſe they are ſcandalized at our Diviſions; for a legal toleration of ſome, is not the cauſe, but conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of our Diviſions, ſeeing Diviſions muſt be before the neceſſity of a Toleration to the Parties divided. <hi>2dly.</hi> If our Diviſions ſcandalize the Papiſts, as I am perſwaded they do; he may enquire at the Memorable Mr. <hi>John Halos,</hi> who are the Dividers, and to whom the Woe is due, that belongs to ſuch as cauſe Offences. <hi>3dly.</hi> Such Papiſts as are ſenſible of groſs Errors in Principles and ungodly Practices in the Worſhip enjoyned them, and yet continue in them, would have had the ſame object on againſt Chriſtianity it ſelf, had they lived in <hi>Corinth</hi> in the days of the Apoſtles, for then were Diviſions: nor do I ſee what loſs the Church ſuſtains by want of ſuch Converts, as can live, for Union's ſake, in groſs Errors, and ungodly Practices, whereof they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced: And why Diviſion ſhould terrify them from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, I ſee not, ſeeing if they will be converted to us, they muſt divide from <hi>Rome. 4thly.</hi> But what if the rigid ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the domineering party of Proteſtants againſt all who differ from them, be the cauſe of Offence? Sure Intelligent Papiſts are not ignorant of the Diviſions among themſelves, but neither Party being permitted to bite and devour each other, except by Pen and Ink, they glory in their Union, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe Diviſions Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Letter to Mr. <hi>Laud</hi> (afterward Archbiſhop <hi>Laud)</hi> expoſtulating with him about his unſettledneſs in Religion, hanging betwixt the Romaniſts and Proteſtants, upon the account of our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, tells him, <q>Whither will ye go for Truth, if ye will allow no truth but where there is no Diviſion? To <hi>Rome</hi> perhaps, famous for Unity, famous for Peace: See now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:188013:10"/>
how happily ye have choſen, how well have you ſped,</q> So their Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> himſelf, a Witneſs above excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, under his own hand, acknowledgeth to the world: <q>and reckons up 237 contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> of Doctrin amongſt the Romiſh Divines; no, they are no more peaceable, but</q> more ſubtil, they fight more cloſely, within doors; all our frays are in the Frield, our ſtrite is in Ceremony, theirs is in Subſtance; ſo the <hi>Decad,</hi> 3 Ep. 5.</p>
            <p>The <hi>D's 5th</hi> Argument to prove that this legal liberty to Proteſtant Diſſenters will advance the Popiſh Intereſt, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the different ſtate of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Swedland,</hi> from that of the United Provinces, in reference to the numbers of Papiſts in theſe Countreys: <hi>For as the ſtrictneſs of the Laws againſt thoſe who differ from theſe Establiſhed Churches hath been remarkably effectual for the rooting out of Popery from amongſt them, ſo the unlimited Toleration granted in</hi> Holland <hi>to all ſorts of Religions, hath multiplied the Papiſts there, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As the ſtrictneſs of the Laws in <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> are remarkable for rooting out Popery, ſo are they for rooting out all Proteſtants, ſave Lutherans: And if their ſtrictneſs be their perfection; we can tell him of more perfect Laws, <hi>viz.</hi> the Laws of the Holy Inquiſition, which are as ſoveraign prophylactick for the Eſtabliſhed Churches of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> as theſe of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> are; ſo that he may thus recommend Lords In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors to the Parliament to be authorized, as Guardian Angels to the Clergy of <hi>Ireland. 2dly.</hi> It is not want of ſtrict Laws againſt Popery that hath preſerved them in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but the not imploying the Laws made againſt them; and miſ-imploying them againſt the diſſenting Proteſtants. <hi>3dly.</hi> His comparing the ſtate of the United Provinces with that of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> to the deſired Toleration, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; ſeeing we plead for no Toleration to Papiſts, as is granted in <hi>Holland.</hi> That the rectricting the Indulgence to thoſe pleaded for by the <hi>V.</hi> will not prevent the advancement
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:188013:11"/>
of the Popiſh Intereſt here, as he ſaith, ſeemeth ſtrange; for if the Law granting liberty to two or three Parties, excluding all others ruined, prevent the creeping in of Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits amongſt us; how can tho Law Eſtabliſhing the Church, prevent the like among them? For if the evil be prevented by virtue of the Law, it may have the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to preſerve both; yea, Experience teacheth us, that it's eaſier to preſerve from being infected by ſuch Vermin the poor and depreſſed Party, than the proſperous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted: Few play the Hypocrite, to be thereby made miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable; tho many may, and daily do, for Profit and Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>His <hi>6th</hi> Argument againſt this legal Toleration is, <hi>that in ſtead of widening the Baſis of the Proteſtant intereſt, as is alledged by the V. this Indulgence would undeniably weaken the foundation of the Proteſtant Security in this Kingdom, becauſe each tolerated Party will rather induſtriouſly promote their own diſtinct Intereſt, than unanimouſly oppoſe the common Enemy, as Experience hath taught us:</hi> And to make good his Aſſertion, he inſtanceth the caſe of the Famous Mr. <hi>Houſton</hi> in the North of this Kingdom,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If the Defendant would allow the Diſſenters to be Proteſtants, to which they pretend as good title as the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church, ſeeing they proteſt againſt Popery as much as they, then the increaſing of their numbers would infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly increaſe the number of Proteſtants, and ſo both widen and ſtrengthen the Baſis of Proteſtant Intereſt: But if he will monopolize the name of Proteſtant to the Eſtabliſh't Church, and by the foundation of its Security underſtand Penal Laws againſt the Diſſenters; tho the Indulgence might ruine that Foundation, the Church might ſtand, and be better ſecured by its Innocency and Affection of its Neighbours, than by its own guilt, and their enmity; but it's ſtrange he ſhould aſſert that experience hath ſufficiently taught us, that each tolerated Party will rather diſtinctly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:188013:11"/>
promote their own Intereſt, than unanimouſly oppoſe the common Enemy, when the experience of the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion knows the truth of the contrary, that we maintained no ſeparated Intereſt from the common; for as our Civil In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts are imbarked in the common, ſo we cannot deſert rhe one, without deſtroying the other: no more can we maintain our Religious Intereſt either without oppoſition to the Popiſh in <hi>Ireland:</hi> His Inſtance to prove his Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, is as ridiculous as Mr. <hi>Houſton</hi> himſelf, who, as he ſays, <hi>ſcandalouſly ſeparated from the main body of the Proteſtants in the North of</hi> Ireland; <hi>and had not extraordinary Providence intervened, the Inteſtine Animoſities of theſe ſeeming Friends had been of more miſchievous conſequence, than the open hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our profeſſed Enemies: And the Diviſions which theſe few pretended Proteſtants endeavoured to foment, were really more formidable than the united Force and Power of a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Popiſh Army, and had been more fatal to our common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All who know the truth of that Inſtance of Mr. <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> and his riſe and retinue in the Dioceſs of <hi>Connor,</hi> which many thouſands were witneſs to, will ridioule him for its motion; for that man being Irregular, was ſuſpended and depos'd by the Presbyterians, and had only a few ſilly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people to adhere to him; and when the whole North arrayed, he alſo ranged his company to oppoſe the common Enemy; ſo that this diſcovers the folly and unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>D.</hi> in making uſe of it: for it ſeemeth ſtrange, that about 200 men, his compliment, without Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, or Order, ſhould be more formidable than the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted force and power of the numerous well-appointed Popiſh Army: nor did any in the North fear thoſe miſchievous conſequences he talks of; for by a prudent neglect of that man, and his ſilly Followers, we have lived to ſee them va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh into Smoke: we know not what that extraordinary Providence was, that prevented theſe fearful miſohiefs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:188013:12"/>
it be the Iriſh prevailing to ſcatter unprovided men; and it would appear, that the <hi>D.</hi> was not very apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the miſchiefs of the open hoſtilities of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Enemies, when he is more terrified with the thoughts of Mr. <hi>Houſton</hi>'s company, who had little formidable in it, except the Motto of his Bannar: poſſibly a ſecond 1641 would not have been ſo miſchievous in its conſequence (in his opinion) as the Diviſions of theſe two parties of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, whereby he diſcovers either little fear of Iriſh Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility, or too much of the ill conſequences of Diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>The <hi>D.</hi> ſuſpecting that all he had ſaid might be of little weight with the <hi>V.</hi> attacks him with the judgment of a Proteſtant Parliament, who in <hi>Feb.</hi> 25. 1662 in an Addreſs to King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> ſay; <q>We have conſidered the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Indulgence propoſed, with reference to theſe conſequences, which muſt neceſſary attend it; It will eſtabliſh Schiſm by a Law, and make the whole Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church precarious, and the cenſures of it of no moment or conſideration at all: It will be a cauſe of increaſing of Sects and Sectaries, whoſe numbers will weaken the true Proteſtant Profeſſion ſo far, that it will be at laſt difficult to defend it ſelf againſt them; and, which is yet further conſiderable, theſe numbers, which by being troubleſome to the Government, find they can arrive to an Indulgence, will, as their numbers increaſe, be yet more troubleſome, that at length they may arrive to a general Toleration, and in time ſome prevalent Sect will at laſt contend for Eſtabliſhment; which, for ought can be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, may end in Popery.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To this I ſhall return him the words of a moderate and learned Conformiſt in his Plea for the Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, <hi>Plea 2. pag. 39.</hi> Who ſaith, <q>That the Houſe of Commons, <hi>A.</hi> 1662. did argue againſt Indulgence, and for keeping up the Act of the Uniformity by way of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:188013:12"/>
prophecy and fore-ſight of conſequences; and their humble advices to the King contain the ſtrongeſt reaſons againſt an Indulgence, that have been found out, contain the great evils of a forbearance; all which he reduceth to ſix Heads, but anſwers to them all thus: As Events prove Prophecies true or falſe, ſo Events have proved theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments weak or ſtrong. That very Parliament, the true Proteſtant part of it, that did faithfully ſerve their King and Countrey, with the additions made to them by a latter Election, to fill up vacant places, ſaw where they were, and became ſenſible of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Uniting Proteſtants by Act of Parliament. And many Epiſcopal Divines, and ſome Biſhops were for it; a clear diſcovery, that the miſchiefs of our Diviſions are of that ſort, that it were better that an abatement were made of ſome things made neceſſary to Uniformity, without which the Diſſenters will not unite, than ſuffer them to hang over our heads, and come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; we plainly ſee that many of theſe reaſons of the Commons were of no force; we will obſerve what is of preſent uſe to our times, which is the firſt; and for the other, it became their Wiſdom, and Religion, to Paſs a Bill taking from the Act of Uniformity; his Majeſty hath not been moleſted by the Importunities of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, who have not ſo much as opened their Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Petitioned the King and Parliament theſe many years. There is no new Sect appearing, or increaſe of any by the Non-conformiſts, to weaken the Proteſtant Religion, who have us'd endeavours to Increaſe and Maintain it, it is is in no danger from them, they are not troubleſome to the Government, are not for a Toleration of intolerable Sects and Sectaries, contend not for an Eſtabliſhment which they would rejoyce in, but as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come learned men, and rational, with as great a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per at leaſt as theirs that writ againſt them, the Peace of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:188013:13"/>
the Nation is not diſturb'd by them, and if Popery come in, it is againſt their wills, Pains and Prayers to expoſe and baffle it: It is their trouble that they are thought troubleſome to the Government, which may by no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary exerciſe of Patience, and Love, overcome the trouble in their own Breaſt, which is the ſeat of trouble; and for the only remaining, which is the evil of Schiſm, it's clear, that Connivance gives no Eſtabliſhment to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But ſeeing the <hi>D.</hi> is ſo confident of the Authority of the Commons in that Parliament, and lays ſo much ſtreſs upon it, we hope he will not decline the Authority of the whole, when the Experience of Ten Years had made them wiſer, for p. 22. our Author tells, what <hi>England</hi> knows, <q>That that very Parliament which was obſerved for a great part of it, to be young Gentlemen growing Elder became more cool and moderate toward Diſſenting Proteſtants, more ſuſpicious of Popery, and the more Reſolute they grew in Maintaining Property, and the Proteſtant Religion, and break the leggs and arms of growing Popery, the more temperate they grew toward Nonconformiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore at that meeting of the Parliament in <hi>Feb.</hi> 24. 1672. An Act paſſed againſt Papiſts; and a Bill was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the ſame Houſe of Commons to the Lords in favour of the Diſſenting, and for Uniting Proteſtants, which, as ſome, who have as much reaſon to know, as any that write, ſay, would have paſſed, if they had got time to ſit, and from that time, that Long Parliament, who had made the Act againſt Conventicles, A. 1670. how Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſoever they were againſt Indulgence, <hi>Feb.</hi> 15. 1662. they ſaw the incompatibility of the Execution of their own Law, and the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and have ever ſince taken other Meaſures. Now</q> whether or not the ſame Parliament, after ten years Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the weakneſs, and ſome worſe evils of their own
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:188013:13"/>
Prophetical Arguments, upon which they retract their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sentence, is to be more regarded, than when they gave their firſt unexperienced thoughts, we ſhall leave all think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men to judge, and of the D's Candour in concealing this part of the Hiſtory: And if we were to manage this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Authority, we have an Act of Parliament, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of as good Proteſtants, <hi>A.</hi> 1689. to ballance the Addreſe of the Commons in 1662. with the concurring Authority of all our Kings, who have been experienced in theſe our differences, aſſerting the conveniency of Indulging tender Conſciences, as we could give him undeniable Inſtances: But one for all, is the Vote of the Houſe of Commons paſſed <hi>Jan. 10th.</hi> 168 where they ſay, <hi>It is the Opinion of this Houſe that the Perſecution of Proteſtant Diſſenters upon the Penal Laws is at this time Grievous to the Subject, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening to the Proteſtant Intereſt, an Encouragement to Popery, and dangerous to the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His 7th, and laſt Argument, which he calls the moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible of all, is the judgment of the Miniſters of <hi>London,</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> againſt Toleration. Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1648.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Tho' we allow the Truth of all thoſe Miniſters ſay, yet they never intended that, for that end, which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts their words to: For it will be hard to perſuade the world, that theſe men judged the Toleration of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians unlawful, ſeeing themſelves were ſuch; and becauſe his whole Argument runs upon a falſe ſuppoſition, that we deſired an univerſal Toleration of all Sects, he may receive our judgment in this, from our confeſſion, <hi>Cap. 20. Sect. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They, who upon pretence of Chriſtian Liberty do practice any Sin, or cheriſh any Luſt, do thereby deſtroy the end of Christian Liberty, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the Power which God hath ordained, and Liberty which Chriſt hath purchaſed, are not intended by God to deſtroy, but mutually to uphold one another; they,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:188013:14"/>
who upon pretence of Chriſtian Liberty ſhall oppoſe any lawful Power, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, reſiſt the Ordinance of God; and for their publiſhing ſuch Opinions, and maintaining ſuch Practices, as are contrary to the Light of Nature, or the known Principles of Chriſtianity, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning Faith, Worſhip, Converſation, or the Power of Godlineſs; <q>Or ſuch Erronious Opinions or Practices, as either in their own nature, or in the manner of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and maintaining them, are deſtructive to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Order, which Chriſt has Eſtabliſhed in the Church, they may be lawfully call'd to account, and proceeded againſt by the Cenſures of the Church, and by the Power of the Civil Magiſtrate. Thus far our Confeſſion of Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By this 'tis apparent, that we juſtify no unlimited Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and when he hath made it appear, that we maintain Opinions and Practices inconſiſtent with the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and known Principles of Chriſtianity either in Faith, Worſhip, or Converſation, or deſtructive of the external Order by Chriſt Eſtabliſhed in his Church, then let us be look't upon as deſerving no Toleration; and till then, we judge our title to it as good as theirs who enjoy their legal Eſtabliſhment: and tho we are not for encouraging any Evils, yet we believe if no Sinner were tolerable, the <hi>D.</hi> himſelf would be intolerable; for the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>G.</hi> 6. 1. that even Brethren may be overtaken in faults; but then they are to be reſtored with the ſpirit of meekneſs, not rigor: Every Sin is not the object of Church Cenſure, or the Magiſtrate's Wrath; but they may, and ought to bear one anothers burthens, and not to bind more heavy burthens on the backs of our Brethren, and then laſh them for their inability to bear them.</p>
            <p>For his Remark, about that which he calls the fortune of Toleration, which is, as he ſaith, <hi>to be always in extreems very good, or very bad, and is at ſeveral times highly applauded,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:188013:14"/>
and violently decry'd by the whole Body of Diſſenting Proteſtants;</hi> it hath ſome truth, but not the whole truth in it; for both Papiſts, and Sons of the Church, have, and do decry, and commend it according to their need: for do not the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Epiſcopal Brethren in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> plead for it as much as Proteſtant Diſſenters: We ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he hath ſeen Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Liberty of Prophecying; and when he hath anſwered the Preface to that Book, he may poſſibly prevent mens looking on Toleration as unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. If he had the wiſdom of the unjuſt Steward, he might improve his Remark, that ſhould he be put out of his Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip (which is metaphyſically poſſible) he might have Friends to receive him into their Houſes.</p>
            <p>To the V's. Queſtion <hi>whether he could produce one Inſtance of any Proteſtant Diſſenter even in the late Reign, turning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> The D. gives a womans reaſon, <hi>he could give ſeveral Inſtances, but will not mention one;</hi> which certainly flows not from tenderneſs of our Reputation, which he labours on all occaſions induſtriouſly to blaſt, but either becauſe he can't, as we are ſure he can't fairly, or becauſe he is tender of their honor now they are turn'd Papiſts, and will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, or fears if we come to ballance Accounts with him, he ſhall be much a Loſer.</p>
            <p>But however, He tells <hi>the great reaſon why ſo few of theirs or our Communion were perverted, is (under God) to be aſcribed to the excellent Diſcourſes wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t againſt Papiſts by the Epiſcopal Clergy; and amongſt the veſt numbers of thoſe admirable Tracts, two only were wrote by Diſſenters;</hi> and then he falls to down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right calling and revi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> think it unjuſt to derogate from the worth of any mans labours, yet it is only native to Animals of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their own Praiſe, and inconſiſtent with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, which directs us to let another man praiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Lips. A ſtranger and not thine own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> D. being jealous none would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:188013:15"/>
to be his Parties Herald, but with ſo much Vanity, That he calls to our remembrance, a frantick man, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Troubles wandred about in the North, under the Title of King of the Rainbow, who with great aſſurance aſſerted he defended <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> from all foreign Enemies, that he fought our Battles, and that we ow'd our lives to his Valour &amp; Conduct, and hath been obſerv'd buſie in an old Fort in his imaginary War: So, tho we will not deny all good that ſuch diſcourſes may have done, yet we are confident that their influence upon Diſſenters hath been very weak, ſeeing very few of them hath heard or ſeen theſe <hi>Admirable Tracts,</hi> which would juſtly deſerve the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thete, if they could preſerve thoſe who never ſaw nor heard them: But how comes he to know, that only two were wrote by Diſſenters againſt Papiſts? doth he know all of that nature is done by them, we ſuppoſe the Morning Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes Preach't and Printed, by the Diſſenting Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> to that purpoſe, may vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with any of theſe admirable Tracts, ſeveral others alſo might be Inſtanced: But yet we ſee not that the Iriſh-Engliſh Clergy have any great ſhare in this Honour, except it be the Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> in his <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Tract</hi> againſt <hi>Manby,</hi> in which he hath taken the ſame method to prevent Diſſenters being perverted, that ſo did, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> recommended cutting off the Head as a Soveraign Remedy againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oothach, for leſt the Catholick Church ſhou'd loſe its Members by their being perverted, he pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently cut them off from being Members of it; And left the Lawful Spiritual Governours of the Church ſhou'd laugh at Presbyterians and Independants, he appears to us to treat them no better, if his Difinition of the Catholick Church hold good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or pag. 4. He defines it to be <hi>the whole Body of Men, profeſſing the Religion of Chriſt, and living under their Lawful Spiritual Governours.</hi> Now the Lawful Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Governours can't live under the Lawful Spiritual Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, for then ſhould they be undermoſt and upmoſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:188013:15"/>
at the ſame time, and therefore a Biſhop is as little a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Catholick Church as a Presbyterian. Biſhop <hi>Sheridon</hi> alſo Preach't a Sermon againſt Popery, which we have ſeen; but how it preſerv'd him in his Biſhoprick, the <hi>D.</hi> knows: and yet notwithſtanding all theſe admirable Tracts he boaſts of, the Eſtabliſh't Church has furniſh't <hi>Rome</hi> with twenty Proſelytes to one, more than all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Proteſtants in <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſo that their Works has been better Amulets for their Neighbours, than themſelves: If we intended to render railing for railing, we would charge the Epiſcopal Clergy with what he falſely accuſeth all Diſſenting Miniſters, as <hi>being Trumpoters in State Tumults and Seditions:</hi> But we leave that work to his Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiſh Brethren, who have upbraided many of their own Clergy with that Evil, under the aggravation of Treachery and Perjury; <hi>But wickedneſs proceedeth from the wicked, my hand ſhall not be upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho the <hi>D.</hi> endeavors to ridicule Preaching the Goſpel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of raiſing the Hue and Cry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet it hath pleaſed God, <hi>by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching, to ſave them that believe:</hi> The Goſpel was planted by Preaching, not by Printing, and ſhall be preſerved by the ſame means, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 32. And as <hi>Rome</hi>'s firſt wound was given by the faithful Preaching of the firſt Reformers, more than by their Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo we underſtand not, that the Walls of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be battered by Books, but as the Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> did fall by Faith, even ſo ſhall <hi>Rome's 2 Theſſ. 2, 8.</hi> The Lord ſhall <hi>conſume it with the ſpirit of his mouth; and Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by God's Word Preached,</hi> Rom. 10. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>The <hi>V.</hi> having told, to mortifie the man's vanity, that years experience might convince them how unſuccesful they had been in gaining Diſſenters to their Communion; the <hi>D.</hi> tells, <hi>that this is mainly to be attributed to the unwearied labours of Diſſenting Preachers; in raiſing unreaſonable preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:188013:16"/>
and in fixing invincible averſion to our Eccleſiaſtical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Conſtitutions, &amp;c.</hi> in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As their endeavors have been very unſuccesful as to the numbers they have gain'd from us, ſo the worth of ſuch is inconſiderable, being perſons whom a worldly Intereſt, and a more licentious Life prevail'd upon; and as they are no Ornaments to their Church (except their admired Biſhop of <hi>Derry)</hi> ſo they are no loſs to us, who could ſpare them more ſuch, when we detect them. Nor is this to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted ſo much to the unwearied labours of Diſſenting Preachers, (as he ſaith) as to the Dignified Clergy's eaſy wearying in their labours, and inverting the Apoſtle's words into, <hi>Woe to me if I Preach the Goſpel;</hi> and the unwearied purſuit of Dignities, and Revenues of the Church, more than Miniſterial Duties: nor need the Diſſenting Preachers weary themſelves to beget in people an averſion and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt the Diſcipline and Conſtitutions of the Church; for 'tis the ſelling the management of Church Diſcipline to Officials and Regiſters, and their ways of exerciſing Church Diſcipline, more by picking mens Pockets, than bringing them to due Penitence, that hath rendred Diſcipline odious and nauſeous even to all ſober Conformiſts, while they ſee Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline uſed as an Engine to drain mens Purſes, more than reform their Manners. And the Keys of Heaven and Hell intruſted with ſuch hands, who for trifles deliver men to Satan, but will not relax them without ſums of Money, whereby they ſhew themſelves too liberal to the Devil but not ſo careful to deliver out of his power: Theſe are things not done in a corner, but ſuch as the Nation is diſſatisfied with; beſides this, the manifeſt partially in the Exerciſe of Diſcipline, makes men think there is little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard had to <hi>Paul</hi>'s charge given to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 5. 21. <hi>I charge thee before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things, without preſerring one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another, doing nothing by partiality:</hi> For 'tis known, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:188013:16"/>
Great Mens Immorality (tho' never ſo heinous) eſcape with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebuke, and the truly poor free to ſin, becauſe they want Silver, according to the Rule in the Official Court.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Deux, 6. Ace non poſſunt, ſix cinque non ſolvere volunt. Hoc tamen eſt notum quater tres ſolvere totum.</head>
               <p>By theſe, and ſuch like Methods, many are driven to us. If he ſay the Church does not allow theſe Practices, why then are Diſſenters Excommunicated for diſobedience to that, which the Church allows not of? But leſt our words ſhou'd give offence, we hope Dr. <hi>Andrews</hi> will not, which he Preached before the <hi>Convocation,</hi> viz. <hi>The Church Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures now a days reach the Purſe only: Evil doers, when they have paid their Fees, return Scot-free; If no Money, then have at the Offenders with the Epiſcopal Sword, preſently at one blow they are cut off from the Church, dilivered over to Satan, proclaimed Publicans, Heathens, Anathema, for the moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous things, and againſt every good Man theſe Brutiſh Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts do fly up and down, and only to be fear'd of the Purſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The D. having Arraign'd Diſſenters as the chief Dividers of the Church, has been ſo juſt not to make them the only Dividers, but hath done them the honour to join the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates as Fomenters of diviſion with them: which he chargeth, 1. Upon the prodigious Licentionſneſs in a late Reign. 2. The Governments too eaſy Condeſcentions at another time. 3. The rigorous Executing the Laws againſt Diſſenters at ſome times: And thus he diſciplins the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Seeing the Government hath had a hand in foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Diviſions, he might have honour'd the King and Magiſtrates ſo far, as to give them the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eminence above Diſſenting Preachers: yet as to his Dividers, 1. Prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Licentiouſneſs, he may enquire at <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 34. If the Clergy might have a hand in it, and had they ſpent the one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:188013:17"/>
half of their Thunderbolts imploy'd againſt Diſſenters, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the prodigiouſly licentious, they might have purg'd themſelves from that Diviſion cauſed by prodigious Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs: yet we know that great Men of the Church have caught; <hi>That it is abſolutely neceſſary to the Peace and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Kingdom, that there be ſet up a more ſevere Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over Mens Conſciences, and Religious Perſuaſions, than over Mens Vices and Immoralities.</hi> Thus Teacheth Bp. <hi>Packer</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Policy, page 53. <hi>And that Princes may with leſs hazard give Liberty to Mens Vices than their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> page 55. And what he Taught, others have Practci'd. 2. <hi>For eaſy Condeſcentions to Diſſenters:</hi> The Church may ſafely purge her ſelf from this guilt; yea, we aſſure her the Diſſenters will be her Compurgators herein. 3. <hi>The Rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Execution of the Laws</hi> we confeſs hath given cauſe to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the Executioners: but then how can he be guiltleſs of the Sin of Dividing, who pleads for the perpetuating theſe Laws, which he confeſſeth, gives juſt occaſion to abhor them, and are Pomenters of Diviſion? How inconſiſtent is he with himſelf and reaſon in this? for if theſe Laws may not be Executed without prejudice to the Union of the Church, why are they continu'd in force? if Rigorous Laws foment Diviſions, as is confeſt, theſe cannot be guiltleſs of the Diviſions, who urge the making and executing ſuch Laws as the <hi>D.</hi> now pleads for.</p>
               <p>The Leſſon he preſcribes to Magiſtrates, <hi>That their beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior towards their People ſhould reſemble that of diſcreetly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Parents towards their Children, not indulging their folly, by an imprudent fondneſs, nor puniſhing their faults by too harſh a Correction, but by conſtantly keeping a ſtrict hand over them, which will prove the moſt Effectual means of preventing or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining their Exorbitancies.</hi> This we hope the Magiſtrate will learn, and look upon the Sons of the Church to be no more B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds, than Diſſenters, but uſe the Rod of Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to drive out that ſolly is bound up in their Hearts, and ſo prevent or reſtrain their Exorbitancies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:188013:17"/>
The <hi>2d</hi> Leſſon this <hi>D.</hi> preſcribes to Magiſtrates is, <hi>That at preſent they keep a ſtrict hand in managing the publick Affairs in this Kingdom, &amp;c.</hi> His Reaſons for their being ſtrict, are theſe: 1. <hi>Within theſe 5 years many thouſands of Families have come from</hi> Scotland <hi>to ſettle in this Nation.</hi> 2. <hi>They and their Teachers are zealous for the Covenant.</hi> 3. <hi>They have come from a place where Epiſcopacy is aboliſhed.</hi> 4. <hi>He fears, from their averſion to the Eccleſiaſtical Policy of the Church, when their Numbers and Preachers are increaſed, they will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the truly Apoſtolical Government of the Eſtabliſh't Church.</hi> And then he preſcribes an Antidote againſt this Plague, <hi>viz. That their Preachers be obliged to perform their Quarantine, and to undergo ſome Religious Teſt before they be admitted to Preach in their Conventicles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Admonition having apparently its riſe from fear, muſt be conſidered with its Cauſes, and Remedy. His fear ſeems to ariſe from his gift of Prophecy; by laying aſide which, or prophecying better things, he might cure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of that panick fear: for we dare aſſure him, that ſome of us are ſo far from deſiring the over-turning of the truly Apoſtolical Government of the Church, that we could wiſh them over-turn'd, who turn it out to turn in another of their own: tho we are perſuaded, if the Biſhops were turn'd out of Parliament from all their Civil Honours, exceſſive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, and ſole Exerciſe of Church-Juriſdiction, and ſhould be oblig'd to Preach the Goſpel conſtantly, and not to Lord it over God's Inheritance, we ſhould not loſe any thing of the Apoſtolical Government; which we may the more boldly ſay, becauſe we find in a Speech of the Lord <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare</hi>'s in Parliament, againſt the Biſhops Voting in caſe of Blood, theſe words: <hi>I like Biſhops very well, but I wiſh that Biſhops were reduc'd to their Primitive Inſtitution: for I fear, while there is in</hi> England <hi>a Lord Biſhop, the Church will not ſtand very ſteadily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:188013:18"/>
To his firſt cauſe of this fear, <hi>viz. The many thouſand Families that are come out of</hi> Scotland, whether the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will judge it the Intereſt of the Kingdom, to hinder its Planting with his Majeſties Induſtrious and Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to gratify the D. and cure him and the Iriſh Papiſts of their fears, is very doubtful. But I believe, thoſe, who value the Proteſtant and Brittiſh Intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> could wiſh that many more thouſand Proteſtant Families were Planted here, tho they were not all of the D's. perſuaſion; nor do we ſee that this would leſſen the Revenue and Strength of the Kingdom, abate Gentlemens Rents, ſpoil the Nations Trade, nor hinder the Clergys Tythes; ſo that it is queſtionable wherein the Nations Intereſt can be to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct Proteſtants ſettling here. If his fears be becauſe ſuch are Scotch, 'tis but the ordinary effect of ſuch panic fear as to bereave Men of conſiderate thoughts which ſeems to be the D's Caſe: For beſide the little Religion he Evidenceth in his Antipathy againſt that Nation, there is as little policy as piety, in its ſeeing the Nobility and Gentry of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (whom he boaſts to be Members of this Eſtabliſht Church) cannot but reſent ſuch a publick affront done to their Nation.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond cauſe of his fear, <hi>viz. Their Preachers Zeal to the Covenant:</hi> If by it he means the National Covenant Subſcribed by King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> and all Ranks of Perſons in <hi>Scotland</hi> in 1580, 1581, and 1590, they will own it, as the antient Confeſſion of that National Church; and we ſuppoſe his Scotch Epiſcopal Brethren dare not diſown it, ſeeing it was a part of that Contradictory Teſt which they impos'd, the old profeſſional part contradicting the new promiſſory part: but we ſuppoſe he intends the ſolemn League and Covenant: and here we believe he may be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken of their Zeal for that, as it is a League with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> obliging them to a Reformation, ſeeing as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:188013:18"/>
theſe Leagues formerly made with <hi>France</hi> oblige <hi>England</hi> ſince the <hi>French</hi> have violated them. The Antidote againſt <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Planting by Proteſtant Subjects from <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſmels rank of National Antipathy, and ſmites his Majeſty King <hi>William,</hi> with his now bleſſed Conſort Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as Plaguers of that Nation, by Aboliſhing Epiſcopacy: but yet let this Antidote be no worſe than its words are, and we refuſe not to perform a juſt quarentine, and undergo any truly Religious Teſt, that His Majeſty ſhall think neceſſary to promote God's Glory, the Nations Peace and Proſperity by: Yet Experience hath found ſome of theſe called Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Teſts to be National Peſts, and ſhould others obſerve them no better then the D. and ſome of his Brethren have done, the Government may poſſibly be rendered more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, but not more ſafe by them.</p>
               <p>But we perceive the D's. fears are increaſing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would have all the Nation Allarm'd with the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the <hi>Cameronians,</hi> who (as he ſaith) <hi>are lately Landed in conſiderable Numbers!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe conſiderable Numbers of <hi>Cameronians</hi> lately landed muſt have come from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>utopia,</hi> for there be no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Numbers of them now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions bring forth no ſuch Fruit: For ſince the late happy Revolution, all, except very few, unite with the Eſtabliſh't Church there, and their Preachers now orderly and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd Miniſters, one whereof is a Chaplain to a Regiment in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and in good eſteem with his Majeſty for his Zeal and Courage, whereof he hath given good proof: And we dare ſay, that thoſe, whom he calls ſo dangerous, have ſpent more blood in the defence of the Proteſtant Religion, and in the Service of their King and Countrey both at home and abroad, than all the Epiſcopal Clergy in <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> for the truth of which we doubt not but the beſt of the three Nations will vouch. But while he is allarming the Kingdom with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:188013:19"/>
doth he not alſo, as a Faithful Watchman warn it of his Jacobitiſh Brethren, who ſwarms hither daily, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their publickly declar'd Contempt of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Government and Authority, in denying Allegiance to him in <hi>Scotland,</hi> are entertain'd as boſom Friends by ſome Clergy-men in <hi>Ireland,</hi> tho they perform'd not their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantine, by ſwearing Allegiance to K. <hi>William:</hi> And if the Government deſire ſatisfaction in this matter, they may (by ſearch of Records in the ſeveral Counties where they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd) find out the truth of this and much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch courſe men.</p>
               <p>The Vindicator had told, <hi>That there had been avowed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Extirpating Proteſtant Diſſenters, declared by many Sanguinary Laws paſt againſt them both in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and that there were later ones in</hi> Scotland <hi>that made it capital to be preſent at their Meetings,</hi> which the D. reckons unpardonable diſingenuity ('tis well it is not the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt) and to prove it, theſe irrefragable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are produced. 1. He never heard it. 2. He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by thoſe, who have reaſon to know better then the Vindicator, that there is not one Sanguinary Law in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters, and in <hi>Scotland</hi> not one, except one, which was <hi>Auguſt</hi> 13. 1670.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To his firſt demonſtration taken from his not hearing it, it ſeems his ears are of a prodigious length, when every matter both of Fact and Law muſt be within the ſphere of their activity: if things ceaſe to be becauſe he heard them not, a great many have had no being, of whom he never heard. The next from his Informer, is little better; for Epiſcopal Informers have not been always men of the beſt reputation; yet it is ſtrange that they ſhould be ignorant of thoſe Laws, by which they had ſo much of other mens wealth; but it's like, that being now out of date, they are not fond of owning their old friends, leſt they ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe new Enemies: But if the D. (who ſees by his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:188013:19"/>
eyes) will receive truer Inſtruction from a Diſſenter, we will make appear that what the Vindicator aſſerts is real truth.</p>
               <p>To begin then with <hi>England,</hi> becauſe its Laws againſt Diſſenters are of eldeſt date, we will find that Sanguinary Laws were there, Firſt, againſt the Soul; Secondly, againſt the Body; Thirdly, againſt the Eſtates of Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters.</p>
               <p>And to give the Church the deſerv'd pre-eminence in this caſe, by her Canons made <hi>Anno</hi> 1603. eleven of theſe in the Van are levelled againſt Diſſenters, by moſt of which they are to be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, but by the A. Biſhop after Repentance, and a publick Recantation of ſuch wicked Errors: And when by this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Cimiter they are cut off from the Church Militant, and by vertue of the keys of Heaven committed to it, the gates of Heaven, which it ſeems were formerly potent, are now ſhut againſt Diſſenters, and <hi>alti janua ditis,</hi> made open, and they delivered to the Devil, leſt he ſhould prove too merciful in not receiving their Mittimus, the poor Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by a Writ <hi>De Excommunicato Capiendo</hi> is to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the Sheriffs, or his Bayliffs, and without Bail or Main-prize caſt into Priſon, there to lye till he for, or recan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, by which he is depriv'd of the benefit of the Law and Clergy both. Now, if this be no ſanguinary Law, to caſt men out of the Church, (out of which they teach there is no Salvation) and to deprive them of their Liberty, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Laws, only for impugning <hi>the Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church of England,</hi> according to the <hi>6th</hi> Canon, and at once to cut men off from their part of Heaven and Earth, unleſs they would counter-act their Conſcience; let the World judge.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Civil Laws made againſt Diſſenters in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were ſanguinary, if that may be conſtrued ſuch, which deprives men of Livelihood and Liberty; For 1. The Act
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:188013:20"/>
of Uniformity; by which, <hi>If any Miniſter convicted to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to uſe the Church Service, or to have uſed any other Rite or Ceremony, Order, Form or Manner, than what is ſet down in the Common-Prayer-Book, he loſeth a whole years profit, and muſt undergo ſix months Impriſonment for the firſt fault: For the ſecond, to be deprived, and ſuffer a whole years Impriſonment: For the third, he is to be deprived, and Impriſoned during life; and if he be not a Beneficed perſon, for the firſt fault he is to be impriſoned a whole year; and for the ſecond, during life:</hi> So that a man, for not uſing the Croſs in Baptiſm, and Kneeling at the Sacrament, (things which God never required) muſt be depriv'd of his Office, Livelihood and Liberty, and thus ſtarv'd in Priſon; but for this, perhaps the <hi>D.</hi> hath a Turkiſh diſtinction, that ſtrangling is no ſhedding of Blood, and yet we reckon he wou'd judge it ſanguinary, were he tryed by it. But farther, <hi>all perſons not reſorting to the Church on Sundays and Holy-days, are to be fined 12 d. per day, and to incur the Cenſures of the Church,</hi> which according to Canon 9, 11, 12, is Excommunication <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> with its appurtenances; yea, by Canon 10, if we ſhall dare to ſay, <hi>that we have long time groaned under the burthen of certain Grievances impoſed upon us, we are to be Excommunicated, and not reſtored until we repent, and publickly retract ſuch our publick Errors.</hi> 2. Act is that made in the 13 <hi>Eliz. to which every perſon not repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Church,</hi> according to Statute 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> The ſecond <hi>ſhall forfeit 20l. for every month, if they ſo make default; and if they forbear for the ſpace of 12 months, they are to be bound with two ſufficient Sureties in 200 l. Bonds to good Behaviour:</hi> And by a Statute 29 <hi>Eliz. All Grants made by ſuch Offenders, which are by them revocable, intended for his maintenance, left at his diſpoſal, or in conſideration whereof, he and his Family are to be kept, ſhall be utterly void against the Queen; for the levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the forfeitures for not coming to the Church, and the Queen may ſeize all the Goods, and two thirds of the Lands and Leaſes of every Offender not repairing to Church as aforeſaid;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:188013:20"/>
which after their firſt conviction, do not pay at the next Term, at the rate of 20 l. per month, and tho the party be not in the Realm, the Indictment is to lye, and upon an Indictment found, a Proclamation is to be made that ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender is to render himſelf to the Sheriff before the next Aſſizes; which if he do not, he is to be held Convict: Theſe who are not able to pay their Forfeitures are to be committed to Priſon till they pay or conform, which if they refuſe, makes the Impriſonment perpetual.</hi> And 35 Queen <hi>Eliz. It is Enacted, That if any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Sixteen abſent themſelves from Church above a Month, or frequent Conventicles, or perſuade any other ſo to do, they ſhall be committed to Priſon, there to continue, till he or ſhe Conform, and make open ſubmiſſion, and confeſs that they have grievouſly offended God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And if within three Months they refuſe to Conform and make ſuch ſubmiſſion they are to abjure the Realm, and if they refuſe to abjure, or return after without leave, they are to be proceeded againſt as Fellons, and have no benefit of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</hi> This we ſuppoſe was literally a Sanguinary Law. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by a Statute the 16 <hi>Car. 2d,</hi> this 35 Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> was revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And farther <hi>Anno 17. Car. 2d. Non-conformiſts who take not the</hi> Oxford <hi>Oath there ſet down, which is this.</hi> I A. B. <hi>do Swear that it is not lawful on any pretence whatſoever to take up Arms againſt the King, and that I abhor, that Trayterous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of taking up Arms by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionat by him in purſuance of ſuch Commiſſions, and that I will not endeavour any Alteration of Government, either in Church or State.</hi> Likewiſe, <hi>If any Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt Miniſter Preach in a Conventicle, or come within 5 Miles of any City or Corporation, or place of his Miniſtry, except on his Journey, or ſummoned by a Subpena, he ſhall forfeit 40l.</hi> Furthermore the Crimes in 22 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> againſt Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, are, 1. <hi>To be preſent at an Aſſembly under colour of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion any other way then according to the Liturgy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>where 5 Perſons, or more beſidess thoſe of the Family are. 2dly. If any take on him to Teach or Preach in ſuch Meetings, for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:188013:21"/>
the firſt Offence he forfeits 20l. For the ſecond, 40 pounds, &amp;c. 3d ly, If any perſon ſuffer ſuch Meeting to be in his Houſe, Out-Houſe, Back-ſide, or Garden; for his firſt Offence, he is to pay twenty pounds; for the ſecond, 40 pounds, &amp;c. and every Hearer five ſhillings, with Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures,</hi> which is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> according to the <hi>11th</hi> Canon.</p>
               <p>Now from all this, we leave it to the judgment even of Adverſaries themſelves, whether the Vindicator might not aſſert, that there were ſanguinary Laws in <hi>England</hi> deſign'd to extirpate Proteſtant Diſſenters; in exerting whereof, the Prelates of the Nation had a warm Vote, tho' now (bleſſed be God) they be aboliſhed by Act 1689.</p>
               <p>His vindicating <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt the guilt of ſanguinary Laws againſt Diſſenters, is proof that he hears ill, elſe the cry of that Blood ſhed there by vertue of theſe Laws, (which hath even reached Heaven, and brought deſerved Vengeance upon the ſhedders thereof) might have pierc'd his ears; and that he ſees ill, if he ſees not theſe Laws yet in record; but his own confeſſion, that there was one ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Law (tho he borrow'd Sir <hi>Geo. Makenzy</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar on it) is a ſufficient proof of a deſign to extirpate Proteſtant Diſſenters there, ſeeing that one Law, <hi>De Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico Comburendo,</hi> as employ'd in <hi>England</hi> by Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> was ſuppoſed ſufficient to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion out of <hi>England;</hi> but had he not deſign'd to blind-fold his Reader, a little more pains, and honeſty, might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled him to diſcover many ſanguinary Laws in <hi>Scotland:</hi> of which, take theſe few inſtances.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The 1 ſt Parliament of <hi>C.</hi> the 2 d. Seſſ. 1. Act 4. It was Enacted, that none be Maſters in Univerſities, School-Maſters, or Pedagogues, who would not own Prelacy,</q> which that Nation had abjur'd; even the Law-makers themſelves, whereby many were depriv'd of their liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood becauſe they would not be perjur'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:188013:21"/>
Seſſ. 2. Act 2. <q>It is Enacted that all Petioning, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Printing, or Remonſtrating, Praying or Preaching ſhewing any diſlike of the King's abſolute Prerogative, be puniſhed as Seditious, and that no Meetings be kept in private Houſes. Upon which accounts ſome ſuffered death.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Seſſ. 3. Act 2. <q>It is Enacted, That all Non-conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters, that preſume to Exerciſe their Miniſtry, be puniſhed as Seditious Perſons: And that all Perſons in in acknowledgement of his Majeſties Government Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, attend the ſervice of the Curates: Noblemen and Gentlemen refuſing, to loſe the fourth part of their Rents; Burgeſſes their freedom, and fourth part of their Moveables; Yeomen a fourth part of their Moveables; and others, twenty ſhillings every time, leaving the Council to inflict other Puniſhments as they thought fit. It is alſo Enacted, That if there were three above the Family at Preaching, or Prayer,, it ſhould be eſteem'd a Conventicle.</q> And for putting theſe Laws in Execution, a High-Commiſſion-Court was Erected, by the King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Act 13. Parl. 10. <hi>Jacob</hi> 6. with power to Examine upon Oath, <hi>Deſuper inquirendis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Parl. 2. <hi>Lauderdale</hi> Commiſſioner. It is Enacted by Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the King's Supremacy, that ordering the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, doth properly belong to His Majeſty and his Succeſſors, as an inherent Right to the Crown, and that he may Enact and Emit ſuch Conſtitutions, Acts and Orders, concerning Church Adminiſtrations, Perſons, Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Matters, as he in his Royal Wiſdom ſhall think fit. And thus a fair way was laid for K. <hi>James</hi>'s reforming the Church. This Act was to be obey'd by all Subjects, any Law or Cuſtom to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>Seſſ. 2. Parl. 2. It is Enacted, That who ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to depoſe upon Oath, their knowledge of Meetings, or Perſons at them, ſhou'd do it on pain of Fining, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Tranſportation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:188013:22"/>
Act 5. Enacted, That outed Miniſters, found Preaching or Praying in any Houſe, but their own Family, be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd till they find bond of 5000 Marks, not to do the like again, every hearer, <hi>toties quoties, 25l.</hi> if a Tenant, <hi>12l.</hi> if a Subtenant; and then all who Preached in the Field, or in a Houſe, if any of the people be without doors, ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with death: And they who can ſeize or ſecure any ſuch Miniſter, dead or alive, ſhall have 100 Marks Reward. The Magiſtrates in Boroughs to be fined at the Councils pleaſure, for any Conventicles held in their Boroughs. Men to be fined if their Wives or Children went to Meetings.</p>
               <p>Act 6. Fines were impos'd from 10 to <hi>20l. ſterl.</hi> on ſuch as had their Children Baptiſed at ſuch Meetings, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in half their Wages.</p>
               <p>Act. 11. Seſſ. 3. The ſame Fines were impos'd on them who kept their Children unbaptiſed for 30 days, and by Act 7. of the ſame Seſ. Intolerable Fines were impos'd on all who abſented themſelves 3 days together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The D. <hi>York</hi> being Commiſſioner, without taking the uſual Oath appointed by Law, and againſt Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making Papiſts incapable of that Truſt; the Fines were doubled for Field Conventicles. Gentlemen were obliged to remove Tenants, and Maſters their Servants, without warning, if they went to Meetings.</p>
               <p>Act. 6. They impos'd on all a ſelf-contradictory Teſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging them to own the Confeſſion of Faith recorded in Parliament, 1 <hi>Ja.</hi> 6. which diſowns the Supremacy, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts the lawfulneſs of defenſive Arms, tho' the contrary to both was Sworn in the promiſſory part of the Teſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as a <hi>Non obſtante;</hi> and for taking this Teſt with his own Explication, was <hi>Argile</hi> Beheaded.</p>
               <p>Parl, 1. <hi>Ja. 7 D. Queensbury</hi> Commiſſioner. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that ſuch as being cited as Witneſſes, in caſes of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Conventicles, and refuſed to depone, ſhould be liable to the puniſhment of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:188013:22"/>
Act 8. All who Preach or Hear at Houſe or Field-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, ſhall be puniſhed with death, and confiſcation.</p>
               <p>We hope now by this Account, (which if any doubt, we refer them to the Printed Statutes of the Nation). If the <hi>D</hi>'s Conſcience be nor ſear'd, it will be ſo much his friend as to ſmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him for the injuſtice he has done to truth, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſerting that there were no ſanguinary Laws in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſave one. And tho theſe Laws were ſo ſevere, as to deſerve abhorrence of all in whom any ſpark of Chriſtian humanity remains: yet the execution of them was more cruelly rigid: Dragoons, and a barbarous Pagan Highland-Hoſt being employ'd to execute them, without any Proceſs of Law. All that can be ſaid for the <hi>D.</hi> is, that if he thinks as he writes, he is ſcandalouſly ignorant of what all <hi>Britain</hi> knows; if otherwiſe, he is gtolsly diſingenuous to impoſe upon the credulity of his friends.</p>
               <p>As the <hi>D.</hi> hath given a ſad ſpecimen of his intelligence, ſo he gives equal diſcovery of his prudence, while he up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids the Scots Conventicle Rebels, for refuſing to Pray for K. <hi>Ja.</hi> For do not his Jacobitiſh Brethren deal ſo by K. <hi>William;</hi> and doth not himſelf ſo now, as they did then, tho' under ſome other obligations to do it than ever they were; whence we may tell him in his own words; <hi>that his Principles and Practices are deſtructive to the Eſtabliſh't Church and Government, if not Praying for K.</hi> Ja. <hi>be ſo. And that there be ſeveral diſtracted Cathedral Rebels, who refuſe to ſave their Livings and Biſhopricks at ſo dear a rate, as Praying for the King.</hi> Therefore he and his Party are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in <hi>bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide,</hi> to accuſe any for ſuch Principles and Practices, tho we deſpiſe both, as much as his folly, in laying theſe things to our charge.</p>
               <p>Secondly it's great imprudence what he ſaith next, <hi>vizt: Certainly theſe who refuſe to give the Government under which they Live, all reaſonable aſſurances, of their Fidelity and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and will not ſolemnly diſown their turbulent Principles,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:188013:23"/>
but ſtill retain their inveterate prejudices, and pernicious diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Eſtabliſht Church, cannot with any modeſty expect to be treated as ſincere and hearty friends, but as declared open Enemies, to the laſting Peace and Settlement of the Nation.</hi> For hereby he ſmites his dearly beloved Epiſcopal Clergy of <hi>Scotland</hi> under the fifth rib, and juſtifies all that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there hath done againſt them, tho' they ſhou'd declare them open Enemies to the Peace of the Nation, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have refus'd to give the Government under which they have lived theſe 5 years, any reaſonable aſſurance of their Fidelity and Obedience, but ſtill retain their invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate prejudices, and pernicious diſaffection to that Church and State, ſo far doth partial paſſion Tranſport him, that he mortally wounds them he pretends to defend.</p>
               <p>The V. having aſſerted as a good effect of the indulgence granted in <hi>England,</hi> that ſince Conformiſts and Diſſenters, converſe more ſociably and live more peaceably than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. This is Contradicted by the D. for this reaſon, he hath been oredibly informed, that Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> were grown very inſolent on the News of the Diſſolution of the laſt Parl. and reſolved to neceſſitate the Government to ſome larger Conceſſions to their Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſſenters have little reaſon to expect a juſt account of their Actions, from Bp's. informers, who have been ſo great a plague to them in <hi>England:</hi> But tho' the Authority he makes uſe of were good, his reaſoning is bad: for while the V. tells what hath been done for time paſt; he reſutes that Hiſtory, by a Prophecy in telling what they reſolve to do, tho' it's hardly credible Engliſh Diſſenters wou'd communicate their Intreagues to Epiſcopal Informers: But, time now can tell the World both the falſhood of his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Prophecy.</p>
               <p>His unjuſt reflection on thoſe he calls our <hi>Non-conforming Fathers in Q.</hi> Eliz. <hi>time, as perſons of reſtleſs Tempers, who for meek Petitions proceeded to Admonitions, then to Satyrical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:188013:23"/>
and thus threatned firſt the Biſhops, and then the Q. and Parl.</hi> evidenceth him to be of ſuch a Spirit, that neither Heaven nor the Graves of Godly Men do ſecure their Names from the venom of his tongue and pen, yet we count it our honour to be Children of ſuch Parents as many of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted for Non-conformity were, being Ornaments to their Nation for their Learning and Godlineſs. And moſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Character he and <hi>Walton</hi> unjuſtly gives them, as their own Works and the beſt Hiſtorians of their time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us.</p>
               <p>The D. being, as he ſays, <hi>led by the</hi> V's. <hi>method, to conſider the Reply's made to his Anſwer to the firſt Paper: Had this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to an Argument of his againſt granting any further favour to Diſſenters, then theſe ſeveral marks of Regal favour which they enjoy'd.</hi> That it's reaſonable that the continuance of the ſame favour ſhou'd be ſecured to them by Law. To this the D. <hi>rejoins that a Legal Security of the ſame favour is not deny'd them, if they be pleas'd to accept of it with theſe Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Reſtrictions that their equally deſerving Brethren do now enjoy it in</hi> England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the favour which we now enjoy through His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Clemency, ſhould have theſe Reſtrictions added to it which our Brethren in <hi>England</hi> have annexed to theirs, it wou'd not be the ſame we now have, ſo far is he miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. 2. We look upon the Reſtriction annexed to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence granted to the Diſſenters in <hi>England,</hi> neither ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Rules of Chriſtian Religion, nor the true intereſt and ſafety of this Nation. Not of the firſt for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>By this Sacramental Teſt (which is annex'd to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of <hi>England)</hi> Dominion muſt be founded in grace, for if Mens Right to their Civil Priviledges muſt depend upon their capacity to receive the Sacrament, to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving whereof the Church in the order of the Communion, requires true Repentance: then it requires grace to capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them for Civil Rights and Priviledges, and for want of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:188013:24"/>
true Repentance they muſt forfeit Imployments to which they have a Hereditary Right. Which Notion hath been Condemn'd as Irrational and Irreligious: yea, <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Aſs Taught better Divinity, when it ſaid, <hi>Maſter, am not I thine Aſs?</hi> Acknowledging his Right, tho' he had not grace. It this principle ſhou'd once obtain, its fatal conſequence might poſſibly reach the Mitres.</p>
               <p>2. But what is yet worſe, this Teſt ſhall make a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, <hi>viz.</hi> (kneeling at the Sacrament) the Condition of both State and Church Memberſhip: For if none but ſuch as kneel at the Communion, ſhall be admitted to ſhare of theſe Priviledges, to which as Chriſtians and free born Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects they have right, the gate unto the Church-Militant, is made ſtraiter then that into the Church-Triumphant. From which we hope Men will not be ſo uncharitable as to exclude all who do not kneel at the Sacrament, ſeeing Chriſt and his Apoſtles uſed no ſuch poſture.</p>
               <p>3. This makes kneeling at the Sacrament, Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount over all the reſt of the Ceremonies, by putting the keys of the Church door only into its hand, and ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the only evidence of ſaving grace, when all that ſcruple it muſt be debar'd from the Sacrament as Prophane, and theſe who bow to, and kneel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tar, are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy.</p>
               <p>4. Not to kneel in receiving, by this Teſt, is made equally criminal with believing Tranſubſtantiation, the Idolatrous Worſhipping of the Bread, and all the abominations of the Maſs with Papiſts: and with denying and contemning both Ceremony and Subſtance with the Quakers; whenas the ſame and no other puniſhment is inflicted upon Papiſts and Quakers, than is upon Proteſtant Diſſenters (for refuſing the ſame Teſt) tho' we agree with them in the Doctrine of the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>5. To put Men upon this Dilemma is the tender mercy of the wicked, and is to tempt Men to damn their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:188013:24"/>
preſerve their Bodies; And to give ſacred things to dogs. For if the perſons have by Chriſt's Inſtitution a right to the Sacrament, by what Authority can Man debar them by their Inventions, if they have none, then theſe are not faithful Stewards of the Miſteries of Chriſt, who abuſe them to ſerve their own ſecular ends.</p>
               <p>6. By this the Validity of the King's Commiſſion, muſt depend upon the Curates Certificate. And ſo His Majeſty muſt have a <hi>Conge Des Lire</hi> from the Clergy, before he can give out his Commiſſion for any Civil Office, leſt he loſe his labour. For the <hi>D.</hi> tells us plainly ſo much p. 27. that there are ſeveral Eccleſiaſtical Laws, ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l in force, by which tho' Diſſenters be not wholly unqualified for Admittance unto Civil Offices, yet they are perfectly diſ-enabled from continuing in them. So that their preſent quiet enjoyment of Employments, is not ſo much owing to their Legal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, as to the Lenity and kindneſs of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Governors. And ſo no Thanks to the King for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters Employments, but to the good Lord Biſhops. It ſeems the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> are not the only pretenders to a Supremacy in <hi>Temporalitus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it is not conſiſtent with the Piety, ſo not with the intereſt of this Nation, to impoſe unneceſſary Teſts and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, whereby men are frighted from coming to Plant in this kingdom, when all wiſe men have thought fit to decoy Inhabitants, by granting large Immunities and Priviledges: By this policy the Roman Empire grew from ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to be the Miſtreſs of the World. But to ſet up Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crows to fright any from coming to Plant and Trade in the Nation, cannot be conſiſtent with the wiſdom of its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: And ſure we are, neither the Heads or Hands of Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> are ſo few, and deſpicable, nor their friends abroad ſo weak or unwilling to help them, that we ſhould think <hi>Ireland</hi> over-ſtock't with Proteſtants to defendit: which Ceremonies will never do (for the Papiſts are better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:188013:25"/>
with them, than to be terrified by them) if another 1641 and another 1688 ſhould recur. And we may tell the World, that the firſt Teſt contriv'd againſt Diſſenters in <hi>Ireland,</hi> tho' it prov'd fatal to its Contrivers, was, by God's Providence, a means of preſerving the Diſſenters; who forſaking the Nation on that account, were preſerved from the Maſſacre 1641; and theſe ſame perſons returning, were the firſt relief that <hi>Ireland</hi> got, which can be made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by many yet alive, and may be inſtructive to paſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>The <hi>V.</hi> having (to prove the equity of giving free-born Subjects, the ſame legal Indulgence, in their Diſſenting, as is given to Foreigners) aſſerted, <hi>that the French Proteſtants, if left to their liberty, would chuſe a Diſcipline and Worſhip more conformable to their own, than that of the Eſtabliſh't Church.</hi> Hath this Anſwer: We are not to paſs judgment on a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, from the inconſiderate words and actions of ſome of the meaner ſort of the Laity, but by the ſolemn Declarations, and conſtant Practices of the Learned Clergy of that Communion. And to ſhew the Sentiments of the French Church, produceth a triple teſtimony of three French Divines in favor of the Eſtabliſh't Church, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the Diſſenters ſeparation from it: from three Letters written fifteen years ago on this Subject, by Monſieur <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyne, M. D. Langle,</hi> and <hi>M. Cloud,</hi> which we ſhall not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We think it ſtrange, that the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhou'd own the French Proteſtants to be a Churh, and to have a learned Clergy, when in the mean time they deny them to have a Lawful Ordained Miniſtry: and force them to be Re-ordained who come for Refuge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> and are willing to conform. So that this ſeems to be but a complement, given for theſe 3 Letters, and no ſincere acknowledgment of their being a Church. A Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend French Miniſter informs us, that flying from Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:188013:25"/>
into <hi>England,</hi> he with ſome others were permitted to Preach in <hi>London,</hi> but upon his refuſal to be Re-ordained, he was not only hindred to Preach, by the Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but deny'd any part of the publick Charity collected for the French Proteſtants, and ſo was neceſſitated to leave <hi>England.</hi> The ſame entertainment others of them met with here in <hi>Ireland</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 1680 or 1682; who flying to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſetting up the beginnings of ſeveral uſeful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures: but being averſe to joyn in the Church-Service, a certain charitable Peer lent them his Houſe to Worſhip in, where they ſerved God, according to the manner of the French Churches; whereupon their Miniſter was ſeized &amp; impriſon'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> until, for obtaining his liberty, he conſented to quit or abjure the Kingdom. And yet Liberty was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly allow'd the Papiſts. And we are well informed how the Papiſts now inſult over them, as having (by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning the validity of their own former Ordination; and being Re-ordain'd by Biſhops in <hi>England)</hi> thereby declared, that they have hitherto been no Church, have had no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments lawfully Adminiſtred among them; which is a great addition to their former miſeries: ſo that whether it be worſe to deſtroy the being of that Church in all time paſt, or perſecute ſome of its Members in time preſent, be the greater ſeverity, and ſo whether the Popiſh or Engliſh Clergy have been more merciful to the Proteſtant Church of <hi>France,</hi> we leave to be conſider'd.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Teſtimony of theſe 3 Men, are not the ſolemn Declaration, and conſtant practice of that Church, as he vainly ſays, but the opinion of three private Doctors, to whom he might oppoſe the Judgment of 3000, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant known practice of that Church, ſolemnly declared, in its publick Confeſſions of Faith, and Synodical Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſowning the Form of Worſhip and Diſciplin of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And it ſeems as unequal to judge of a Church by the Sentiments of ſeveral of her learn'd Clergy,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:188013:26"/>
as by the Laity: What a Monſter would the Church of <hi>England</hi> be, if we were left to judge of her, by the ſeveral opinions of her Learned Clergy, whereof ſome approve, others condemn <hi>Arminiaſm;</hi> ſome are paſſive obedient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, others not, ſome for Epiſcopacy <hi>jure Divino,</hi> others think it only <hi>jure Humano,</hi> ſome have been for, others are now againſt, Liberty of Propheſying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The juſteſt way then of judging what are the ſentiments of a Church, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the private practices or opinions of Clergy or Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; but by their Unanimous, deliberate and publickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Judgment in their Confeſſions of Faith and Synodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Conſtitutions: which had he produc'd againſt us, had been ſome ſervice to his cauſe. And we have juſt cauſe to except againſt the Evidence. Some of whom have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and have diſgrac'd their Church, by renouncing its Ordination, ſo that theſe who have diſhonor'd their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, will little regard their Brethren.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We know that indirect means have been uſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch Teſtimonies againſt us, and can tell of one who had 4 good fat Benefices in <hi>England,</hi> with a Faculty of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſidence, to Enable him to Traffick in <hi>France,</hi> introducing Diſſenters, and Exalting and vindicating the Prelacy and Ceremonies of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Teſtimonies are not fairly produc'd, but a part conceal'd of the Letters, which had he repeated would have condemn'd himſelf. And therefore M. <hi>Cloud</hi> in his Letter as Publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> p. 448. hath this. <q>I hope my Lord, you will not be wanting in the Duties of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Spirit of Peace, and that when the diſpute ſhall be only of ſome Ceremonies, which are ſtumbling blocks. and which in themſelves are nothing, in compariſon of an intire re-union of your Church, under your holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, you will make it ſeen, that you love the Spouſe of your Maſter, more than your ſelves; And that it is not ſo much from your greatneſs and Eccleſiaſtical Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:188013:26"/>
that you deſire to receive your joy and glory, as from your Paſtoral Vertues, and the ardent care you take of your Flocks.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>M. <hi>De Langle</hi> tells you that even amongſt theſe ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating Brethren, there is a very great Number of good Men, whoſe Faith is pure Piety ſincere; And it ſeems to me that the good and charitable Biſhops ought to ſay of them, as <hi>Optatus Melivitatus</hi> ſaid of the Donatiſts, in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a different ſenſe, <hi>Si Collegium Epiſcopate notunt habere nobiſcum, tamen fratres ſunt.</hi> And I'me ſure, ſaith he, that if there were nothing wanting to cure your Diviſions but tho abſtaining from ſome Expreſſions, the quitting ſome Ceremonies, the changing the colour of ſome Habits, you would reſolve to do that, and ſomething more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</q> But this the <hi>D.</hi> diſingenuouſly conceals becauſe of his Moderation, which is contrary to his Nature or Deſign.</p>
               <p>The <hi>V.</hi> having aſſerted alſo, that <hi>a further ſecurity ought to be granted to Proteſtant Diſſenters, than to Papiſts; for this reaſon, that ſome difference ſhould be made between them who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve well, and them who deſerve ill, of the Govarnment.</hi> The <hi>D.</hi> allowing the reaſoning to be unque6ionably true, yet will have it underſtood with this ſuppoſition; that if the Civil Parent be forced by the preſſure of ſome unfortunate <q>occurrences, to a conceſſion of ſuch favorable and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious conditions to an Enemy; which if he were left to the freedom of his own will, neither his fatherly kindneſs would incline him, nor his prudence permit him, to allow even to ſome of his own Children; this were no reflection on his juſtice, or kindneſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Suppoſito quolibet ſequitur quodlibet;</hi> But let us ſuppoſe as well as he, what is real matter of fact, that the Civil Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent is under no ſuch preſſure, but delivered from it by the aſſiſtance of his dutiful Children: It wou'd reflect on his juſtice, not only to treat equally dutiful Children unequally: but to deal worſe with the dutiful Children, than with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:188013:27"/>
heart-Enemies. And it is but to Preach up Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, to tell us, that our Civil Parents may reward Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion with priviledges, not to be granted to Loyal Subjects. For if Rebellion be the way to obtain priviledges, men will eaſily be induc'd to Rebel.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>D</hi>'s reflection on Diſſenters, <hi>as men of uncertain meaſures, and unſteady tempers, and therefore not to be truſted; for it's unknown, what changes ſome ſudden turns of publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, might make in the paſſions and intereſts of ſuch men.</hi> We Anſwer, that tho we pretend not to immutability, yet moſt Diſſenters dare aſſert the certainty of their meaſures, and ſteadineſs of their tempers, to have exceeded their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers: for neither can he charge us with breach of our Oath to any King, after Swearing never to take up Arms againſt him, nor any in Authority by him, upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever: nor did we violate our Faith by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring alteration of the Government in the State. Having never taken ſuch an Oath. Some of his own Brethren can tell him, that the Pillars of his Party, who in former Reigns were fixed Stars, are now become Planets. And that of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks, put in the Tower by King <hi>Ja.</hi> five of them prov'd Princes Metal. The Speech made by the Biſhop of <hi>M.</hi> in the name of the Clergy, to King <hi>Ja.</hi> at the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin, March</hi> 1688. And that made to K. <hi>William</hi> at his Camp nigh <hi>Dublin, 7 July,</hi> 1690. by the ſame Perſons, convince us, that ſudden turns of publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, will change mens paſſions, yea, and prayers to, witneſs that ſet framed 1688. againſt the Invaſion intended by the Pr. of <hi>O.</hi> and the new Edition framed ſince for K. <hi>William,</hi> where God is thanked for not hearing the former prayers, ſo that <hi>Turpe eſt doctori cum culpa reda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>guit ipſum.</hi> If they be afraid of our unſteady tempers, let us be Eſtabliſhed by Law and that prevents the evil in us as well as them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>D</hi>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſequence from the <hi>uncertain meaſures, &amp;c. of Diſſenters,</hi> viz. <hi>that all prudent and unbyaſs'd perſons will agree
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:188013:27"/>
in judging that a limited Indulgence will be more proper for the Non-Conformiſts, than a legal and reſtrictive Liberty, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are of opinion, that neither We, nor the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh't Church have right to unlimited Liberty; for as <hi>Rex habet in Regno ſuo ſuperiores, Deum legem &amp; Parliamentum,</hi> as a great Lawyer ſaith; ſo we are ſatisfied, that both C? &amp; N. C? be limited by theſe, only we deſire that our Liberty granted, be not clogg'd with Teſts deſtructive of that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, by which only the beſt and moſt capable of ſerving their King and Country, amongſt the Diſſenters, are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enabled thereto: And tho' as he ſaith, that <hi>none blame the</hi> Chineſes <hi>for building a Wall to defend their Frontiers from the Incurſions of the</hi> Tartars: yet we are told by as good an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor as himſelf, that, that great Wall doth not keep the Cham of Tartary from invading that rich and plentiful Country, inſomuch that his ſucceſſors have been quiet poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of it, ever ſince 1650. But tho' Walls be good for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yet the Chineſies were never ſuch fools as to make partition Walls to divide their Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The <hi>D.</hi> vain gloriouſly boaſting, that <hi>he had beaten the V. out of his ſeveral Arguments,</hi> purſues him with open mouth to matter of fact. And is as followeth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>V.</hi> had hinted a memorial of the State of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſince the Revolution, to vindicate the State and Church from the unjuſt Calumnys of the Anſwerer to the Caſe, which Memorial he had from two Scotch Gentlemen, particularly acquainted with the affairs of that Nation: which the <hi>D.</hi> will <hi>have to be a forgery pretended to be wrought by a friend, when it was the</hi> V'<hi>s own Act and Deed; and his reaſons for</hi> this forgery are, 1. <hi>The Title diſcovers it to be his. 2. The Genius of the Perſon, who is not like other Men, for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting things in a falſe light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>D,</hi> pretends indeed to an Extraordinary Sagacity in diſcerning Stiles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:188013:28"/>
And yet what the <hi>V.</hi> aſſerted in that is firm truth, for the Gentleman (if needful) can be produced, and will own that Letter to be theirs, and prove every tittle in it to be true; ſo that if there be any Genius's more remarkable for raiſing and falſe accuſing of the Brethren than others, the <hi>D.</hi> is unhappily match'd with one of thoſe.</p>
               <p>But let's come to the Merits of the Cauſe: The firſt thing in the Letter he is offended at, is a general reflection caſt upon the whole Body of the Scotch Biſhops, for their declaring their utmoſt abhorrence of his preſens Majeſty's deſcent into <hi>England,</hi> their Unanimous deſerting of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of States, both which he denies to be true for this reaſon, <hi>That if they had been guilty of theſe things, it would have occaſioned ſome publick and ſevere remark, to be paſſed upon them, and would have been inſiſted on, as the moſt plauſible, if not the greateſt reaſon for extirpating of Epiſcopacy, whereas in the Act for Aboliſhing Prelacy, there is not the leaſt cenſure paſs'd on any of the Biſhops.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That the Biſhops of <hi>Scotland</hi> did both declare their abhorrence of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s deſcent, and Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly deſert the convention of States, are ſuch evident truths, that nothing but wilfull Ignorance, or groſs Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would make a man deny them, becauſe they were not done in a corner, but in the face of the Nation, now their Addreſs to King <hi>James</hi> will ſufficiently prove the firſt, which take as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Addreſs of the Arch Biſhops and Biſhops of</hi> Scotland <hi>to K.</hi> James, <hi>upon the news of the Prince of</hi> Orange'<hi>s Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking,</hi> Nov. 10. 1688. <hi>Vide Gazette, Numb.</hi> 2398.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe your Most Sacred Majeſty.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>VVE proſtrate our ſelves to pay our moſt devout thanks and adoration to the Soveraign Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, for preſerving your ſacred Life and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:188013:28"/>
Perſon, ſo frequently expoſed to the greateſt hazards, and as often delivered, and you miraculouſly preſerved with Glory and Victory, in defence of the Rights and honour of Your Majeſty's Auguſt Brother, and theſe Kingdoms, and that by his merciful goodneſs the ragings of the Sea, and madneſs of unreaſonable men have been ſtilled and oalmed, and Your Majeſty, as <hi>the darling of Heaven,</hi> peaceably ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the I hrones of your Royal Anceſtors; whoſe long Illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trious and unparallel'd Line is the greateſt glory of this your Ancient Kingdom: we pay our moſt humble gratitude to Your Majeſty for the repeated aſſurances of your Royal Protection to our National Church and Religion, as the Laws have Eſtabliſhed them, which are very ſuitable to the gracious countenance, incouragement, and Protection, your Majeſty was pleaſed to afford to our Church, whilſt we were happy in your preſence amongſt us.</p>
                     <p>We Magnifie the Divine Majeſty for bleſſing you with a Son, and us with a Prince, whom we pray Heaven may bleſs and preſerve to ſway Your Royal Scepter after you, and that he may inherit with Your Royal Dominions, the Illuſtrious and Heroick virtues of his Auguſt and moſt Serene Parents.</p>
                     <p>We are amaz'd to hear of the danger of an Invaſion from <hi>Holland,</hi> which excites our prayers, for an univerſal Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to all orders of men, that God may yet ſpare his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, preſerve Your Royal Perſon, prevent the Effuſion of Chriſtian blood, and give ſuch Succeſs to your Majeſty's Arms, that all who invade your Majeſty's juſt and undoubted Right, and Diſturb or Interrupt the Peace of your Realms may be diſappointed and cloathed with ſhame; ſo that on your Royal Head the Crown may ſtill flouriſh.</p>
                     <p>As by the grace of God we ſhall preſerve in our ſelves an unſhaken and firm Loyalty, ſo we ſhall be careful and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to promote in all your Subjects an intrepid and ſtedfaſt Allegiance to your Majeſty, as an eſſential part of their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:188013:29"/>
Religion, and the glory of our holy Profeſſion: Not doubting but that God in his great mercy, who hath ſo often preſerved and delivered your Majeſty, will ſtill preſerve and deliver you, by giving you the hearts of your Subjects, and the necks of your Enemies, ſo Pray we, who in all humility are,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe your moſt Sacred Majeſty, Your Majeſty's moſt Humble, moſt Faithful, and moſt Obedient Subjects and Servants.</salute>
                        <dateline>Edinburgh <date>Nov. 3 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed by the Lords Biſhops.
<list>
                              <item>B. St. <hi>Andrews.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Glaſgow.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Galloway.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Aberdeen.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Dunkell.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Buchan.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Orkney.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Murray.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Roſs.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Dumblaine.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>B. <hi>Iſles.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Here is a Specimen of thoſe Gentlemens Genius whoſe heads the <hi>D.</hi> would preſerve while he bold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y oppoſeth truth, and neceſſitates us to lay open to the world this Tryal of Skill of his Epiſcopal Brethren, who all yet (except the Biſhop of <hi>Rapho</hi> whom an Iriſh Biſhoprick hath converted) glory in their being counted worthy to ſuffer for K. <hi>James,</hi> and continue to deny Allegiance to K. <hi>William,</hi> with many of their fellow Brethren.</p>
               <p>That the Scoth Biſhops unanimouſly deſerted the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of States, we ſuppoſe none of themſelves will deny, which if any do, we ſhall.</p>
               <p>In Anſwer to his reaſons proving theſe Reflections un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, becauſe <hi>that the converſion would have paſs'd ſome publick and ſevere mark upon them had that been true,</hi> we ſay, that by this he ſees the mildneſs and tenderneſs of that convention, who without laying open to the world their groſſeſt Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, only voted the Biſhops and their Clergy the great
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:188013:29"/>
and unſupportable grievance of the Nation, and thereupon voted the total aboliſhing of Prelacy, and if theſe be not publick and ſevere marks indeed upon them, why doth he make ſuch a horrid Noiſe about their Perſecution; further 'tis not to be attributed to want of matter, that in the Act they are excluded by, there is no particular mention of the misbecoming actions of their Lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Parliaments are not Hiſtorians, but yet if he long for a Legend of their Lives, he may poſſibly obtain his deſires e're long, little to their Credit, or his Comfort, for there are many recorded In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of their misbecoming actions noticed by thoſe who ſmarted under them, which if he neceſſitates us to lay open to the world, poſſibly his Brethren may thank him: For do's he think, that ſo long as it remains in the Records of Counſel that they impoſed, and took a contradictory Teſt, that it will not be alledged that they are perjured themſelves, and the cauſe of it in others? or that they abjured what they had formerly ſworn with great Solemnity, and betrayed the truth committed to them. Yea ſure ſo long as it continues in the Records of theſe Counſels, whereof they were Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that they ordered men to be killed without any Tryal or Colour of Law, or ſo much as with an exception whether they reſiſted or no, it will be hard to purge them from the guilt of Murther: for it is very evident that theſe Prelates had a hot hand in all the Innocent Blood ſhed in <hi>Scotland</hi> in K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. and K. <hi>James</hi> I. times, which we leave to thoſe who may write their Hiſtory: Poſſibly the <hi>D.</hi> believes not this, becauſe he heard it not, and therefore we urge him to inform himſelf better from Authentick Proofs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of that Nation, that the Stains of his Brethren there may be a warning to him and all Clergy-men to fright them from mercileſs cruelty, to which from a ſmall tryal of his skill already given, we fear he may be too much given.</p>
               <p>His ſecond exception againſt thoſe two Gentlemens Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, <hi>That it confidently aſſerts, that there is not ſo much as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:188013:30"/>
one ſingle man, who was in the Poſſeſſion of their Churches and publick Livings wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n K.</hi> James <hi>abdicated and forfeited, who hath ſince K.</hi> William'<hi>s acceſſion to the Crown been thruſt out for any other Crimes than either, 1. for not reading the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereby K.</hi> William <hi>and Q.</hi> Mary <hi>were Declared King and Queen, or 2. for their not Praying for His Majeſty, or 3. for not Swearing the Oath of Allegiance and Aſſurance, or 4, for ſuch Immoralities as the Church of</hi> England <hi>as truly diſallows as Prebyterians.</hi> To contradict which, he produceth an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of one Mr. <hi>Samuel Mowat</hi> a Clergy-man of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and at the time in <hi>Dublin, &amp;c.</hi> who was in poſſeſſion of his Church in <hi>Scotland</hi> after K. <hi>William</hi> and Q <hi>Mary</hi>'s acceſſion to the Throne, and read the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> publiſhed by the Council of <hi>Scotland, April</hi> 13. 1689. by the appointment of the General Aſſembly, 2. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Their Majeſties, 3. took the Oath of Allegiance and Aſſurance, 4. was free of Immoralities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and declared himſelf willing to ſubmit to the Presbyterian Government, according to his Majeſty's Formula, and yet he was rejected by them becauſe he would not renounce the Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and declare his ſorrow for ſubmitting to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We might ſatisfy our ſelves with this, that Mr. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Mowat</hi> point blank denies what the <hi>D.</hi> hath written, to be his Teſtimony, and that it is groſly falſifyed; but tho' he had ſaid all this, his ſingle Teſtimony does not prove it's Truth, for while he ſays that the Aſſembly appointed the reading the Proclamation whereby K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi> were Declared King and Queen, which Proclamation was publiſhed <hi>April</hi> 13. 1690. This muſt be falſe ſeeing there was no Aſſembly till <hi>October</hi> 16. 1690. when they firſt ſat after the Revolution. It's true he Petition'd the Aſſembly who referr'd his Caſe to the Presbyteries of <hi>Lanerk</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> where he had formerly been officiated, but was by them rejected for his Immoralities which himſelf knows, and all have cauſe to believe, ſeeing Biſhop <hi>Foley</hi> late Biſhop of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:188013:30"/>
                  <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Connor</hi> did for groſs Immoralities fully proven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, deprive him of his Curacy he had got in the Pariſh of <hi>Dunean</hi> in the County of <hi>Antrim:</hi> So that if he was barbarorſly robbed by Presbiterians in <hi>Scotland,</hi> he has met with as little mercy from his Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as the Records of the Dioceſs of <hi>Connor</hi> can teſtify.</p>
               <p>His third Exception to theſe Gentlemens Letter is to theſe words in it, <hi>viz.</hi> So far are they in <hi>Scotland</hi> from exerciſing ſeverities againſt men, for being Epiſcopal in their Judgment, that a great part of the Miniſters of that Kingdom, who injoyed not only the Protection of the Government, but the free and Publick Exerciſe of their Miniſtry, together with the legal Eſtabliſhed maintenance before the firſt of <hi>September</hi> laſt, were or profeſſed to be of the Epiſcopal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and had not at that time ſo much as taken the Oath of Allegiance to his Majeſty, and yet of theſe no more is required for their continuance in their Pariſhes, than that they take the ſaid Oath of Allegiance and Aſſurance and that they behave themſelves worthily in Doctrine, Life and Converſation, as appears by the Act of Parliament paſt <hi>July</hi> 16. 1695.</p>
               <p>Before the <hi>D.</hi> can anſwer this he throws himſelf into a paraxiſm of aſtoniſhment, <hi>at thoſe who pretending to be more then ordinary ſtrict and holy Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and the moſt faithful Servants of the God of truth, that they can allow themſelves the liberty of willfully miſrepreſenting the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious matters of Fact, and the plaineſt State of publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and flatly contrary to truth and the mind of the writer;</hi> of which he offers to prove the <hi>V.</hi> ſcandalouſly guilty. But had he rightly pitcht on the guilty, and as truly confeſt his own fault, as he fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly accuſeth the <hi>V.</hi> he might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd compaſſion; to cry out againſt thoſe Sins in others, which we nouriſh in our own Boſoms, is hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>But in anſwer to theſe words, he firſt concedeth a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, <hi>viz. That the Epiſcopal Clergy in</hi> Scotland <hi>have
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:188013:31"/>
enjoyed the free Exerciſe of their Religion and quiet poſſeſſion of their Pariſhes,</hi> &amp;c. which indeed many in the North yet do. But ſaith he, 1. <hi>Theſe Inſtances are but ſeeming favours. 2. They be produc'd as arguments of the moderation of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government, whereas they are nothing elſe but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the weakneſs of the Party.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Protection of the Government in the free and publick Exerciſe of Religion with the Legally eſtabliſht maintenance, be but ſeeming favours: Let the Diſſenters here have only ſuch ſeeming favours and we ſhall promiſe in their name real thanks for the ſame. But, 2. He might have own'd them real favours, had he conſider'd on whom they were confer'd <hi>even the Abetters of Viſcount Dundee's Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> For by his ſilence to the third Paragraph of that Letter, viz. <hi>That at the Abetters of Viſcount Dundee's Rebellion were, or pretended to be of the Epiſcopal perſwaſion, as have alſo all thoſe that have made any Publick Commotion in that Kingdom ſince this happy Revolution,</hi> he tacitly confeſſeth the truth thereof. But thirdly that theſe favours were the effects only of the Presbyterian parties weakneſs, will not be ſo eaſily believed by conſidering men, for why ſhould the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be able to deſtroy the Root, the Biſhops and their prelacy and yet not be able to Lop off the Branches, is improbable: Theſe ſure who could extirpate prelacy in the North, had Power to drive out Curacy there too. But to make it evident that it was not the effect of weakneſs but their moderation, they have now driven out all that rebellious brood, who had contemn'd the King's Clemency and Churches moderation. Yet farther, had the Church of that Kingdom been weak, the State was not, but could eaſily extirpate them, for he is mightily miſtaken of <hi>Scotland,</hi> if he thinks that many of that People would be Martyrs for Prelacy.</p>
               <p>That the Epiſcopal Party in the North are a formidable Party, and therefore kept it depends on the Credit of his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:188013:31"/>
Informers: for were they ſuch as he ſaith, they're neither ſtout nor kind in ſuffering their Reverend Fathers to be laid aſide: Why might not the Children who were able to ſecure themſelves, being ſo formidable, been willing alſo to defend and continue their Fathers? Yet his reaſon to prove them a formidable party, viz. <hi>That part of</hi> Scotland <hi>on the North of</hi> Tay <hi>is known to be little leſs than the half of the Kingdom</hi> is not very formidable: for if the Highlands and Iſles of <hi>Scotland</hi> be comprehended in this, his Geography may hold good, but his reaſon's lame, for he will have little Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of many of the Epiſcopal Highlanders, who poſſeſs more Land than Religion: And that the Epiſcopal Party there is eleven to one, depends on the veracity of his Informers, who, we ſee, are no friends to his Reputation, and will at laſt cauſe him to turn Bankrupt of it, if he continue to give ſuch Left-handed News-mongers ſuch Credit: For deduce from the number Papiſts (the moſt of whom are in the North) he muſt abate of the proportion; for in the Shires of <hi>Sutherland, Stranaver, Roſs</hi> and <hi>Murray</hi> there might be, and hath been a force (which was a terror to it's Enemies) raiſed to defend the Settlement of State and Church. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, conſiderable numbers are in every part of that Country, and theſe as ſtrict as any in <hi>Scotland;</hi> by which we ſee he's little acquainted with the State of that part of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Theſe favors then werenot the effect of weakneſs, but the genuine ſupple fruit of the Clemency and Moderation of that Church, which by long experience of the evil of oppreſſion (which is apt to make wiſe men mad) are reſolved upon it as the ſureſt method to ſecure themſelves; and indeed their moderation is that which now is become moſt formidable to their wiſeſt Enemies, and the true cauſe why not the ſame moderation but diſtinct courſes were taken with the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ergy in the North and in the Weſt, is becauſe the Miniſters in the North were generally men of better Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:188013:32"/>
and Lives, and leſs concern'd in theſe Cruelties and Oppreſſions, by which the Weſt was haraſſed; and ſo, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done leſs harm, were more favoured, while thoſe in the Weſt met with Adonibezek's Reward. Now from all this let the Reader judge if the <hi>D.</hi> had juſt cauſe for his ſo raſh judging the Vindicator.</p>
               <p>His 2. Reaſon to prove the <hi>V. ſcandalouſly guilty of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuity, and repreſenting things contrary to Truth, and his certain knowledge is, that there are no Acts of Parliament in favour of the Epiſcopal Clergy, ſave that of</hi> July 16. 1695. <hi>And therefore leaves it to the Reader to judge what ſort of uſage the Epiſcopal Clergy had for five years past, not only from the unparalell'd rage of a barbarons Rabble, but alſo from the intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate zeal of their bitter and bigotted Enemies in Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We join iſſues with him, in referring to the conſideration of the prudent and impartial Reader, what ſort of uſage the Epiſcopal Miniſters in <hi>Scotland</hi> have had theſe five years paſt, and tho' we think he will be none of theſe Readers, yet let him judge of his own words page 7. where he hath confeſt <hi>that the greateſt part of them</hi> (for theſe in the North he hath laboured to prove ſo) <hi>have had the Protection of the Government in the free and publick Exerciſe of their Religion, and the quiet poſſeſſion of their own Pariſhes, and legal maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, notwithſtanding that they had not taken the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to His Majeſty, nor made any Submiſſion to the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian judicatories.</hi> Is this barbarous uſage? we wiſh the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment here would treat us thus barbarouſly. Let him ſeriouſly reflect on what he ſaith page 10. <hi>Certainly theſe, who refuſe to give the Government under which they live all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable aſſurances of their Fidelity, and Obedience, and will not Diſavow their turbulent Principles, but ſtill retain their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate prejudices, and pernicius Diſaffection to the Eſtabliſhed Church and State, cannot with any Modeſty expect to be treated as ſincere and hearty friends, but as declared and open Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the laſting Peace and Settlement of the Nation.</hi> How appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:188013:32"/>
all this is to his Scotch Brethren, we leave all knowing men to judge: and tho' now that Government might juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy it ſelf, himſelf being judge, tho' they had uſed his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as <hi>declared Enemies to the Peace of that Nation,</hi> becauſe they have hitherto for five years (tho' often required) refuſed to give the Government, under which they liv'd, any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſecurity for their Fidelity and Obedience, yet hath it dealt favourably with them.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>They have made but one Act in their favours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Let us have but one ſuch, tho' two years after theirs, and we ſhall pardon all that's by-paſt. But doth not the Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> think herſelf Eſtabliſhed by one Act of Uniformity, yet it is falſe that they had no more Acts than one paſt in their favours, for <hi>April</hi> 13. 1689. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of States <hi>did prohibit any injury to be done by any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, to any Miniſter of the Goſpel, either in Church or Meeting houſe, who are preſently in poſſeſſion and exerciſe of their Miniſtry.</hi> By this Act a ſtop was put to all Rabbling which had been in the <hi>Interregnum;</hi> and in <hi>Aug</hi> 16. 1689. a Proclamation was iſſued out, <hi>Reſtoring all that had been put out by violence after April</hi> 13. 1689. So that they had more Acts in their favour than they deſerv'd, ſeeing they continued to deny Allegiance to K. <hi>William</hi> and Q <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To what he ſaith of the unparalell'd rage of the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Rabble, (tho' neither Reaſon nor Religion will juſtify tumultous and confuſed out-rages) yet that ſame rage had a paralell in the ſame proportion as near thirty years are to three months, during all which time more blood was ſhed in <hi>Scotland</hi> for Non-conformity, then in the bloody Reign of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> for that which Papiſts call Hereſie. The Act of Council <hi>October</hi> 1662. is another paralell to the Rabb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e's rage, by which 300 legally Eſtabliſh't Miniſters were turn'd out of their Churches and Houſes, without either Citation or Hearing; whereas that Rabble ſome days before-hand gave a Citation to thoſe whom they turn'd out, and told them why they did ſo treat them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:188013:33"/>
Further, 'tis no wonder that this man dare ſpeak evil of Presbyterians as ſuch, when he dare revile the Gods, and ſpeak evil of Dignities; not paying that reſpect to the Authority of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which the Arch-angel paid to the Devil; when, contending with him, he durſt bring no railing accuſation againſt him: but this man dares Arraigne, without diſtinction, the Authority of that Nation, whereof His Majeſty is Head and Fountain, as <hi>Intemperate Zealots and bitter, and bigotted Enemies to Epiſcopal Miniſters.</hi> Had a Diſſenter us'd half ſuch Language, we know who would have cryed out, Crucify him, Crucify him. And indeed ſuch ſcurrilous Language may a waken Authority, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what they may expect from ſome ſort of Clerks, if their Mitres and Bellies be once touched.</p>
               <p>Having railed upon the Authority of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he next falls foul on the Act of Parliament, <hi>July</hi> 16. 1695. notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all it's Clemency; Complaining of it as <hi>a Continuation of Severities.</hi> And that for theſe reaſons, 1. ſaith he, <hi>the favour is granted only to theſe Miniſters who were at His Majeſties Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Crown, and have ſince continued actual Ministers of their particular Pariſhes, and ſo no Proviſion made for thoſe who were Rabbled out, tho' they ſhould take the Oath of Allegiance, &amp;c.</hi> which he hopes the <hi>V.</hi> will allow to be Severity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It needs not be thought ſevere to keep our ſome of thoſe, whom the Rabble put out, ſeeing many of thoſe 300 Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who were thruſt out <hi>October</hi> 1662. by the Counſel without and againſt all Matter or Form of Law, were yet alive; And never were by the prelatical Church it ſelf Canonically ſuſpended or degraded, nor legally deprived by the Magiſtrate, ſo that they'r continued ſtill <hi>dejure</hi> Miniſters of theſe Pariſhes: when then that violence by which they were barred from the Exerciſe of their Miniſtry was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they might peaceably re-enter, having all right to officiate there, there being neither Canonical nor legal Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to obſtruct them; in the ſame manner as the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:188013:33"/>
Incumbents here, (after they were forced from their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in K. <hi>James</hi>'s time) returned to them in K. <hi>William's;</hi> the parallel being the ſame, becauſe the Biſhops came laſt into <hi>Scotland,</hi> not by Law but the Will of the Governor. If any ſeverity by done then it is juſtly deſerved by thoſe, who unjuſtly thruſt themſelves into other mens Poſſeſſions: But 2. many if not all in the Weſt, were violently thruſt in upon the people, to whom by Law the Election of their Miniſters belongs, and therefore they never looked on them as Miniſters, for the Scotch Law allows no man to be put on any Pariſh without the People's Election and Conſent. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain 3. Thoſe men had been active for the moſt part in all the oppreſſions of that People, at leaſt, as Informers and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and were voted by the convention <hi>the griivance;</hi> If then they were happily delivered from the Yoak, which neither they nor their fathers were able to bear, it needs not be wondred at, that the Government was not willing to gall the necks of that People with ſuch yoaks again; Beſides all this, theſe very men were, and are known to be heart-Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Revolution, and were they let in again, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly they would open a door to K. <hi>James</hi>'s re-entry. Let all men judge then if it were not ſevere to humour ſuch men.</p>
               <p>But his other ground of diſſatisfaction with that Act is, <hi>That it excludes thoſe who were under Sentence of Depoſition or Deprivation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Doth not the Law of <hi>England</hi> alſo deprive men of the Benefice, who are degraded from the Office, ſeeing <hi>Beneficium datur propter Officium;</hi> for none were depoſed by Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; but ſuch, whoſe Crimes upon full and fair Tryal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſuch Treatment. Is that ſevere in a Parliament to deny thoſe men wages, who have cut themſelves off from ſervice in the Church.</p>
               <p>Further, to evince the more than ordinary ſeverity in <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt the Epiſcopal Clergy ſince the Revolution,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:188013:34"/>
the <hi>D.</hi> alledgeth an Act of Parliament <hi>June,</hi> 12. 1693. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is is Enacted. <hi>That no Perſon be admitted or continued to be a Miniſter or Preacher within the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he own the Presbyterian Government to be the only Church Government of that Church, that he will ſubmit thereunto, and and concur therewith, and never endeavour directly or indirectly to do any thing to the prejudice or ſubverſion thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The diſingenuity ſo oft complained of in the <hi>V.</hi> ſeems not to be ſo much a diſlike of the evil, as that this <hi>D.</hi> would make a monopoly of it for himſelf; for in this report we have a conſiderable deal of it, for he waves the conſideration of what it was brought to prove, that a great many Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Miniſters enjoyed the Protection of the Government in the free Exerciſe of their Miniſtry, and legally eſtabliſh't maintainance, 2. That the places of greateſt truſt are in the hands of thoſe who are Epiſcopal in Judgment, ſeveral of whom were inſtanced, ſo that no ſeverity is exerciſed meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for mens judgments in that matter, all which by his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence he ſeems to confeſs, and yet inſiſteth in his ordinary rote of of exclaiming againſt the Government, But we ſay, 2. The Act cited doth not inflict any penalty on any for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Epiſcopal in Judgment, 3. There is nothing in this Act but what upon the matter was agreeed to by the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Clergy in their Addreſs preſented to the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of that Church, held <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. 1691/2. with the following Formula they promiſed to Subſcribe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Addreſs of the Epiſcopal Clergy to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly held at</hi> Edinburgh.</head>
               <p>VVE under-ſubſcribers for our ſelves, and our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituent Miniſters of the Goſpel humbly ſhew, that ſince the Epiſcopacy is aboliſhed and Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is eſtabliſhed as it was 1592. we being deſirous to exerciſe the holy Function, wherewith we are inveſted,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:188013:34"/>
in our ſeveral Stations, for the Glory of God, Advancement of Religion, their Majeſties Service, and the Peace of the Nation, do therefore humbly deſire that ſtops and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be taken off, ſo that we may be admitted as Presbyters to ſit in Presbyteries, Synods, and General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies in concurrence with the Presbyterian Miniſters in the Government of the Church as now eſtabliſhed by Law in this Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Formula Propoſed is,</head>
               <p>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do ſincerely Promiſe and Declare, that I will ſubmit to the Presbyterian Government of this Church, as now by Law eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom under K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> by Presbyteries, Provincial Synods, and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſemblies, and that I will as it becomes a Miniſter of the Goſpel, heartily concur with the ſaid Government for the ſuppreſſing of Sin and Wickedneſs, the promoting Peace, and purging the Church of all Erroneous and Seandalous Miniſters, and do further Promiſe that I will Subſcribe the confeſſion of Faith, the Larger and Shorter Catechiſms now Confirmed by Act of Parliament as containing the Doctrine of the Proteſtant Religion Profeſſed in this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>By all this it appears that the Act obliges to nothing but what theſe Addreſſes offered, except a promiſe not to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Government; which they indeed refuſed as a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but we leave the world to judge of the ſincerity of ſuch Miniſters of the Goſpel, who will promiſe to ſubmit to a Government, and concur with it, but will not promiſe not to ſubvert it; but (if needful) we could fully detect to the world the juggle of that whole deſign. But 4. Knows he not that the Act of Uniformity requires the ſame from all Conformiſts, which he exclaims againſt in the Church of <hi>Scotland?</hi> is not then the height of partiality to condemn that as rigid ſeverity in others, which we applaud in our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as Juſtice and Prudence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:188013:35"/>
But his ſecond Exception againſt this Act is, <hi>it's ordering that uniformity of Worſhip and Adminiſtration of all publick Ordinances in the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>be obſerved by all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Preachers, as it is at preſent performed, or ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after declar'd by the Authority of the ſame:</hi> which he looks on as equally unreaſonable, as the Papiſts requiring Implicit Faith, or ſubſcription to the Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is very unjuſt in him to inſtance that as a piece of ſeverity againſt the Epiſcopal Clergy, which by the Act all Presbyterian Miniſters as well as they are obliged to. But if uniformity of Worſhip and Adminiſtration of all publick Ordinances be ſo Popiſh and unreaſonable, why ſo much noiſe about it in his Church? to deprive men of a birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right priviledge, if they comply not: But 'tis Scotiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity only diſguſts him, for what concerns the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Iriſh, he can ſay, <hi>ego mihimet ignoſco.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſaith he, <hi>They are to ſubſcribe to what ſhall be Ordered by the Church, as well as to what is at preſent Ordered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ask him ſeriouſly whether he that ſwears Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Obedience to his Ordinary, doth not oblige him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ruled according to ſuch Canons, as ſhall be made by the Church as well as by theſe which are already made, or when a Judge ſweareth to adminiſter Juſtice according to Law, whether he obligeth not himſelf to Judge by Acts of Parliament that ſhall be made, as well as by thoſe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready are? And if ſo, he dare not ſay, (whatever he may think) that they are guided by an implicit Faith or takes an Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Even ſo when the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> promiſe to govern their flocks, and be governed themſelves by ſuch conſtitutions as are already made, or hereafter ſhall by the common conſent of the Church eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, what man <hi>compos mentis</hi> can condemn them? doth not natures light reach us, that all who join themſelves to a Society ruled by Laws, are obliged to be governed by theſe Laws already made or to be made, eſpecially when
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:188013:35"/>
they are made by themſelves? if this be Popery, he muſt be ſuch, or reſiſt the Government in the execution of Laws made ſince his creation, but men of inconſiderate &amp; ſlippery judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be dilemma'd.</p>
               <p>His laſt inſtance of Scotiſh ſeverity is from an Act made <hi>July</hi> 5. 1695. againſt Intruders, by whom are underſtood all who have not an orderly call from the Heritors, Elders, and People, with a legal Admiſſion by the Presbytery; now ſuch by that Law are to be removed from theſe Churches, into which they have intruded, and rendred incapable of any Church or Stipend within the Kingdom for ſeven years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but he tells, <hi>that by theſe Intruders are chiefly means Epiſcopal Miniſters thruſt out by the Rabble, who had repoſſeſs'd their own Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Act was made againſt allIntruders without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, Presbyterian, or others; and we ſuppoſe thought Rational by all reaſonable men, for the Engliſh Law juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies not a forcible Entry, even tho' a Perſon hath a right. And I doubt not, but the Church of <hi>Engl.</hi> would condemn it in her own caſe: for I queſtion if the <hi>D.</hi> could defend the late Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Connor</hi> with the Arch-Deacon, (who looked on themſelves unjuſtly deprived of Biſhopprick and Livings by the late Regal viſitation) ſhould they re-enter and poſſeſs themſelves of what they have loſt, without own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church or State.</p>
               <p>But we ſay that thoſe who were rabbled out, neither have nor dare intrude into thoſe Churches from which they were rabbled, and challengeth him to inſtance one who hath ſo done. But the truth of the matter is this, ſome of thoſe who were rabbled out in the Weſt and South, went to the North, and there by the connivance of the Inheritors, and ſome of the Pariſhioners did intrude into vacant Pariſhes: ſome alſo had been depoſed by the Church for Immoralities, others who were put out of their Benefices by the Counſel, for refuſing to ſwear Allegiance to K. <hi>William,</hi> and ſupported
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:188013:36"/>
by the Jacobite party, did enter into Churches in contempt of both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Government. Againſt theſe this Act was made, ſo that none are counted Intruders, meenly for repoſſeſſing the Church out of which they were turned by the Rabble, ſeeing that by the Proclamation <hi>Aug.</hi> 6. 1689. all who had been Rabbled ſince the Settlement of the Government, were reſtored to their Churches.</p>
               <p>By this the <hi>D.</hi> (as he thinks having <hi>proved the Parliament of</hi> Scotland <hi>guilty of great Severity, for making an Act againſt Intruders) concludes, undoubtedly the reaſon of the</hi> V's. <hi>not publiſhing that Act of Parliament</hi> July 16. 1695. <hi>not to be what is alledged, but his fear of ſetting matters in a true light, and expoſing too plainly his groſs and willful miſrepreſentations of the preſent State of that Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We leave it to the Parliament of <hi>Ireland,</hi> whether they will thank him for inveighing againſt the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> thus at random, when both have the ſame head, and in all theſe Invectives his Sacred Majeſty is reflected on: But how ridiculous is it to reaſon thus? The Vindicator durſt not publiſh the Act of <hi>July</hi> 16. 1695. leſt he ſhould have expoſed the ſeverity of the Parliament againſt Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, when there is nothing in that Act againſt Intruſion, but it is, (as himſelf tells us) by an Act <hi>July</hi> 5. 1695. what needs the <hi>V.</hi> fear the publiſhing that Act, which all allow to be an Act of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emency, we are ſatisfied the <hi>V.</hi> had not ſeen that againſt which he ſo much Inveighs: Nor needed he fear the publiſhing that other Act which was in Print: yea ſo far were Diſſenters, from any ſear from that Act that they induſtriouſly ſpread it amongſt Members of Parliament here, as a good precedent of Moderation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>D.</hi> having diſcharg'd his ſpleen upon the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> returns upon the Church Government, ſaying, by way of mock, <hi>I muſt indeed acknowledge that we cannot boaſt of our coming up to, or equal in the example which the preſent Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government in</hi> Scotland <hi>has ſet us. For firſt, our mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:188013:36"/>
to Diſſenters has not expreſt it ſelf in raiſing of the Rabble againſt them; much leſs in returning them publick and ſolemn thanks for the greatneſs of their Zeal in ſo doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His firſt inſtance of this Churches negative moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Diſſenters, contains an unreaſonable calumny thrown upon the Presbyterian Government of the Ch. of <hi>Scotl.</hi> for during the Rabble's Reign, there was no legal Government in Church or State: And therefore the Church is not chargeable with things done before it was re-eſtabliſhed or had power. That the Church gave the Rabble publick and ſolemn Thanks for their Rabbling, is falſe; but the truth was this, the Prelates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the Jacobitiſh Party, headed by the Viſcount <hi>Dundee,</hi> having conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Convention of States, then aſſembled at <hi>Edenburg,</hi> to ſettle the Crown of that Kingdom upon K <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> had ſecretly conveyed 200 and upwards of armed men into the Town, in order to ſcatter the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo defeat the Nations Settlement. Hereupon the Gentlemen and Commons of the Weſt, being then in Arms, came with all expedition to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> whereupon the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Dundee</hi> with his party immediately fled and entred into an open Rebellion, which ended with his Life at <hi>Killy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crankie.</hi> Theſe Gentlemen who protected the Convention of Eſtates, till they had eſtabliſhed the Government, are by him and his Epiſcopal Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> called the Rabble. Theſe indeed received the publick thanks of the Convention of Eſtates, inſtead of their pay, and ſo went all home peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. But at this time there could be no Eſtabliſh't Church, ſeeing there was no Eſtabliſh't Civil Government.</p>
               <p>2. That he and his have not raiſed the Rabble againſt Diſſenters in <hi>Ireland,</hi> we owe not to him or his, but to the Rabble (if any ſuch be) who if once up might poſſibly turn their rage upon others. Yet he and ſome of his have not failed to incenſe the Magiſtrate againſt Diſſenters, who have thereupon imploy'd arm'd force againſt them: For
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:188013:37"/>
notwithſtanding all that the Diſſenting Miniſters had ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>North</hi> for their Loyalty to <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. (being all bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>Oliver</hi> for refuſing the Oath called the <hi>Tender,</hi> which many Epiſcopal Clergy-men eaſily ſwallow'd) yet upon his Reſtauration the Prelates ſtirr'd him up, contrary to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, to impriſon all Diſſenting Miniſters, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the People for Non-conformity, which was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly done: This, the Living Generation can abundantly Teſtify.</p>
               <p>A Second Evidence of the Churches Moderation to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters he offers, is, <hi>That the Church of</hi> England <hi>Parliament, in this Kingdom, has not declared that Non-Conformiſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, in exerciſing any part of their Miniſterial Function, have offer'd a high contempt of the Law, as tending to perpetuate Schiſm, and of dangerous conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Seeing, as he ſaith, <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>Parliament hath not declared Non-Conformiſt Miniſters contemners of the Law, in exerciſing any part of their Miniſtry.</hi> How cometh it to paſs, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> Clergy daily declare them guilty of offering high contempt to the Law? As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Schiſmaticks; that the exerciſe of their Miniſtry is of dangerous conſequence. We have cauſe to thank the Church of <hi>England</hi> Parliament, for their Juſtice and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; but neither of us have reaſon to thank the Clergy for declaring the contrary. And tho we may be ſatisfied with this Confeſſion, that there is no Act of Parliament againſt us, vet we have cauſe to fear he will retract, elſe he hath labour'd in vain in this Pamphlet.</p>
               <p>The third Inſtance given of the Churches Moderation to us, is, <hi>They have not made an Act of Parliament againſt ut, making Non-Conforming Miniſters Intruders, (altho they be really ſuch) into Pariſhes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Law doth not make Non-Conforming Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Intruders, by what Law doth he call them ſo? The Law of the Land he vindicates from this Aſperſion, and we
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:188013:37"/>
are ſure the Law of God layeth no ſuch crime to our charge. For Miniſters, duly qualified, and by the unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a Chriſtian People, elected and call'd to be their Miniſters, are not intruders, tho' their Election be not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſy'd by the Civil Sanction; elſe all the Miniſters of the Goſpel for the firſt 300 years of Chriſtianity had been In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders. That a Chriſtian People have power to Elect and call their own Miniſters is according to the Primitive Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Rule <hi>Lib. 1. Ep. 4.</hi> is conſonant to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>viz. Plebs ipſa, poteſtatem habet vel eligendi dig nos ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes vel indig nos recuſandi.</hi> And even in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, in Pope <hi>Leo</hi>'s time, it was a Rule, <hi>Qui prae futurus eſt omnibus ab omnibus Elegatur.</hi> And ſuch we are able to make appear our Election to the Miniſtry to be.</p>
               <p>2. Nor hath the Parl. of <hi>Scotland</hi> made any Act againſt intruding into Pariſhes, but againſt intruding into Churches and ſeizing upon Manſes and Glebs: which if <hi>N. C's.</hi> here had done; it's poſſible they had both heard and felt that there are Acts of Parl. againſt ſuch intruders.</p>
               <p>The fourth inſtance of Moderation is that <hi>the Eſtabliſh'd Church hath not forbid theſe Diſſenters, whom the Calamities of the late times had driven away, to return and perform any Miniſterial Acts in the places where formerly they held their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles for want of a Legal Call.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Had Diſſenters as obſtinately refuſed to ſwear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to K. <hi>W.</hi> and Q. <hi>M.</hi> as his Epiſcopal Brethren did in <hi>Scotland:</hi> we ſhou'd have had as little favour as the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurant Clergy there have had, and juſtly deſerv'd it. But why the Government of <hi>Scotland</hi> only ſhou'd be condemn'd for ſeverity, when both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> the Non-ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Biſhops and Clergy have met with the ſame meaſure, and yet he dates not tax the Government here, or in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of ſeverity upon that account, ſo that he is either groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impartial, or a Jacobite in heart, tho' he appear for King <hi>William.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:188013:38"/>
The Fifth Inſtance of Moderation, is, <hi>That they have not here authorized or required the Mayors of Corporations, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace, to remove all thoſe who have intruded, or ſhall intrude, as they have done in</hi> Scotland.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Civil Magiſtrate were ſubject to the Authority of the Church, we have cauſe to be confident of being otherwiſe dealt with than at preſent we are, God be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for it. We think he deſerves a fee, if he'll make good that Diſſenters may, without counter acting Acts of Parl. enter and poſſeſs Churches and Tythes: but then why makes he ſuch a hideous out-cry againſt the Miniſter of <hi>Letterkenny</hi> for his intruſion.</p>
               <p>His Sixth and laſt Inſtance of Moderation exceeding that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is, <hi>that they have not ordered Writs of Rebellion againſt Diſſenting Miniſters, in order to the removing them out of Pariſhes where they live, and making them deſiſt from exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing Miniſterial Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For all this boaſted of Moderation, the time was when there were Writs out againſt all the Diſſenting Miniſters to apprehend them, whereupon many were apprehended and impriſon'd, which is well known. And we owe but little thanks to Church-men for the mercy we now enjoy. But by this he inſinuates, that the Epiſcopal Clergy are by Writs and <hi>Capias</hi>'s driven from living in any Pariſhes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which is a Calumny, and by it we may ſee how ſafe his Majeſty's Government is like to be, under ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors of Conſcience, who labour to poſſeſs his Subjects againſt him and his Government, as cruel and ſevere, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Clemency he has us'd to ſuch as are declar'd Enemies to his Authority.</p>
               <p>The <hi>D.</hi> having triumph'd in the victory of the Eſtabliſh't Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> over that of <hi>Scotland</hi> in point of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſeems to be mov'd with a Prophetick Spirit, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, that <hi>in caſe ſuch Revolution of Church Affairs ſhould happen in this Kingdom, as hath lately been in</hi> Scotland; <hi>the</hi> V.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:188013:38"/>
                  <hi>and his Adherents would imitate the Presbyterians in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and make the Epiſcopal Clergy deſiſt from exerciſing any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Acts, and Iſſue out Writs of Rebellion againſt them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Either he fears, what he ſuppoſeth, will come to paſs, or not. If he doth really fear ſuch Revolution, then we think 'twere his wiſdom to be preparing an Ark for ſaving himſelf and houſhold: tho it be no policy to declare his fears, ſeeing thereby he incourageth Diſſenters, and weakens the hands of his Friends, by repreſenting us as a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble party: But if he believes no probability of what he ſuppoſeth he needs not trouble us or his party with ſuch Prophecies; for if he were not conſcious to himſelf that he had deſerved ill of Diſſenters, he would not fear ill from them.</p>
               <p>To make his Prophecy probable, he tells us, that the Profeſſors in Colleges of <hi>Scotland</hi> felt the rigor of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Viſitation, which he calls by the odious name of <hi>Inquiſition practiſed upon the Profeſſor of the College of Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> in <hi>Aug.</hi> and <hi>Sept.</hi> 1690. according to an Act paſſed the <hi>4th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1690. By which it is ordered, that no Miniſter or Profeſſor in any College or School ſhall be allowed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Exerciſe of his Function, but ſuch as ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Confeſſion of Faith ratify'd by this preſent Parliament, and ſubmit to the Government of the Church now Eſtabliſht by Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To ſtigmatize the Viſitors of the Univerſity's acting by his Majeſty's Commiſſion, and Parliamentary Authority with the odious name of Inquiſitors, and the Viſitation with the name of Inquiſition, doth palpably inſinuate, that tho the Heroick Anceſtors of our King did drive the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition out of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> yet he and his Queen have brought it into <hi>Scotland.</hi> And tho he will ſwear he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>flection on his Majeſty, yet it's too apparent he would make him, and theſe acting by Authority under him, ſucceſſors to St. <hi>Dominick.</hi> 2. He falſely attributes to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:188013:39"/>
the Church the Act of the State. 3. When he wou'd prove a removal of Perſons Epiſcopal from Civil Employments he inſtances in Profeſſors of Divinity, which are not eſteem'd Civil Employments in <hi>Scotland.</hi> 4. The ground of their removal was their refuſing to ſwear Allegiance to K. <hi>W.</hi> and Q <hi>M.</hi> and the reaſon they gave for their refuſal was that they were not crown'd K. and Q. of <hi>Scotland,</hi> tho' they made no ſuch ſcruple of ſwearing to K. <hi>James,</hi> whether or no by juſtifying them in this he partake with them in their evil deeds, let all Men judge. 5. It's highly hypocritical to rail at that as Sin in others which we applaud in ourſelves as a Vertue, for what more criminal is it in the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> to oblige its Profeſſors of Divinity to ſubſcribe its legally Eſtabliſh'd Doctrin, and to ſubmit to its legally E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh'd Church-Government, then it is in the Church of <hi>England</hi> to require Subſcription to their 39 Articles, Aſſent and Conſent to her Liturgy and Ceremonies, and Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Obedience to her Biſhops.</p>
               <p>For an Epilogue to his Hiſtory of Scots Affairs, ſince the Revolution, he gives a mock Commendation (as he is pleas'd to call it) <hi>the ingenuous temper of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in their Act for a ſolemn National Faſt.</hi> Nov. 12. 1690. wherein they gave a particular Confeſſion of the Sins of the Nation. To which he ſaith, <hi>Amen,</hi> wiſhing they may be as ſincere in repenting, as they have been ingenious in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To have our Prayers and Faſts turned to reproach, is but what befel our betters, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 10. and therefore we may the eaſier bear it; but doth not the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> dayly confeſs, we have erred and ſtrayed from thy ways; we have done theſe things which we ought not to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to require his Charity to the Church of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſh him ingealous and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:188013:39"/>
The D. having made his progreſs through <hi>Scotland,</hi> in his return home to <hi>Ireland,</hi> gives us a taſte of his skill in perſuading, while he would have us believe, that <hi>the gently Penal Laws, are not (as the V. inſinuates) a ſevere laſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd as Inſtruments of an Unreaſonable Correction, but as the neceſſary means of keeping ſuch Children, as are of a froward and ungovernable temper, within the bounds of a due Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and therefore it ought not to be eſteemed an unkind ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but a prudent tenderneſs in a Parent, to deny them ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, as in all propability will be abuſed, to the dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing him of his Parental Authority, and to the incouraging of them, to a total withdrawing of their Filial Duty and Obedience for the future.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This <hi>D.</hi> ſeems to be, or at leaſt wou'd have Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be, like the Wives of <hi>Maſcovy,</hi> who are jealous of their Husbands affection unleſs they correct them ſeverely; But he muſt beat us out of reaſon and ſenſe both, e're he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade us to this, and had he but taſted as much of theſe gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Penal Laws as ſome have lately done, for refuſing the Oath of a Church-Warden, he wou'd change his Note. If to be Excommunicated, thrown into Priſon, till a Man and his Family be utterly ruin'd, be gentle correction, how dares he exclaim againſt the ſeverity of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where there is not one ſuch Penal Law, nor one inſtance of a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's being fin'd, and impriſoned, for meer Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, much leſs for refuſing to be Lay-Elders. And we ſuppoſe he cannot give inſtance, of any Church in the World, who Excommunicate, Fine and Impriſon Men for refuſing to be Officers in the Church, eſpecially theſe, whom they condemn as Schiſmaticks. And to thruſt Men into Places of Truſt in the Church out of Malice. That many more Epiſcopal Children, have diſcover'd their froward and ungovernable temper (ſince the happy Revolution) then of Diſſenters, is ſenſibly felt by the Government, and therefore the reflection on us hath as little Truth as Charity.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:188013:40"/>
Nor is it rational to ſuppoſe us ſuch enemies to our own caſe, and peace, as to endeavour to diveſt theſe of Authority, by whoſe powerful Clemency we are protected from the claws of ſome of the angry Clergy.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond thing deſired by Diſſenters, <hi>viz. That there be no ſuch Clauſes annexed to the Bill of Indulgence, as might diſenable them from ſerving their King, and Country, he obſerves to be the ſame Argument the Papiſts made uſe of in the late Reign for taking off the Penal Laws and Teſt, and that the deſign of Diſſenters is the ſame, with that of the Papiſts,</hi> viz. <hi>not only to capacitate themſelves for all Employments, of Honour, Truſt and Profit, but alſo to exclude others, of a different per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, from having a ſhare in any, unleſs perhaps in mean and unprofitable ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Obſervation (tho his own) is not obſervable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for it's Wit or Honeſty, for if Diſſenters ought not to uſe the Argument, becauſe Papiſts have us'd it; then the Church ought far leſs to Croſs in Baptiſm and kneel at the Sacrament, ſeeing the Papiſts have greſly abuſed them. But it's well known that Diſſenters did refuſe, to joyn with the Papiſts in taking off the penal Laws and Teſt, tho they thereby might have had their own Fetters knockt off; yet they rather chus'd to continue in chains, then to ſuffer ſuch ravenous Creatures to run looſe; And we remember what fair promiſes were then made to Diſſenters, for this piece of generoſity, but the world knows how religiouſly theſe promiſes have been kept. And he may ſee that where Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians have more then we deſire, they have not ingroſs'd to themſelves, all places of Honour and Truſt, as now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where ſuch imployments are enjoy'd, by Perſons declared Epiſcopal in Judgment; And its ridiculous to tell, that Diſſenters won'd inhanfe all imployments, to thoſe of their own perſwaſion, and exclude others, ſeeing all of them are not of one perſuaſion, and ſo cannot inhance all to their own Party. But unleſs the Magiſtrates (to whom the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:188013:40"/>
grant of ſuch Offices belongs) ſhou'd turn Diſſenters, it's unreaſonable to fear that Diſſenters ſhou'd be able to make ſuch a Monopoly.</p>
               <p>While he tells us <hi>That it's not reaſonable that they ſhou'd pull down any part of their Church, to furniſh Diſſenters with Materials to build and ſtrenthen theirs.</hi> We muſt ſay that we knew not before now, that Penal Laws againſt Diſſenters were any part or parcel of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> which if they be, as is ſaid, it will be no demonſtration of that Churches Antiquity, at leaſt for that part of it: which muſt commence with the Act of Uniformity. Surely the Primitive Church had no ſuch Pillars to ſupport it, for 300 years and more, and yet the Gates, of Hell were not able to prevail againſt it. Bp. <hi>Taylor</hi> liberty of propheſying p. 18. will better inform him <q>That impoſing on Mens underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, being Maſters of their Conſciences, and Lording it over their Faith, came in with the rotinue and train of Antichriſt, The increaſe of Intereſt, and abatement of Chriſtian Simplicity, when the Churches Fortune grew better, and her Sons grew worſe, and ſome of her Fathers worſt of all. And cites <hi>Tertullian,</hi> ſaying, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d nec Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eſt cogere religionem, quae ſuſcipi debet ſponte non vi.</hi> To this he adds, That all wiſe Princes till they were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n with Faction, or ſollicited by peeviſh Perſons, gave To eration to different Sects, whoſe opinions did not diſturb the Publick Intereſt. Heretical Perſons who are impatient of an Adverſary, were the firſt, who intreated the Emperors to perſecute the Catholicks, but till 400 years after Chriſt, no Catholick Perſons, or very few, did provoke the ſecular Arm, or implore its aid againſt Hereticks.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>D.</hi> having given his judgment with more paſſion than truth, againſt Diſſenters, particularly theſe in the North, to make it appear reaſonable (as he ſaith), he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to prove it by matter of fact ſince the Revolution,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:188013:41"/>
atteſted by ſeveral perſons of known Prudence and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in the North, who have given an account of many hard things againſt two Miniſters there, both doctrinal and practical; the firſt of theſe is Mr. <hi>Liſton,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Letterkenny;</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> is Mr. <hi>William Holms.</hi> Mr. <hi>Liſton</hi> is accuſed, <hi>Firſt, of conſtant declaring the Church of</hi> England <hi>Popiſh and Antichriſtian. 2. Praying for its deſtruction. 3. Preacb'd againſt its Feaſtivals, and ſaid that they worſhiped the Devil. 4. Diſcharg'd his Hearers to entertain any Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts as Servants, but allow'd them to keep Popiſh Servants. 5. That he perſwaded the Parents of a Gentlewoman who had conformed, to deny her Meat, Drink, and Lodging, and to hang her for her Apoſtacy. 6. He abus'd the Legal Incumbent, and pull'd him out of the Church of</hi> Letterkenny.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Were this heavy charge as fully proven, as it's confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently alledged, it would not amount to all that's intended thereby, <hi>viz.</hi> To make all the Diſſenting Miniſters of the North odious to the Government, as a factious and violent people; no more, than the Simony, Adultery, Drunkenneſs, habitual Non-Reſidence, and neglect of Office prov'd againſt the Biſhop and Clergy of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Connor,</hi> at the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Viſitation, will prove all the Clergy of <hi>Ireland</hi> guilty of the ſame crimes: Tho ſome are of opinion, that thoſe on whom that Tower of <hi>Siloam</hi> fell, were not the only Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,; but if other Dioceſſes had umdergone the ſame Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deal, theſe condemned might have ſome comfort in having more companions. If any deſiderate proof of this, they ſhall have ſatisfaction from more Authentick Records than theſe produc'd to prove Mr. <hi>Liſton</hi>'s Lybel.</p>
               <p>2. Had he deſign'd impartial juſtice in this matter, he had been as particular in naming the witneſſes, as he is in naming the accuſed, and their crimes; for before judgment paſs, the Law allows the Accuſed to ſee their Witneſſes, to know if they have any exceptions againſt them; but by his hiding them, he gives the world ground to ſuſpect they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:188013:41"/>
are not evidence beyond exception. And ſeeing the Civil Law denies them to be good evidence, or have been but lately reconcil'd: for this cauſe, <hi>in offenſus affectus ieſtiam queritur ne irati nocere cupiant laeſi ulciſci ſe velint.</hi> We have cauſe to ſuſpect the Evidence; for thoſe who perſecute men when alive, and reproach them when dead, are not their friends. Yea, all this evidence is but on hear-ſay, ſeeing we have it from Conforming Clergy, who could no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways know what he Preach'd and Prayed conſtantly, but by others teſtimony: And the Law ſaith, <hi>Teſtimonium quod ab aliena relatione dependet non valet.</hi> And indeed, to accuſe a man long after his death, as here Mr. <hi>Liſton</hi> is, when yet while alive, he was not purſu'd (though the Law both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical was open to them, and the faults, if proved, puniſhable by the Judge) is contrary to the Light of Nature, and Law of Nations, which teach, that <hi>Citatio &amp; defenſio ſunt juris naturalis,</hi> and condemn no man uncited, unheard. The Civil Law ſays, that <hi>ſententia contra mortuos ferenda non eſt;</hi> for that were, <hi>cum larvis pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare,</hi> to fight with mens ghoſts, which is neither Humanity nor Religion. And ſeveral of the things aſſerted are ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, that they muſt be ſcant in Charity who believe them.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>2d</hi> Inſtance of Mr. <hi>W. H.</hi> It's an arrow out of the ſame quiver, the perſon being a Probationer, upon the rumor of what is here alledg'd, was call'd to account for it, but vindicated himſelf ſufficiently, whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears we incourage no ſuch intemperate, and indiſcreet actions amongſt any of our perſuaſion, but bring them to account for it; and we know by whoſe induſtry all the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea Legenda</hi> that can be collected in that part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, are confidently publiſhed with <hi>teſte meipſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From theſe Inſtances he draws, as he calls it, an <hi>undoubted concluſion, that if Diſſenters had the uncontrolable liberty of a legal irreſtrictive Indulgence, they wou'd be moſt turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:188013:42"/>
inſolent, and tumultuous, which he proves by the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation made by the Houſe of Commons to King</hi> Charles <hi>the</hi> 2d <hi>above 30 years ago, as we heard before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Were theſe two Inſtances as true, as we have made them appear to be falſe and malicious; his concluſion might be doubted, as much as a concluſion from the many Inſtances of Simony, Adultery, Drunkenneſs, and conſtant Non-Reſidence judicially proved at the late Regal Viſitation at <hi>Lisburn,</hi> to prove all the Clergy of <hi>Ireland</hi> guilty of theſe Crimes; and ſeeing he can produce no Inſtances of intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſpeeches, and illegal violences of Diſſenters in the <hi>North,</hi> except theſe two pretended: this may ſatisfie the Government how far we are from ſuch a diſtemper as he reproaches us with, tho we have had provocations from the intemperate ſpeeches of ſome Clergy-men.</p>
               <p>As for his only ſtrong Argument; <hi>his fear of the increaſe of the power and number of Diſſenters, and therefore the Eſtabliſh't Church ſhould not be over-fond of theſe ſeeming Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His Party hath no cauſe to thank him for his policy; for by repreſenting the Diſſenters as ſo formidable a party, he encourageth them, and weakens the hearts and hands of his Brethren by theſe frightful Propheſies: If he be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally affraid of our power and increaſe, his wiſdom will be ſeaſonably to yield, and unite with us: For theſe penal Laws have not leſſened our numbers, or weakened our power, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſince their commencement we are in <hi>Ireland</hi> 100 to one; and if upwards of 100 years experience of the abſolute in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of theſe Laws to prevent the daily growth of Diſſenter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the Eſtabliſh't Church will not convince him of their being uſeleſs Engines to defend it, we cannot help him more than theſe do his cauſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>V.</hi> having urg'd, <hi>That a Legal Indulgence was needful, in caſe another Rebellion, which God forbid ſhould happen: elſe what Gentleman among us wou'd riſe, for others to command? or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:188013:42"/>
wou'd Tenants cheerfully riſe with them on whom they have no dependance? and in whom they can as little truſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>D.</hi> tells us <hi>there's no danger of that, for the generality of the Nobility and Gentry of the North are Conformiſts, their Landlords, and Acquaintances, and men of great Eſtates to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Nobility and Gentry that are Conformiſts, who in the late troubles promiſed fair things to Diſſenters, ſhou'd by the importunity of ſome of the hotter Clergy, be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſuaded, contrary to their own moderate temper and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eit that place they have now in the eſteem of Diſſenters; it would be impoſſible to induce reaſonable men to truſt them in a time of War, who had deceiv'd them in a time of Peace. But we hope the Nobility and Gentry value as and their own intereſt more, than to ſacrifice both to ſome implacable men for Ceremonies. It would be no prudence to provoke ſuch multitudes, which in times of confuſion little regard ſuch diſtinctions as in Peace they do; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther follow whom they love, and have been obliged by, than them they ſuſpect, and have been hurt by.</p>
               <p>That thoſe who ſhut the Gates of <hi>Derry</hi> were Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and thoſe who were Governors in it the time of the Siege, is aſſerted with more vanity than truth, if he ſay they were the only perſons: But as both parties were united in heart and hand in that matter, ſo we ſhall not divide them in the praiſe: Tho we believe, what's well known, that the common Souldiers were the Governors, elſe it ſeems the Event had prov'd worſe than it did.</p>
               <p>As to his credible information, <hi>that in the ſuccesful party at</hi> Enni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>killen, <hi>there was not one Commiſſion Officer, not ſo much as one Enſign, that was not of the Eſtabliſh't Church, and of the private Centinels, there were ſix Conformiſts to one Diſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We fear his Informers have impoſed too much on his credulity, and to the hazard of his reputation, have employ'd
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:188013:43"/>
him to retail many untruths. For we are as fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the contrary, as we can be of a thing of that nature, having it from thoſe who know well, that there were above eight Captains of the Presbyterian perſwaſion before, and at the Troubles, and ſome of us have been at the Tent of one of them at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> whoſe Father and Grandfather were Presbyterian Miniſters of good eſteem in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and is now in the Army in <hi>Flanders.</hi> There were ſeven Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and ſeveral Enſigns, whoſe names we ſhall not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh without their leave. Mr. <hi>Kelſo</hi> the Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter at <hi>Enniskillen,</hi> while he lived was very active, and died at <hi>Enniskillen:</hi> at that time one of his Congregation had a Company conſiſting of 140 men. It's true, moſt of them occaſionally heard the Church of <hi>England</hi> Miniſters; and after Mr. <hi>Kelſo</hi>'s death, and the removal of the reſt, they had none elſe to hear, yet declared they themſelves Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, and the moſt of them who are alive, do ſo ſtill: And he muſt allow us to know our own better than he doth. But as we do not take all for ours who come occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally to hear us, no more ought he to take all for his, who occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally hear him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>V</hi>'s Argument againſt the Teſt, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England</hi> had thought the Sacramental Teſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they cou'd eaſily have added it, as they have the Teſt againſt Popery mentioned in the ſame Act. We have this Anſwer: <hi>If the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>had intended to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Proteſtant Diſſenters in this Kingdom from a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Teſt, as they had to the Teſt againſt Popery, they might have as eaſily forbid the former, as they have poſitively enjoyn'd the latter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Anſwer is a weak Brother to ſome of the reſt; for if the Parliament doth not enjoyn, we think they do excuſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and had they not enjoyn'd an Act of Uniformity, we think we ſhou'd be excuſed for our Non conformity; for where there's no Law, there's no tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:188013:43"/>
The Charge given againſt <hi>Diſſenters in the North for not paying Conformiſt Miniſters their dues, till his Majeſty put forth his Royal Proclamation for payment of them,</hi> is not fairly ſaid. <hi>1ſt,</hi> Becauſe all the Diſſenters were not guilty, ſeveral of thoſe who ſtaid in K. <hi>James</hi>'s time, and had Stocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the lower part of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim</hi> did pay to theſe Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents who ſtaid with them. <hi>2d,</hi> The Conformiſts were as guilty of this as Diſſenters; the reaſon of both was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability in the moſt parts, having nothing left to ſupport their lives and families; and when the Army came where there was any thing, they took free quarters. And as they were not able, ſo they thought not themſelves bound in Conſcience to maintain Non-Reſidents and Pluraliſts, who, had they not been prodigal in time of Peace, had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der little neceſſity. Beſides, ſome of the Clergy were in <hi>England,</hi> ſome Chaplains in the Army; yea, ſome of the Clergy will confeſs, that they were more kindly and juſtly dealt with by Diſſenters, than by their own people, as all moderate men did find, and will upon ſuch occaſions. But if this was injuſtice, the Landlords ſuffer'd far more, who got nothing, and after the troubles did freely forgive one, two, or three years Rent, and yet make no noiſe. It's well known the Biſhops did not abate one farthing of their Rents, even for thoſe times in which they could not keep their Tenants in peaceable poſſeſſion, which ſeverity was ſo much reſented by ſome Conforming Gentlemen, that they threaten'd to turn Presbyterians on that account.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>D</hi>'s great fears, <hi>that if the deſired liberty were granted to Diſſenters, the door being once opened, they wou'd all ruſh into the profitable and honorable Employments.</hi> This ſhews an earthly conſtitution of Soul, to have fears and cares mainly employ'd about things ſecular, and like <hi>Demetrius,</hi> who, tho he pretended the glory of the <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> yet his and the Craftſ-men's trouble, was, the fear of the loſs of their wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:188013:44"/>
In defence of the Sacramental Teſt, the <hi>D.</hi> tells us, they do not drive any to the Sacrament; but ſince the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is God's Vice-Gerent, it's ſurely not unfit that he ſhou'd imitate Almighty God, whom he repreſents, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing temporal advantages, as encouragement to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of religious actions; and they are beſt qualify'd for publick Employments of the greateſt profit, truſt and honor, that give moſt publick and ſignal evidence of their piety towards God, and obedience to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Is it not driving to the Sacrament, when men are forc'd to it under pain of being driven to the Devil? See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as refuſe to communicate with the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are to be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> according to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non 9. of the Conſtitution 1603, and Canon 5. Conſtitution 1641. And is it not to drive men, when they muſt either quit their Civil Employments, and be made incapable of them; and to ſtarve themſelves and families, unleſs they will Communicate according to the form preſcrib'd? And do not we daily ſee, that all the Souldiers are forc'd to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, how ignorant and vicious ſoever they be? elſe they loſe their pay.</p>
               <p>That Civil Magiſtrates may encourage thoſe that do well, and be terrors to evil doers, we fully believe; but that kneeling at receiving the Sacrament (about which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between you and us is) is a religious action, or a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and ſignal obedience of piety to God; we admire how you dare aſſert, ſeeing he hath no where required it at our hands; and there are true acts of piety to God, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Magiſtrate, which we ſee are not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as this act of Will-worſhip is: And why one ſingle Ceremony ſhou'd be made the teſt of our piety to God, and obedience to the Civil Magiſtrate, no man can give a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional account. <hi>That there be ſo many of the Eſtabliſh't Church fitly prepared according to the Rubrick for reception of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:188013:44"/>
Sacrament as are fit for all the profitable and honorable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments,</hi> we are ſatisfied; but are forty that ſo ſmall a proportion of them fall in the hands of ſuch, and that they are treated no better than Diſſenters for the moſt part<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while ſome, whoſe Rubrick fitneſs is ſhrewdly ſuſpected, thrive better.</p>
               <p>As to what the <hi>V.</hi> ſays of the modes of Receiving the Sacrament, who is againſt making ſitting, ſtanding, or kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only poſture of Receiving: we muſt allow him to abound in his own ſenſe; but know that the moſt part of Presbyterians and Independants in <hi>Ireland</hi> are otherwiſe minded: who all judge and declare, that the Table geſture in receiving the Sacrament, and not the Adoration, is moſt agreeable to the firſt pattern given us by Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and practiſed in the Primitive Church: and to charge the ſitting poſture with undecency, is an undecent reflection upon Chriſt and his Apoſtles. That the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the poſture of Adoration, was not brought into the Church until the <hi>14th</hi> Century, and that only into the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Church, with the opinion of the corporal preſence, is ſo well known, that it cannot modeſtly be deny'd. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Diſſenters wonder that ſo late an invention, brought into the Church upon ſo bad an occaſion, and for worſe ends, ſhou'd be inſiſted upon by perſons proſeſſing reverence to Antiquity, and declare their abhorrence of corrupting the doctrine of the Sacrament, with its ill conſequence.</p>
               <p>Yet we do not ſee what danger the Church is in, of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>its Authority infringed, or Laws nulled by the V</hi>'s opinion; who, tho he looks upon ſitting, ſtanding, or kneeling, too narrow incloſures, to keep people from the Lord's Table, yet will, it ſeems, allow liberty to Churches to determine in theſe things as they ſhall ſee meet.</p>
               <p>As for the Churches Authority to make Laws: 1. We think her power not Legiſlative, but Miniſterial, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Divine Laws. 2. That her Conſtitutions, at ſuch,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:188013:45"/>
do not immediately and directly bind the Conſcience. 3. That her Authority to appoint Rites and Ceremonies of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical ſignification, or as parts of Worſhip, is none. 4. That her power is in determining Circumſtances, and that theſe determinations are of the ſame extent and continuance with the reaſons thereof; and that all her Concluſions, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Edification, Order, Unity and Peace of Chriſt, are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void, and nullities. So that the world needs not be ſo much terrify'd with that great word, Church Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, if they truly underſtand it, and the liberty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt hath made us free.</p>
               <p>When he tells us, that he cannot be counted a wiſe man, that wilfully entertains ſeruples in his mind, and ſuffers himſelf to be influenc'd by them in his practice, we do not comprehend him, ſeeing ſcruples are fears of the mind, which vex the Conſcience, as a ſmall ſtone in the ſhooc doth hurt the foot; and are therefore ſins of weakneſs: if they be wilfully entertained, they are not ſcruples, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wickedneſs: ſo that we know neither wiſe man, nor fool, that will wilfully entertain any ſuch diſeaſes. But yet as wiſe men as himſelf, have had ſcruples, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who ſcrupled converſe with the Gentiles, <hi>Acts 10. Gal. 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Principle laid down, <hi>viz. That it's more agreeable to the Character of a truly wiſe man, so be ſcrupulouſly fearful of diſobeying, than obeying the commands of Authority;</hi> will hold good where the Authority is infallible, otherwiſe not: for we may as lawfully ſcruple, yea, deny obedience to their unjuſt commands, as to diſobey their lawful commands; and we find it agreed well with the character of the truly wiſe Apoſtles, to ſcruple obedience to the commands of Authority. It had been <hi>Ephraim</hi>'s wiſdom, not to have walkt willingly after the command of <hi>Jorohoam,</hi> for which he was broken in judgment. Shall we ſuppoſe the ſeven Biſhops put in the Tower, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to obey the late
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:188013:45"/>
King <hi>Ja</hi>'s Authority, were no wiſe men. Seeing therefore we owe no implicit obedience to any man, we ought to be as afraid of obeying unlawful, as diſobeying lawful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
               <p>Why he ſhou'd be ſurprized with the <hi>V</hi>'s aſſerting, that Non-Conformiſts have been both before and ever ſince the Revolution qualify'd with Civil Offices, we do not ſee: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had both Phyſical, Moral, and Civil Qualifications, and are not barr'd as yet by a Sacramental Teſt: but it ſeems the <hi>V.</hi> did forget that a Canonical qualification was neceſſary for being in any Civil Office. For there are, as he ſays, <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws, by which, tho Diſsenters be not wholly unqualify'd for admittance into Civil Offices, they are wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled for continuing in them.</hi> Tho this be poſſible, it ſeems not reaſonable, that any cauſe ſhou'd diſable a man to bear and execute an Office, which did not diſable him to enter in it, when the matter is known before. By this the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick Laws are like Decoy Ducks, which let in their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low creatures, and then catch them in the Net. But it ſeems Diſſenters muſt pay the thanks for all their Civil Offices, to the lenity of Eccleſiaſtical Governors, and not to the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Civil Magiſtrate, who ſeems to be as much <hi>ſub ferula</hi> of the Church as Diſſenters are; for tho they may give, they cannot make good their grants.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>D</hi>'s modeſty cou'd have allow'd him to ſuffer others to commend his Anſwer for its fulneſs, or had he been ſo patient, as to hear what could be ſaid againſt it, he wou'd not have ſo ſeverely reflected on the <hi>V.</hi> or boaſted of himſelf as he doth.</p>
               <p>That there might be a ſymetry in this defence, as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, ſo he ends with hard words, in which he taxeth the <hi>V. with undecent and profane ridiculing the firſt Conſtitution of the Apoſtles againſt eating of blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To accuſe any of ſo great Crimes without ſufficient proof, is rather reviling than reaſoning, which is ordinary
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:188013:46"/>
with men of ſtronger paſſions than reaſon, when they are not able to anſwer Arguments, they fall upon them and the Arguer, employing bantering as a <hi>ſuccedanium</hi> for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>His <hi>2d.</hi> Accuſation, that the <hi>V. unjuſtly and irreverently applyeth the words of our Saviour,</hi> Mat. 7. 10. <hi>to the celebrated Parl. of Ireland.</hi> We believe the Members of Parliament will not look on theſe words with the <hi>D</hi>'s eyes, but will rather conſider them as an alluſion, and that upon ſuppoſition that the Parliament ſhou'd give a toleration to Diſſenters clog'd with ſuch a Teſt; it wou'd be as giving a ſtone when bread is asked.</p>
               <p>To conclude, There are ſome reflections on the doctrine and practice of ſome Diſſenters occaſionally communicating with the Eſtabliſh't Church: where he obſerves the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of ſome of the <hi>V</hi>'s words, which we not being able to juſtify, leave to their Author to vindicate them, and will ingenuouſly acknowledge, with the Author of that Book called <hi>Vox Clamantis;</hi> which he cites, <hi>That ſuch Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts as upon occaſion to get into places of Honour, and Profit, will and can take all manner of Teſts that have been of late im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or can on ſuch occaſions take the Sacrament according to the form and way of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>tho they never did it before, and perhaps never intended it after, except on the like occaſion, are too juſtly ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oxious to be ſuſpected, as men of flexible and profligate Conſciences.</hi> But we are ſure the <hi>V.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to juſtify no ſuch perſons.</p>
               <p>Having now impartially conſider'd this Defence, we muſt tell him, that if he had borrow'd as much out of Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet's Irenicum,</hi> as he hath ſtolen out of his Unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of Separation, and given leſs credit to his Jacobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Pamphleteers in the affairs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he had better conſulted for his own reputation, and our eaſe and might have ſpar'd ſeveral reflections he too liberally beſtows on his Majeſty's Government in <hi>Scotland:</hi> but hereby he hath
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:188013:46"/>
given a Commentar upon the old Prelatick Maxim, <hi>No Biſhop, no King:</hi> that is, if Kings do not ſupport Biſhops, there ſhall be no Kings.</p>
               <p>But we wiſh that our Zeal may be better employ'd about things wherein the glory of God, the good of Souls, and the peace of the Church and State may be more concern'd, than either they enjoying their Ceremonies, or we our Civil Offices.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:188013:47"/>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:188013:47"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO A Peaceable &amp; Friendly Addreſs TO THE <hi>Non-Conformiſts, &amp;c,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALtho' the reaſonings of this Addreſs appear not to be ſo powerful, as to make us Schiſmaticks, and thereby uncapable of a <hi>Legal Toleration;</hi> yet, left our not pleading to ſuch an Indictment as is here drawn up againſt us, ſhou'd be conſtrued to flow from ſullenneſs, or conſcious of a weak and ill cauſe; we cannot but conſider them, and that either to prevent the Addreſſor's conceit of his Work, as if it were impregnable, or choler for looking on it as contemptible.</p>
            <p>If it be <hi>malum omen ceſpitare in limine,</hi> the Doctor hath ſnappered on a piece of diſingenuity in the very frontis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece; for what he calls a Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs to Non-Conformiſts, upon peruſal, appears to be a Libel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them as Schiſmaticks, and it's deſign to provoke the Civil Magiſtrate to keep us ſtill under the laſh of penal Laws for Non-Conformity; ſo that, as it is reported of a Poliſh Ambaſſador ſent to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> at his arrival, he pretended he came for Peace, but when he had his publick
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:188013:48"/>
Audience, he proclaimed War, whereupon the Queen ſaid, <hi>Heu quam decepta fui Legatum expectavi, Herauldum accept, I look'd for an Ambaſſador, but have receiv'd a Herauld;</hi> ſo when ye have rais'd our expectations with the name of a Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs, bring in an Accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, as guilty of a Crime (which if what Divines ſay of it be true) is no leſs than renting the myſtical Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and if this be your kindneſs to your friends and brethren, you muſt excuſe us if we be not fond of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>In your Epiſtle, ſeeing you flatter your ſelf with <hi>hopes of doing ſome good, and confidence of doing no hurt, by publiſhing this Addreſs, and that becauſe of the calmneſs and temper, ye have ſtuded in it, to prevent giving offence to your Non Conforming Brethren,</hi> as ye call them, we hope it will be no hurt to tell you, that the ſtudyed temper and calmneſs of your words, will not make an attonement for the diſtemper of its matter, and windy ſtorm and tempeſt thereby deſigned; for you miſtake your Non-Conforming brethren, if you think them ſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as not to be offended with good words and fair ſpeeches, <hi>whereby men lye in wait to deceive,</hi> and, <hi>tho' your words be ſmoother than butter,</hi> yet it is evident to us <hi>that war is in your heart,</hi> while ye <hi>caſt iniquity upon us,</hi> and were they <hi>ſofter than Oyl,</hi> we muſt look upon them as <hi>drawn Swords,</hi> while by them ye are ſtirring up thoſe, who bear not the <hi>Sword in vain</hi> to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it <hi>againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the large encomium you exalt your Patron with, as <hi>an eminent example of temper and moderation to Diſſenters, and that none was more mild and gentle to them than he, ev'n in thoſe times when it was in his power to uſe ſeverity towards them;</hi> we cannot but from experience of the contrary, <hi>diſſent</hi> from you in this, as well as in ſome other things: for Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts do remember, that they never met with greater ſeverity, at leaſt in the North, than when the Primate of all <hi>Ireland</hi> and Chancellor rode both upon one horſe; and we
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:188013:48"/>
adviſe you for his honour, and your own honeſty, not to put us upon the proof of it.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>that remarkable effect of his arguments and moderation that he obliged divers Non-Conforming Miniſters to receive Ordmation at his hands, according to the form preſcribed by your Church, and to conform to the Worſhip and Diſcipline thereof;</hi> if ſuch were ordained Miniſters before, tho' by Presbyters, you will find it hard to convince any of the Reformed Churches, or all of your own either that this was the proper effect of moderation, but rather of Prelatick Domination, and an uncharitable condemning of the forreign Reformed Churches as none, and their Miniſterial Adminiſtration as void and null, for want of Epiſcopal Ordination: and we fear that love of the world prevailed more powerfully than any other arguments, elſe it's hard to believe that conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Miniſters would have renounced their former Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which if they did, without a publick declaration of their former ſin, in unlawful invading the Miniſterial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and cheating the world by a pretended Adminiſtration of Sacraments, when they had no power ſo to do, as ye have not by them gained honeſt Miniſters, ſo we have loſt as few; and if this be the native fruit of his Moderation, we bleſs God that hath delivered us from it; and thus we ſhall apply our ſelves to the Addreſs it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It hath ever been the honour of <hi>Peace</hi> to be well ſpoken of by all men, <hi>Pacem le poſcimus omnes;</hi> but the unhappineſs of many men to be under the dominion of ſuch Luſts, as diſenable them to purſue it; that there are, and ſhall be diviſions among us we confeſs; but to convince the guilty of their Sin, is this <hi>hoc opus, hic labor eſt:</hi> ſeeing it is as rare to find men impartial as infallible.</p>
            <p>Conſidering what brevity I intend, I ſhall not catch all advantages I might take by ſome unneceſſary phraſes of this Addreſs, in which the Doctor rather catechiſeth the Non-Conformiſts, by asking queſtions, than convinceth them by
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:188013:49"/>
reaſons, proving his own, or diſproving their principles and practices; and tho ſome ſhort categorical anſwers of yea and nay might ſuffice, I ſhall give anſwer with a reaſon to it, tho not bound more than he, who gives none for his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. And, <hi>(1st)</hi> While he tell us that there is a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration between us, and thereby a Schiſm in our National Church, the conſequence is not good; for there may be a ſeparation without Schiſm, as there is between all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Churches which are locally ſeparate, without any Schiſm of your National Church. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, <hi>A&amp;s</hi> 15. 39. yet were no Schiſmaticks; and there may be Schiſms where there is no ſeparation of Churches, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>(2d)</hi> Before ye had (as with confidence ye do) aſſerted a Schiſm betwixt you and us, it had been requiſite that ye had proved that there was once an union in theſe things in which we divide, ſeeing all diviſion preſuppoſeth a prior union: if then we were never joyned in one, how can there be a diviſion? now I apprehend, it will puzzle you to prove, that the Presbyterians in the North ever joyned with the Eſtabliſh't Church in theſe things in which we now differ, to wit, Church-Government, Liturgy, and Ceremonies: therefore if you would ſuccesfully attack Diſſenters, you muſt not uſe the ſame Topicks for all; ſome you muſt prove Schiſmaticks tho they never joyned; others you muſt convince that there is a National Church, before you will be able to perſwade them that they have divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it.</p>
            <p>To your firſt Queſtion; <hi>Is there any of theſe things which are neceſſary to the ſalvation of a Chriſtian, wanting in the Communion of our Church? Do we not profeſs and teach the true Chriſtian Faith in all its Fundamental Articles?</hi> Anſwer, <hi>(1st.)</hi> Tho you may be ſo inured to officiate by Delegates, as to think we ſhould ſerve the Cure for you, we do not find our ſelves obliged to prove what you affirm, ſeeing the rule hath hitherto univerſally obtained <hi>affirmanti incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:188013:49"/>
probatio:</hi> It lies upon you to ſhew that your Church teacheth all the Fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and not on us, who are not bound <hi>to give the reaſon of the Faith that is in you:</hi> Chriſt and his Apoſtles proved their Doctrines, and left them not to be diſproved by Jews and Pagans, until they had firſt proved them. (2.) But in reverence to the antiquity of the queſtion, which is old Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick, I ſhall give it a Proteſtant's anſwer, which cannot be excepted againſt for Non-conformity, being the learned <hi>Chillingsworth</hi>'s in his Book, <hi>The Religion of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant the ſafe way to Salvation,</hi> in anſwer to a Papiſt who maintained the contrary. The Papiſt had put this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <q>Page 4. Parag. 14, 15. If the Roman Church did not fall into any Error that was damnable, how can it be damnable to live in her Communion? and if her Errors were not damnable, nor did exclude Salvation, how can they be excuſed from Schiſm who forſake her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To this <hi>Chillingworth</hi> anſwers, <hi>Page 16. All that we forſake in you, is the belief, profeſſion, and practice of your Errors;</hi> Hereupon you caſt us out of your Communion, and with a ſtrange contradictious and ridiculous confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence complain that we forſake it, as if a man ſhould thruſt his friend out of doors, and then be offended at his departure; but for us not to forſake the belief of your Errors, having diſcovered them to be Errors, was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and therefore to do ſo, could not be damnable, believing them to be Errors; not to forſake the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and practice of them, had been damnable hypocriſie: ſo that either you muſt free your Church from requiring the belief of any Error whatſoever, or whether you will or not, you muſt free us from Schiſm: for Schiſm there cannot be, unleſs we were obliged to continue in it. Man cannot be obliged by man, but to what he was formerly or virtually obliged by God. God, the eternal Truth, neither can nor will oblige us to believe any the moſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:188013:50"/>
innocent falſhood to be a divine truth, that is to err, nor to proſeſs a known Error, which is to lye; ſo that if ye require the belief of any Error, among the conditions of your Communion; our obligation to Communicate with you ceaſeth, and ſo the imputation of Schiſm to us vaniſheth to nothing; but lies heavy on you, for making our ſeparation neceſſary, by requiring unneceſſary and unlawful conditions of your Communion. Hereafter I therefore intreat you demand not, how came we to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your Communion without Schiſm, ſeeing ye err'd not damnably; but how could we ſo do, ſeeing ye err'd not at all? Which if either ye do prove, or we cannot diſprove, we will turn to your Communion, or ſubſcribe our ſelves Schiſmaticks: In the mean time let us continue as we are. Yet notwithſtanding of all your Errors, we do not renounce your Communion totally and abſolutely, but only leave Communicating with you in the practice and profeſſion of your Errors; the trial whereof, will be to propoſe ſome form of worſhipping God, taken wholly out of the Scriptures, and herein, if we refuſe to joyn with you, then, and not till then, let us be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as Schiſmaticks; ſo he whom the late Arch-Biſhop <hi>Tillotſon</hi> thought it an honour to be his Scholar.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To the next Queſtion; <hi>Is there any thing required by us from them that Communicate with us, that is a Sin?</hi> We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer affirmatively, there be things required, which to us are ſo.</p>
            <p>To the third Queſtion; <hi>Are there any of our Conſtitutions contrary to God's Law?</hi> We anſwer, to us it appears there be.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>4th; Hath God any where forbid us to uſe the ſign of the Croſs after Baptiſm, a Ring in the Celebration of Marriage, a Surplice in divine Service, the poſture of kneeling at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Lord's Supper, or any of thoſe Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which are appointed to be uſed among us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:188013:50"/>
Anſwer; Things are either forbidden expreſly, or by juſt and neceſſary conſequence: though then they be not expreſly by name forbidden, they be by good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: for whatever is not commanded by GOD, and is required by men as a part or means of the worſhip of God, is forbidden by God. <hi>(1st.)</hi> Then, whatever part or means of divine worſhip is not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is forbidden, is evident from that reaſon given, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. 1. Why God deſtroyed <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> for offering ſtrange fire, which is this, <hi>for I commanded them not.</hi> The reaſon of God's rejecting what was offered, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 12. is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> the cauſe of God's Judgments on falſe Prophets, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 14, 15. is, <hi>I ſent them not, neither have I commanded them.</hi> Fear or Worſhip of God taught by the commandments of men, is not only vain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 9. but brings plagues on them who abuſe their wiſdom that way, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 14. And we are lately taught this to be the doctrine of the Eſtabliſh't Church by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> in his <hi>Vanity of Humane Inventions, page 3. (1st.)</hi> ſaith he, <q>It belongs to God only, to give rules how he will be worſhipped, which is a truth naturally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in the minds of men, and univerſally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged at all times. (2.) The holy Scriptures contain the revelation of God's will concerning his own Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. (3.) It concerns us to keep as cloſe as we can to the directions which God hath been pleaſed to afford us, without adding to, omitting, or altering any thing that he hath therein laid down; for ſince God hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed us a certain and perfect direction for his Worſhip in the holy Scripture, it is to be ſuppoſed, that all ways of Worſhip are diſpleaſing to him, that are not expreſly contained or warranted by the examples of holy men mentioned therein. Now, if Croſs, Ring, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be not</q> expreſly contain'd in Scripture, or warranted by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of holy men therein, they muſt, according to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:188013:51"/>
of <hi>Derry</hi>'s reaſoning, be diſpleaſing to God, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by him.</p>
            <p>I know nothing that can be excepted againſt this, but that Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are neither required as parts, nor ways and means of Worſhip; but that they are required as ſuch, is evident. <hi>(1st.)</hi> The Liturgy or Divine Service, is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the Worſhip of God, and thoſe Ceremonies are a part of the Liturgy, therefore they are parts of the Worſhip of God; for <hi>quod eſt pars partis eſt pars totius. (2d.)</hi> That they are reputed ways and means of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is plain, becauſe no ſolemn publick Worſhip can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without them, no Sacraments given or received without croſſing or kneeling; yea, if all Miniſters ſhould refuſe to ſay Common Prayer, or Adminiſter Sacraments otherwiſe than preſcribed by the Common Prayer, that is, with all theſe Ceremonies; then, according to the Act of Uniformity, it would be unlawful to worſhip God publickly in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Hence, we ſee an Anſwer to his Queſtion, <hi>Can any thing be call'd a Sin which God hath not forbid?</hi> Anſwer, it may; for uncommanded Worſhip is Sin; to Baptize without the Sign of the Croſs, Communicate without Kneeling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not forbidden of God, and yet the Eſtabliſh't Church account theſe Sins; elſe why are men Impriſoned and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated for what is acknowledged to be no Sin; yea, puniſh't more ſeverely, than for ſome groſs immoralities, for which they are not excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> tho for Non-conformity they ought to be, according to the Canons. <hi>(2d.)</hi> Oil, Salt, Chriſm, Spittle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are no more forbidden than the Sign of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> why then hath the Church rejected them, they being lawful? The ſame Arguments are uſed by the Papiſts for all their Ceremonies; ſelling Doves, and changing Money, were not forbidden, yet Chriſt drove all out of the Temple.</p>
            <p>To vindicate your Ceremonies, you tell us, <hi>you place no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:188013:51"/>
in them. Anſwer,</hi> If they be not holy, they are not ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil nor natural Ceremonies, and therefore muſt be profane, nor doth your placing no holineſs in them, free them from Superſtition, if ye ſuper-add them as parts of Worſhip, to God's Statutes, while ye tell us, <hi>that ye only uſe them as things in themſelves indifferent, ordained by Humane Authority for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Order. Anſ.</hi> Tho' Ceremonies were indifferent in their Nature, yet they never can be ſo in their uſe, for as our actions are ſpecified good or evil by their ends, the end being good or evil, or neither, they in their uſe muſt be good, evil or idle and impertinent, and ſo can never be uſed as things indifferent. 2. Things indifferent being neither good or evil, can make nothing either better or worſe, for add nothing to ſomething, and it will be no bigger, ſo they can make nothing decent or orderly, ſeeing they have nothing of decency or order in them, elſe they were things really good, and not indifferent. (3.) Theſe Ceremonies muſt either be neceſſary means of decency and order, or not; if neceſſary they are not only not indifferent, but all worſhip perform'd without them hath been undecently and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly perform'd, and ſo Chriſt and his Apoſtles Baptized, Prayed and Communicated undecently, becauſe without Croſſes, Surplices, and Kneeling; if not neceſſary, why is all this needleſs contention for things confeſſedly unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>We confeſs with you, that Worſhip cannot be perform'd without circumſtances, and that all outward circumſtances of Worſhip are not expreſly preſcribed by God, yet we are fully pwerſwaded, that myſtical Rites and Ceremonies inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and impoſed by men, as terms of Communion with them, are not circumſtances, tho' craftily or ignorantly they be confounded; yet all men of reaſon know them not to be the ſame; for time, place, perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are circumſtances of humane actions but none can call them Rites or Ceremonies of actions; if they were, then Ceremonies ſhould be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:188013:52"/>
and not indifferent, ſeeing it is impoſſible to do any thing without ſuch circumſtances: We have often told you that ſuch natural circumſtances as are neceſſary for a decent and orderly performance of our actions, being included in the general Precept, we eſteem lawful; but ſuch myſtical Rites and Ceremonies as are not neceſſarily required to the performance of any of God's Commandments, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in any general Law of Chriſt, we judge addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to his Inſtitutions, and contrary to that Precept, <hi>Deut. 12. 2. What things ſoever I command you, obſerve to do it; thou ſhalt not add thereto, or diminiſh therefrom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing you humble your ſelf in deſiring us to teach you, <hi>how ye ſhall more effectually diſclaim all ſuperſtition in the uſe of them than ye do, and promiſe to confeſs your fault, if ye give us not ſatisfaction;</hi> we preſume to teach you a more effectual way, and that is, <hi>to diſclaim all uſe of them,</hi> and ſo you effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually diſclaim all ſuperſtitious abuſe of them; and herein we expect the ſatisfaction ye promiſe.</p>
            <p>When you have convinc'd us of that innocency of your Church wherein ye glory, you'll find it eaſy to induce us to joyn with you; but this you have not made convincingly appear among Non-Conformiſts, among whom we find you have met with two ſorts; <hi>(1st.)</hi> Such as judge Communion with the Eſtabliſh't Church abſolutely unlawful, theſe you tell, that their judgment is falſe, and apparently uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, unleſs they can ſhew that ſomething is wanting which God hath commanded, or required that he hath forbidden. Anſw. For ſuch, what is already ſaid, let it be conſidered, and then judge whether their judgment be falſe and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, though we know few that are for abſolute and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſeparation from you. (2.) A ſecond ſort of ſuch as doubt of the lawfulneſs of your Communion, to whom you offer your ſelf a <hi>ductor dubitantium,</hi> and after ſtating their Caſe, reſolve it: <hi>Their Caſe is, they doubt (that is are not well aſſured) whether it be lawful to conform; the reſolution
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:188013:52"/>
you propoſe, is, if they are not able by any means to clear their doubts, and ſatisfy their ſcruples, yet ſurely in ſuch a caſe, they ought to chooſe that way which is moſt free and ſafe from the danger of Sin.</hi> But we wou'd ask you, how a perſon that is not, as you ſay, by any means able to clear his doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which is the moſt ſafe way, ſhall chooſe the moſt ſafe way? this is to oblige men to impoſſibilities; for while one hath uſed all means to clear his doubts about which is the ſafeſt, and yet theſe continue, he cannot chooſe the ſafeſt, becauſe he knows it not; and if he chooſe without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, he acts neither as a Chriſtian, nor a reaſonable man, and ſo <hi>Cicero de Offic.</hi> tho' a Pagan, is in my mind a better Caſuiſt than you, who adviſeth <hi>quod dubitas aequum an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum ſit, ne feceris,</hi> what you doubt, whether it be juſt or unjuſt, do it not, and herein he agreeth with the Apoſtle, <hi>whatſoever is not of Faith, is Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But which is the ſafeſt way? to this, you ſay, 1. <hi>It's Evident we ſhould promote the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church. 2. Give Obedience to the Commands of Lawful Authority,</hi> Rom. 13. 1. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>But then it's only doubtful whether he ſhould conform to Ceremonies by Law Eſtabliſh'd; if then he cannot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſolid grounds ſatisfy himſelf, that ſuch Conformity is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> ſuch a doubt ought not to be put in the ballance with the aforeſaid Commands. <hi>Anſw.</hi> By your leave, ſuch a doubt may be put in the ballance with the fore-mentioned duties, ſeeing the ſame God, and the ſame Scripture hath told us, <hi>that he that doubteth is damned, if he cateth, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> Rom. 14. <hi>ult.</hi> Now, if we may not follow peace, or obey Superiors, except in Faith, for whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin, then to conform doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, either for peace, or in obedience to the Magiſtrate, is ſinful Conformity, as well as praying to God without Faith, is Sin, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1, 6, 7. Now a little more reaſon and divinity would have taught you, 1. That Negative Precepts bind <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> that is, can at no time, nor in no caſe, be broken
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:188013:53"/>
without ſin, but poſitive Precepts bind <hi>ſemper,</hi> that is, as Schoolmen ſay, they are ſtill obliging, tho' not at all times, as it is always a duty to pray, but not at all times. 2. A Rule againſt which there is no exception will over-ballance that which is limited by exceptions, for this Rule, <hi>what ſoever is not of Faith is ſin,</hi> is without exception. The other two Precepts are reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icted by it, as Rom. 12. 18. <hi>if it be poſſible as much as in you lyeth live peaceably with all Men;</hi> Here the Precept is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited as far as is poſſible with a good Conſcience, but we muſt not ſell peace with God, and our Conſciences to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it with Men: Our Obedience to Superiors is limited by lawfulneſs, poſſibilty, expedience and Edification. 3. If your Epiſcopal Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould doubt of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of ſubmitting to Presbytery now by Law Eſtabliſh't there, it ſeems by you they are bound to conform for peace, and in Obedience to Authority, notwithſtanding of their doubts; why don't you then Preach this Doctrine to them? or if a Man in <hi>France, Spain, Italy, &amp;c.</hi> were in doubt, and could by no means clear himſelf of theſe doubts, whether Popery or Proteſtaniſm were ſafeſt, by your Rule he is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be a Papiſt in obedience to Authority.</p>
            <p>To your Queſtion, <hi>why may not I ſay, he that doubteth is damn'd if he refuſe Conformity, rather than if he Conform.</hi> Anſ. Why doth not the Apoſtle ſay, he that doubteth is damned if he refuſe to eat, rather than if he eateth, ſuch a Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary as you make, would deſtroy the Text; for when a doubt is about doing, and not about omitting, the ſin muſt be in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not in omitting; ſo that all this Sophiſtry will not make v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id that good old Rule <hi>Cautiſſimi cujuſque praeceptum quoddubitas ne feceris,</hi> obey not the Precept of the moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, if ye do it. But by what Authority do you Addreſs theſe as Non-conformiſts, who ſo ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> betwixt two Opinions, as neither to follow God nor <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al?</hi> they are none of ours no more than they are yours, <hi>for he that gathereth not vith us ſcattereth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:188013:53"/>
To your Non-conformiſts Objection, to wit, <hi>to impoſe ſuch things upon us as are in themſelves indifferent, is an Infringe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> Gal. 5. 1. Your anſwer is, <hi>to impoſe the belief or practiſe of any thing as an eſſential part of Religion, and neceſſary to Salvation, which God hath not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly required, ſuch impoſing infringeth Chriſtian Liberty, and none elſe.</hi> Anſw. As you have not faithfully framed the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts Objection, ſo you have not fully anſwered that of your own framing; our objection is, that impoſing things in their own nature indifferent, either as parts or means of Worſhip, or conditions of our Communion in it, and ſo to determine our practice, as to deſtroy its indifferency in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or forbearing things indifferent, is at once to deſtroy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, and to infringe that Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and in which we are bound to ſtand faſt; for Chriſt having freed us from all parts and parcels of Worſhip which are not of his own Inſtitution, from all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or Communion with him and his Ordinances, but thoſe of his own preſcribing, ſo he hath allowed us the uſe of indifferent things indifferently, as Chriſtian Prudence and Charity ſhall determine; for any men to impoſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, is at the ſame time unjuſtly to invade Chriſt's Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and Chriſtians Priviledges, both which we judge our ſelves bound to maintain.</p>
            <p>Your Anſwer is not ſufficient to the Objection, even as your ſelf have framed it; <hi>viz. That only to impoſe the belief or practice of any thing as an eſſential part of Religion, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation, not particularly required of God, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement of Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> Anſw. Chriſtian Liberty may be infringed, tho the thing be not required as an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of Religion; for the main violation of Chriſtian Liberty lies in a fix't, ſtated and perpetual compulſion to do what God hath permitted me to omit, or a prohibition to do what he hath made lawful for me: thus the Apoſtle teacheth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>All things are lawful for me, but I will
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:188013:54"/>
not be brought under the power of any perſon or thing in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters indifferent;</hi> for ſuch a reſignation of my ſelf to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained fixedly, is to bind up my ſelf from opportunity of my uſing my Chriſtian Liberty for the ſpiritual good of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; for if I ſhould be ſo circumſtantial, that by forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an indifferent thing, ſuch as you call the Croſs in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, I might do good to my Neighbour's Soul, I am ſo tied, that I cannot forbear to prevent my Brother's ſinning, and ſo we cannot imitate the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Cor. 6. 13 Wherefore if meat make my Brother to offend, I will not eat fleſh while the world ſtandeth.</hi> (2) To ſubmit to ſuch predetermination, is to alter the very nature of things indifferent, by making that ſinful which God hath made lawful, contrary to your own doctrine, <hi>page</hi> 2. However unnec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſary or impertinent any thing may be eſteemed, yet nothing is to be look'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon as a Sin, but what is contrary to the Law of God. (3) By ſuch impoſing and determining in matters indifferent, more is attributed to the poſitive precepts of men, than to the moral Laws of God; for obedience to ſome poſitive moral Laws of God may be ſuſpended <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> to give way to a greater good; but in this caſe we muſt act uniformly, without reſpect to circumſtances, tho thouſands ſhou'd be offended; and wounded in Conſcience, and prejudiced againſt Religion thereby.</p>
            <p>But if we can make appear, that theſe Ceremonies, as impoſed by you, are made eſſential parts of Religion, and neceſſary to Salvation, then you muſt acknowledge them deſtructive of Chriſtian Liberty: This will appear, if it be conſidered, (1.) That if theſe Impoſitions be neceſſary in order to Communion with the Church, and Communion with the Church neceſſary to Salvation, then they muſt be neceſſary to Salvation, that they are made neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of our Communion with the Church, is evident by the Act of Uniformity, and your calling us all Schiſmaticks, who conform not to them. (2.) What is made neceſſary
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:188013:54"/>
to the Solemn Worſhip of God is made neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but ſo are they, ſeeing without them it cannot be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly performed in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> (3.) If the bare omiſſion of them, tho' out of tenderneſs of Conſcience be ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ged Schiſm, Sedition and Rebellion, and be made worthy of Fining, Impriſonment, and Excommunication. (4.) If for calling them unlawful, a man muſt be delivered to Satan, according to <hi>Can</hi> 6. (5) If the omiſſion of theſe, make a Miniſter more lyable to Deprivation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than Whoredom, Drunkenneſs, or breaking the Lord's day. (6.) If the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers of Conformity to them, be judged worſe than Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Papiſts? if they be more neceſſary than the Peace and Unity of the Church, with what confidence can any man ſay, that he judgeth them not neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p>That our Directory requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reth any Ceremonies of myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſignification, or impoſeth any indifferent things, ſave ſuch circumſtances as nature's Light and right Reaſon direct us to, for the decent and orderly performance of our duties, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and demand proof from all who aſſert it.</p>
            <p>Having juſtify'd, as you think, the nature of your Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, you proceed to vindicate their number, telling us, <hi>if we ſhould ſay, that your Ceremonies were too numerous and burthenſome,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if this were really ſo, it were only an inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and not a ſin.</hi> Anſ. God's word tells us, that to do what is not convenient is ſinful, <hi>Rom. 1. 28. Epheſ</hi> 5. 4. though to ſuffer things inconvenient is not ſtill ſo; and by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority can any burthen Conſciences with their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions? was not this the ſin of the Phariſees, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. 4. if <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complain'd as you ſay, of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and burthen of Ceremonies in his time, why may not Diſſenters do ſo now, who are as unable to bear them as he was? yet had he lived in ſome place of the World, and complain'd of ſuch a burthen, there is a Canon, called the 10th, by which he had been <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſhut out of the Church. But ye'll ſay, he did not ſeparate, tho' he complained.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:188013:55"/>
Anſw. How do ye know, that he did not ſeparate? if he refuſed to uſe them, he ſeparated from them as well as we do, and if he uſed them after his complaint of their being burthenſome and too numerous, it would be hard to excuſe him from ſinning againſt his confeſſion, but we have more Charity for him than to believe he did ſo.</p>
            <p>To your Non-Conformiſts laſt Objection, to wit, <hi>The Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are unneceſſary, and therefore the Governors of the Church are not to lay unneceſſary impoſitions on the People,</hi> Ye Anſwer thus, <hi>Tho' this were true, that Governors did impoſe ſuch things, yet our complyance therewith for Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſake, were no ſin, but a virtue.</hi> Anſw. That they are unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, you confeſs, while you declare them indifferent, and therefore the dubious ſuppoſition, <hi>if they were,</hi> &amp;c. is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but that it is a virtue rather than a ſin to comply with the unneceſſary impoſitions of Church Governors, for peace and unity, is aſſerted, not proved, ſeeing nothing can be a Chriſtian virtue, which wants Chriſt's Command, and we know of none he hath given for our complyance with Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors in their unneceſſary impoſitions: Yea, we find Church Governors obliged by their Commiſſion to teach us to obſerve no more than what Chriſt commanded them, <hi>Matth. 28. 20. Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you,</hi> and the good Centurian <hi>Cornelius</hi> would ſubmit no further to the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, Acts 10. 33. Now therefore are we all here preſent before God,</hi> to hear all things that <hi>are commanded thee of God,</hi> for ſeeing God and Nature do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in vain, they have no power to impoſe things needleſs, and where their power to command is void, we are under no Obligation to obey; yea, ſuch complyance is but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy with men uſurping power, and ſo partaking of their ſins, <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> to the face in his impoſing unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things on the Jews, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 11. And ſeeing the Church hath no Power but to Edification, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 8. We are to follow them no further than they follow Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:188013:55"/>
The Synod of <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15. guided by the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, thought fit to impoſe nothing but neceſſary things. Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi> page 101 of his Vindication, ſays, It was not the Erroneous opinions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the impoſing them by Law on other Churches, that warranted the ſeparation. So, when things unneceſſary are made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of our Communion, we look not upon it as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian virtue to comply with them.</p>
            <p>Having aſſerted, not only the lawfulneſs, but innocence of your Communion, <hi>you profeſs your ſelf aſſured that we do not think every man is at liberty, either to join himſelf with the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh't Church of a place, or to ſet up a diſtinct Church for himſelf.</hi> Anſw. Such as on good grounds judge your Communion lawful and innocent, will not ſet up for themſelves, but your aſſerting your ſelves ſuch, makes it not evident, ſeeing <hi>there is a generation, all whoſe ways are clean in their own eyes, tho they be not waſh'd from their iniquity;</hi> Therefore we ſay with Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable <hi>Hales</hi> of <hi>Eaton,</hi> page 194. <q>Notwithſtanding of the great benefit of Communion, in regard of divers Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers Men are ſubject to, Diſſention and Diſ-union are often neceſſary, for when either falſe or uncertain Concluſions are obtruded for truth, and acts either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful or miniſtring juſt ſcruple, are required of us to be performed by us, in thoſe caſes conſent were conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and open conteſtation is not Faction or Schiſm, but due Chriſtian animoſity: For tho' you value your ſelves</q> mightily on account of your legal eſtabliſhment, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed your moſt powerful argument, yet the aforeſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, page 231. ſays, <q>That publick Aſſemblys, though ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to form of Law, are indeed nothing elſe but Riots and Conventicles, if they be ſtain'd with Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Superſtition. A Legal Eſtabliſhment gives</q> protection and proviſion, but makes neither Doctrine true, Worſhip pure, or Government of Divine apponitment; and ſeeing it adds no intrinſick value to a Church, it can
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:188013:56"/>
merit nothing barely upon that account, elſe other Churches who have had a longer title to a Legal Eſtabliſhment than ye, might expect more honour.</p>
            <p>While you deſire to know <hi>whether one or more bare incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies which are or may be free from ſin, can be a ſufficient reaſon to ſeparate from an eſtabliſh't Church.</hi> Anſw. We tell you, that if the inconveniencies are ſinleſs, we are willing to ſuffer in and with an Eſtabliſh't Church, or tho' it were not Eſtabliſhed by Law; but if the inconveniencies be to our Conſciences, we muſt and will Diſſent, nor will our Charity bear with what is inconſiſtent with a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Such as found their ſeparation from your Aſſemblys upon this, that <hi>they find themſelves more edified in Godlineſs and Piety by their own Meetings than yours, ye confeſs your inability to find what reaſon they can ground upon this for a down-right ſeparation and utter refuſal of your Communion.</hi> Anſw. Tho' our edification in Godlineſs is the great end of our joyning with any Aſſembly, and where that may be beſt had, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is there moſt eligible; yet if we may be really edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Aſſembly whereof we are Members, we allow not ſeparation on pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of better elſewhere, no more than a Womans leaving her Husband to live with another for more pleaſure and conveniency. Yet Edification being the end of Church-Communion, no wiſe men ſhould condemn thoſe who chooſe the beſt means for that end: I ſuppoſe you make uſe of the beſt meat and medicines for preſerving of your life and health, and would take it ill, 'tis poſſible, if Governors of Church or State, ſhould confine you to the quantity, quality, and time of your Diet, which experience teaches you to be inconſiſtent with health and ſtrength; and why may not men be as much concern'd for their Souls as Bodies. Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> page 109. in anſwer to a queſtion diſputed by <hi>Grotius,</hi> to wit, whether it be in a time when Churches are divided, it be a Chriſtians duty to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with either Party that divides the Church, or to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:188013:56"/>
Communion from all of them; the Dr. ſays, that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, by virtue of his general obligation to Communion, is bound to adhere to that Church which retains moſt of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelick purity in it. <hi>Bramhall</hi> in his vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> page 7. cites Dr. <hi>Holden</hi> with appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation; <q>When there is a mutual diviſion of two parts, or member of the Myſtical Body of the Church one from the other; (yet both retain Communion with the univerſal Church) which for the moſt part ſprings from ſome doubtful opinion, or leſs neceſſary part of Divine Worſhip, whatſoever part you take, you are no Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, becauſe the univerſal Church hath condemn'd no part; ſo that real experience of edification will warrant</q> ſeparation from theſe Aſſemblies where it is not found, to theſe where it is found.</p>
            <p>To ſuch <hi>as plead for occaſional Communion, who do not utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renounce your Communion, but ſometimes come to your pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, and receive the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper after your form; your Queſtion upon this, is; If occaſional Communion be lawful, why is conſtant unlawful?</hi> Anſw. Altho I allow of no ſuch amphibious creatures as a Non and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt appears to be, becauſe as a Neuter in the Common-Wealth, <hi>nec amicum perit, nec inimicum pellit,</hi> ſo in Religion he is worſe, according to Chriſt's reaſoning, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 23. yet, if we diſtinguiſh occaſional Communion in total, and partial; total, I call a communicating in all, Sermons, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and Ceremonies; for ſuch I have nothing to ſay, and will not judge other mens Servants: but as for thoſe who can, and do occaſionally hear ſuch as are orthodox in the Faith, and ſober in their Converſation, as they do not deſpiſe others, ſo we do not judge them. But as for moſt of us, we are of your judgement, as to ſuch who commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with you occaſionally in all things, according to the form preſcribed; if they ſee no ſin in ſuch conformity, they are but fools to ſuffer for non conformity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:188013:57"/>
Having heard your Doctrine, we come now to its Uſe, in which you ingenuouſly diſcover your deſign, which is either to perſwade us to Conformity, or diſſwade us from thoughts of a legal toleration. As for your deſire to know <hi>our aims and purpoſes in reſpest to an Act of Toleration,</hi> tho we are not obliged to diſcover our thoughts to you, yet finding you a plain-dealing man in telling yours, we ſhall tell you ours, by ingenuouſly anſwering your Quaeries diſtinctly. To the firſt, to wit, <hi>Is it only to have the liberty of ſerving God in that way which you think to be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, and thereby to be free of perſecution, and to go the readieſt way to Heaven, as ye ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> To this, (1.) We confeſs we ſincerely deſire liberty to ſerve God according to that perfect rule he hath given us, which we firmly believe is the beſt way, and ſafeſt both for you and us both. (2.) We deſire by this, not only to be freed from perſecution, but that ye may free your ſelves from the guilt and appearance of that evil. (3.) Having bodies as well as ſouls, by which we are bound to glorify God, and ſerve our King and Countrey as we ſhall be called or capable, we deſire that we be not deprived of, or ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unfit for enjoying our birth-right-privileges as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Subjects, and perſons profeſſing the Reformed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, by yoking our Conſciences to unlawful or ſuſpected practices, or inſnaring Oaths. But ye tell us, <hi>If liberty to ſerve God the way we think beſt, be all we deſire, why are we againſt the Sacramental Teſt? by which we are made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of any Office or Employment, unleſs we Receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament after the form preſcribed by the Church of</hi> England: <hi>if we be not content with liberty, unleſs we have ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and be made capable of Employments of Power, Truſt, and Profit; 'tis apparent we deſign ſomewhat elſe than the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our ſouls, and freedom from perſecution.</hi> Anſw. Tho Non-Conformiſts ſhou'd aim at more than the ſaving of their ſouls, and freedom from perſecution, where is the great fault of it; if we be guilty in this, you are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:188013:57"/>
who we ſuppoſe aim at ſomething more than theſe things. I have already, in the Animadverſions ſhewn the inconſiſtency of the Teſt with the true intereſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which the Ingenuous Author of the Remarks on the Affairs of <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> hath well done: but it ſeems you have low thoughts of Salvation, who rate it lower than Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Truſt and Profit upon Earth; for that you ſeem to grant us liberty to ſeek, but the other is too good for us; and therefore you are either not in earneſt in permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us to ſeek the beſt way of Salvation, or elſe you over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value earthly honour and profit, while you would mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polize that to your party, and deprive others of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means of ſubſiſting, and ſerving God and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>2d</hi> Queſtion, <hi>if it be our aim to lay a foundation for the overthrow of the Eſtabliſh't Church, and to get into our hands all Civil and Eccleſiaſtic Power, which is already done by thoſe of our perſwaſion in another Kingdom. Ye confeſs ye were not wiſe if ye give us not all the oppoſition ye can.</hi> Anſw. That our deſign is not to overthrow any Church, is evident, becauſe we have not moved for the withdrawing either power or profit from you; all that is deſired, is, that we who have been, are, and may be uſeful to the Nation, may not be rendred uſeleſs; and ſure the Church may ſtand, tho' ſhe don't inhance all Offices of Power, Truſt, and Profit; theſe are not the Rock on which Chriſt built his Church. But is there no means to keep her from ruine but a Sacramental Teſt? how has ſhe been preſerved hitherto without it; experience hath taught us, that ſuch Engines have done more hurt than good to their contrivers; and therefore it were to be wiſh'd, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how deeply the Nations have been involv'd in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, they would be wiſer than to make <hi>ſnares wherein them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as well as others are caught.</hi> And now we come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider your Politicks; where firſt ye tell us, <hi>It becomes the wiſdom of every Government to conſider even the remote, if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:188013:58"/>
conſequences of what they do, and to ſet up two ſeveral Parties differing from each other in matters of Religion, to make Factions one againſt the other, and to ſtand in perpetual diſtinct oppoſition and competition one with the other, for all the places of Truſt, Power and Profit in the Common-Wealth, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve will be thought by moſt wiſe men, to be very impolitick.</hi> Anſw. If a State ſhould ſet up Parties for that end, no doubt they were out in the Politicks; but where is want of policy, in making perſons of equal merit, equally ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable? doth it not rather tend to the making of Factions, to let one party inhance all, while another equally deſerving is contemn'd and neglected: <hi>Jacob</hi>'s fondneſs of <hi>Joſeph</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got diviſions in the Family. (2.) This being but a remote probable conſequence, as you acknowledge, may as well not be as be, nor ſhould Magiſtrates be diſcouraged from making good Laws, for fear of remote conſequences. (3.) What extraordinary Factions are now made about ſuch Offices, tho' Diſſenters are not bar'd by this Teſt. In <hi>France</hi> the Proteſtants enjoy'd Civil Offices of Power and Profit by the Edict of <hi>Nants;</hi> and yet the French have been more out in their politicks ſince than before. And indeed Teſts will never prevent that evil in the State, no more than the Oath of Simony prevents competitions for Dignities in the Churches; but I am apprehenſive, that had the Church the ſole Power of diſpoſing all Civil Offices, you would be leſs afraid of Diſſenters coming into them, and for your jealouſie is, that they are not in hands who will diſpoſe of them right. The <hi>2d</hi> remote and probable conſequence is, <hi>That none knows but our Succeſſors in the next Generation may advance a little further than what is propoſed by their Predeceſſors in this: and ſince the Presbyterian party in theſe Kingdoms did in the late Wars, 1641. actually overthrow the Eſtabliſh't Epiſcopal Church, and have now again overturn'd the Epiſcopal Church in</hi> Scotland, <hi>ye have all the reaſon to fear, that tho' preſent N. Conf. keep a friendly correſpondence with you, animoſities may
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:188013:58"/>
probably ariſe betwixt Succeſſors, yours and ours, which if not carefully prevented may tend to the ruine perhaps of both Church and State; and ought not the Government to provide for poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as well as for the preſent Generation.</hi> Anſw. Tho' all this ſhould come to paſs, yet it is ſevere juſtice, to puniſh the Predeceſſors for the probable faults of the Succeſſors, not as yet committed; in hell there is more juſtice, where men are only puniſh't for real and by-paſt Crimes. But the reaſons you give for the probability of your Conſequence, to wit, <hi>that the Presbyterian party hath twice overthrown the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal,</hi> ye improve not well: It were then your Wiſdom with good advice to make War againſt them, for the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> policy was more ſucceſsful than <hi>Pharaoh's.</hi> However, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Teſt is but a ſlender defence, ſeeing it is well known, that the Scots Teſt did not preſerve Epiſcopacy there, nor all the Oaths in force before 1641, ſecure the Church, and therefore Chriſtian moderation, and a good Conſcience, will be better armour for the Church.</p>
            <p>But if we conſider the more near conſequences of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Toleration deſired, they will be found more certain and hurtful. (1) The weakening and diſcouraging of the great part of the moſt induſtrious profitable Subjects of the Kingdom, which will enſue, if this be deny'd, (2.) The alienating of the affections of all ſober men from Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are known to be the chief, if not ſole oppoſers of this deſire. (3.) If ever there ſhould be a neceſſity of uſing the ſervice of Non-Conformiſts, it would be impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to induce them to unite with theſe, who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of fair promiſes, in time of former trouble, have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully broken to them in time of Peace, and diſcover heart-enmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y againſt them.</p>
            <p>And now ſeeing you profeſs ſo great a Zeal for Peace and Unity, which you pretend to plead for, be as earneſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the bones of contention, elſe we cannot be perſwaded of your ſincerity; but there are a Sett of men who call to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:188013:59"/>
my remembrance, a Fool which King <hi>James</hi> the firſt had, when in <hi>Scotland,</hi> this fellow was pleaſant diverſion to the King, but being unhappily addicted to tipling, he was frequently abſent when deſired, whereupon the King, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright him from that practice, caus'd to erect a Gallows at the Bridge of <hi>Stirling,</hi> and bring forth a Quart of Ale, and ſet the ſame upon the ledge of the Bridge, telling him, that he muſt either throw the Ale in the River, or the King into the River, otherwiſe he muſt be hang'd; he after much howling &amp; many apologies, comes &amp; tells the King, that if he ſuffer'd hurt, he muſt blame himſelf for it, and therefore attempts to heave him over the Bridge, rather than part with his Ale. So ſome for all the affection pretended for Peace and Unity, will rather drown Peace than part with their Ceremonies. And thus I conclude, that there is no hurt done by this Anſwer to your Addreſs, elſe you were miſtaken in your confidence that it could do no hurt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
